Making rice koji starts by soaking rice in water.
Hi, I'm Nalase Akouji Maker from Japan.
After soaking overnight, dry it well and steam the rice.
Don't bore it. You have to steam it.
After about 45 minutes, when it's shiny and perfectly steamed,
sprinkle Koji's spores on top.
I'm using Tanikouji from Hishio-Ku in Kyoto.
This one is perfect for rice koji.
Mixed gently so the spores reach every single grain,
then wrap it in cross to keep it cozy.
To prevent drying, I put it in the container.
This Boston pizza box works surprisingly well.
Now, I'm going to make it at a warm temperature for about 48 hours.
This time, I'm using my DIY incubator.
Check out my other video for how to make it.
After 24 hours, transfer your baby koji to a bigger container.
Keep it around 30-45-45 degrees Celsius.
It will start to heat up naturally.
Mix it every few hours.
And the last 15 hours, just let it go.
Your koji will be ready around 48 hours.
It doesn't have to be super fluffy.
Enjoy the process.