.
of a larger impact.
Has I talked about this cross disciplinary collaboration is a central, but there's a couple,
there's two important kind of developments that are enabling on this cyborg or to happen.
One of these is just an increased accessibility of the equipment and the technology that we need to do by
on engineering of these organisms.
As this technology becomes more accessible or ability to utilize it in the food and
this tree is increased.
And then we also have an increased body of foundation and basic science research on
faster to a psoriasis, genetics, regulatory mechanisms, secret-tory mechanisms, epigenetic
regulation.
And as this body of foundational research, gurus or ability to kind of manipulate Koji in precise
ways and graces over time as well.
So what are the questions that I'm often asked is why aspiri does arise?
Because our company focuses primarily on Koji, on aspiri, do us our eyesay.
When there are a variety of organisms that are used both in traditional fermentation and in
the precision fermentation industry.
But there's several reasons that aspiri psoriasis is an ideal candidate for transforming
food products into ingredients and into additives.
Probably the most important is that the genetic sequence of psoriasis is enriched for
biosynthetic gene clusters that produce second-dairy metabolites.
And in particular, we're talking about hydrolytic and enzyme and amino acid, mitzatabolism
and amino acid sugar uptake transporters.
And as we'll see later on in the presentation, all of these are important when we're
using Koji to produce extra cellular products.
So products that are basically secreted by Koji into the extra cellular environment.
So traditionally, whether that's your psakey or amom psakey or your showy, whatever it is,
we rely on Koji to secret metabolites into the extra cellular environment.
And so the ability for Koji to do this is critical to the reason that it's ideally suited
for these types of applications.
And other key reason is it's hyphor growth.
This is talking about the way that Koji grows and permeates into interior of your substrate.
So the Koji will permeate through external walls of your substrate.
And actually deliver these extra cellular metabolites into your substrate.
And this is also critical.
And then additionally, it's tolerant to hyaluronic conditions.
Low water activity.
And these are just important for in fermentations, the ability of Koji to tolerate the environment.
Because we always have to remember.
And this is in any type of fermentation that these are living organisms that have
physiological constraints.
And so part of our concerns are always increasing the physiological tolerance of Koji so that it can
actually survive in our.
Formantations.
And we'll talk about this also a bit later.
And then the the other kind of important thing that he said suited for these applications is that it
does have USDA generally.
Rucking nice as safe status.
So essentially what this means is it allows us to get around a lot of the.
Regulations for using organisms in food production and it makes it significantly easier
to create products and get them out onto the market using.
So if Koji is such a perfectly suited.
Um, candidate for turning food.
Waste into other products.
Why engineer it like why do we need to go in and.
Mass with it if it's already suited to accomplish these types of tasks.
And the answer is that there's a variety of reasons.
Some of which are to optimize the processes that the organism is already doing and then others
or to enable it to do completely new things.
So as we'll talk about later, we can induce Koji to produce proteins and to produce heterologists.
But tabilights or metabolites that it doesn't usually produce.
Which can increase the types of things that we're able to use it.
For I'm so some of the specific things that we can.
Do by by engineering Koji already can increase the production of certain.
Let's tabilights and reduce the production of others and as we'll see.
Koji obviously is safe and.
Doesn't produce afloatoxins and.
It is safe for food.
Use.
But there are others second dairy metabolites that in some applications are.
This bill on the desirable or can potentially have harmful impacts.
And we'll talk about that.
I'll show a table on with some of what those particular.
Tom has are.
We can also just improve the ability for Koji to.
And we can also improve the ability to grow in difficult or specific conditions.
So as I'm sure you all know and have seen if you.
Made Koji at home there's certain.
Subst.
That it's significantly significantly better adapted to.
Grow in and some of the products that we are.
Tass with handling are not particularly easy for an un.
What if I just.
The rain on to.
Draw on and so what we can do is essentially help it.
Um adapt to these difficult conditions.
Um.
I see some interesting questions in the chat.
I will answer on in a second.
But thank you.
Those are super important questions.
And then um that I've talked about.
We can also induce had a logistic.
Session so expression of things that aren't.
Normally or in.
Theogenouslyx.
For us.
And then we can help to increase the consistency of.
Formatation which is especially important in an industrial setting.
So not just look briefly and be fully get into the engineering about some of the.
History of as for you.
Yo, it's a riser.
Research and I I am not an expert on the.
History.
Especially not expert on the cultural history.
There are people who have spoken in this conference that absolutely are.
I mean I would.
And.
Well, I is to.
Definitely.
Believe them over me, but.
This is.
Back to the origin is in the.
16th century in China as a.
The polyam.
Like.
Corobial.
Format.
So in a community with several other organisms, several other.
Fishes.
And then at some point between the 10th century.
B.C. and third century AD,
was imported over to.
Tip.
Pan alongside the idea of solids.
Date.
Formatation.
So fermentation on a solid subs.
Drey.
And then after the arrival in.
Pan, it was culture.
In traditional and our.
Tisital fermentation practices.
Using ash and using.
What ash, which is an incredibly.
Interesting development because this is at a time that pre dates are understanding of.
During theory and it predates past door and.
Go.
And essentially.
Without having an understanding of the biological mechanisms of play, they were.
Using the ash as an anti a mycrobial agent to prevent contamination of the.
Goji and to allow it to be cultured in a.
Cleaner single organism isolate, which is incredibly interesting.
And then 1876 is the.
First.
Laboratory isolation in the 2005.
We have the first sequencing for any of my technical people.
This was a shot.
Gone hold genome sequence.
There's been other higher resolution.
I'm sequence as sense, but.
This was of the R. I. B.
40s.
The reign of aspirin.
DOS arising and it was done in 2005.
And so to this day, the R. I. B. 40 serves as our.
For reference, genome a lot of time, so it's the genome that we have the.
Most amount of information about.
But since 2005, there have obviously been a.
Large amount of other sequencing efforts.
In different areas.
Using all different types of approaches.
And so what we can see by looking at the genetic sequence of.
Um, gas for go a surrisa is that there is a.
Ninety nine point eight percent sequence similarity between a orrisa and a.
The phoenix and a phoenix is a.
Food pathogen it produces afflits.
Toxins which are um toxic to humans.
And it is um something that in the.
Food and just three there is considerable effort to.
But contamination of food.
Quaith aspirin.
Kill us.
Flavis.
So this is super interesting.
There's 99.8 percent similarity between an organism that is.
Use an intentionally aoculated into.
Food and an organism that is purposely.
It's diluted on and what um.
Genetic.
Fologine has determined.
Is that the separation of aspirin.
So let's.
Flavis an aspirin kill us a rise a happened um.
Right at the same time that we first see aspirin kill us a rise a being intentionally.
Used for.
Food.
Production and.
What we believe this means is that actually aspirin.
There was a rising is a result of human selection of.
Human domestic.
Tation for and.
Dustrily.
The desirable.
Attributes so for the ability to produce and.
Zymes and do.
Her produced products that have an industrial importance um.
And I think this is super interesting.
And so we've talked a little bit about.
aspirin kill us a rise a overall how it's suited to be.
Used to help tackle the.
Food.
Wease problem and then a little bit just touching on the.
Evolutionary.
Um.
Pass in the evolutionary history of it.
And so now I'm going to go a little bit into how we actually um.
Engineer and the different types of approaches that we're able to use.
And before I go into this, I want to just answer um.
One of the questions in the chat on this talking about.
Well, our.
Darranes of aspirin kill us a rise a be.
Toppy r.
Rided and I think this is a super important question.
And I'm happy that you asked it because.
There is a comment practice in the violence.
Tag industry of patenting sequences of patting.
Genetic sequences as a practice symbiote.
Has not patting did any sequences.
We.
Um.
The.
Bellap or systems as intellectual.
Properties so are systems of.
Formatation and processing.
Um.
With different parameters different.
Bios.
We act or can.
Dissons.
This is our intellectual property.
We don't actively patent the.
Darranes because I believe that they're singing.
Um.
Nith again, ethical.
Um, consideration of the significant potential issues that come into play.
When we do.
Didn't patent him for a biological data.
Um, and.
You know, it's definitely something that we can talk more about.
Um, but.
Thank you.
For asking.
That as a question.
So let's go into the study of.
Formatted foods and this is just kind of a.
Brief overview of some of the.
Different tools that we can.
You use an essentially there's two.
Different approaches that we can take to understand.
What's happening in your.
Miso or your.
Kim.
She or your.
I'm a.
Zaki.
So we can either start with a.
And.
Genomic approach or much.
Tableomic approach.
And so for a.
Genomic approach will be.
Again, by directing.
The DNA or RNA sequencing and then doing.
Functional and.
Compositional analysis.
So what we're trying to understand is how the.
Genetics of the organisms and the.
The sequences of the organisms are connected to the.
Compounds that are.
Produce and so when we start with the sequences, we can do.
Bio and.
Formatic analysis and then we can use coffee.
Tational approaches to predict.
The flavor compounds based on the.
DNA sequence and so.
So.
With genomic approaches, we start with the DNA and then.
Project the flavor compounds based on the sequence.
A different approach that we can take as a.
Tableomic approach and so for these approaches will start with.
The.
Desk chromatography, which is essentially.
Alives us to separate the.
Different.
Comp pounds based on the.
Molecular.
Wait or their size.
And then I identify chemically.
And then we can see what compounds are.
Project can so for a metatolomic approach instead of starting with the sequence or instead of starting.
With the DNA, we start with the.
Chemical compounds that are.
Produce and starting with these compounds, we can.
Then attempt to correlate.
The genetics or the predicted genetics to the.
flavor compounds that we were able to detect through.
Deep CMS and the reality of it is we usually use these two approaches.
Simultaneously and so this allows us to have a more comprehensive understanding of how the sequences are connected to the.
Comp pounds produced and then we can use these.
Troises to.
Guide or selection of.
Darders and to guide or engineering of.
Ania riser.
So our.
Goals of this type of.
Dutty and of this type of.
Monipulation are initially to understand.
What the.
metabolic and enzymatic path.
Or that are active in our product and that are producing the.
flavors that are able to be detected in the end.
Product and then something else that we're able to.
Look at is the interactions between.
Different organisms and how.
These impact the production of.
Polar avoid in the end.
Product and then after we have an understanding.
We can move into optimizing.
The organism so optimizing the.
Goji that's actually acting in the.
format so we can look at regulation.
Of the.
The video production which are essentially the.
Bores of the code you there.
Use as a.
Darder and we can optimize the production of.
Second.
Tabelites and then we could also optimize the production of homologous and heterologous.
Protein so homologous.
Protein are proteins that ask.
Gelus a riser.
Um.
Produces already.
Without any genetic alteration and then heterologous.
Our proteins that we actually.
Um.
Our.
In.
Loosing it to produce.
Theroed.
Tonetic alteration.
And then there's some different.
Mechanisms that we can.
Um.
Monipulate to increase.
Protein.
So by.
By playing around with the.
But.
Parational.
Proteus and.
Um.
By the basic we.
Fusing these heterologous proteins to.
Carriers.
Um to aid in its success.
For extra cellular.
So.
Dreshen.
So um.
Next I'm going to talk about some of the potential.
targets that we can aim to produce.
Through these.
Genetic engineering approaches and through these optimization of.
Proteus and so.
This chart here is just talking about some of the.
Second.
Dairy metabolites that are produced by aspirin.
Dose riser and as you can see, there's a.
Or I.
Um.
Of.
Different bio ag activities here.
And so.
Depending on our desired.
Um, we can either in.
Rich the expression of them.
Tablight or we can.
Reduce or rep.
Press the.
Russian on the tabloid.
Other potential targets are.
And.
So the biggest industrial.
Views of.
Coji today is in the production of and.
And then the majority of it is.
Proteases so either alkaline proteases or other.
Neutral pup proteases.
Um that's about 60% of the industrial.
Production that.
Muses aspirin.
Gill a sorriser and these type of.
Range of applications in.
Food and in other industries.
We can also.
Um.
Produce amolases we can produce alpha amolasing.
Galuco amolase that takes.
Darches and essentially.
Gill leave the.
Darches at specific points on in order to produce.
Um simpler sugars.
Um there's also.
Corolla and no.
Pop today says.
These are specific for the production.
Or.
For the.
Dig justion of proteins with high amounts of.
Broling and so especially for.
Galuten intolerance there's the potential that these.
Um and no peptidases can be used as a.
Therap.
Pudic.
Inter intention as well.
And yes, absolutely examples of.
Applications the alpha amolases and.
Galuco amolases are.
Use to produce sugars so it's.
Especially in.
Um the.
Corn and this.
Um.
Dry either use in the production of.
Serums of a high.
Fructose corn syrup of other.
Serums.
Um proteases are.
Using.
Cleaning agents and soaps and.
Durgents.
Um there's some other applications also here on the next slide.
Some of the other potential targets.
Um as far as enzymes.
Cellulases.
Um cellulases convert cellulose into sugar into.
Galucos.
I'm so these are used in a variety of industries including in our own in.
And then there's a variety of other.
And.
Zymes that I'm.
Log.
Go to specifically into, but they have a variety of different.
Mechanisms and applications.
Um.
Dax will talk.
Or briefly about the different approaches to.
Genetic.
Moleculation.
Um there's basically three.
Duranages or three types of.
Proaches.
I'm the.
First is the view selection.
Barkers.
So um this is a traditional approach.
Um that's been used for a long.
Time to select for.
Duranages of organisms.
That produce.
Certain second.
Dairy-med tablets.
Traditionally these are.
The types of selection markers that are.
Use are antibiotic.
Resistance which we can absolutely not use.
All in any of our organisms.
Partially because it's illegal.
And partially because there's potential.
Rendasm.
Biological and safety implications.
But we are able to use Oxford.
Trophic markers.
So basically taking us.
Duran of.
Koji engineering it so that it.
Cannot produce all the essential.
No transcendent that it needs in order to sort of.
vibe and then.
Using that to select for.
Duranages that have.
Succeeds.
Up.
Taking amute.
Tation or have.
Sess fully incorporated the.
Dyer alteration in.
To issue.
Diram.
So there is a potential for the use of.
Autot.
Drophic.
Mutants.
However in our personal practice it.
Isn't something that we.
Use super often because the production of.
Autot.
Trophic.
Mutants.
Um.
Is a bit of a slower.
Process.
I mean it isn't as high.
Presolution as some of these other techniques.
Um.
The other.
Uh.
Kind of.
Cata.
Glory of approaches are.
Um.
These.
Trans.
Form.
M.
Um.
That are essentially taking a.
Genetic sequence and inserting it.
Be a traditional.
Um.
M.
mechanism into the.
Um.
As for.
Gila Suraise.
Um.
And there's a couple different.
M.
Here.
Um.
We don't typically.
Use them as often.
Um.
Because of some.
Difficult.
Coaties.
Um.
That.
Make them a bit harder to.
Use and.
The.
efficacy isn't as high as.
Um.
These other.
Genetic.
Malipulation.
So the.
Genetic.
Malipulation that I'm going to focus on are these.
Interspecies.
Be she's recombination.
The.
Gen silencing be a RNA.
I and then this.
CRISPR or task.
Nine alteration.
And so these are.
Um.
Genetic.
Tools that can operate at a bit higher.
Um.
Resolution and that have higher success.
I'm especially with.
Um.
Asper.
Gilles arising.
Um.
So at a very high level.
Level what these.
Genetic.
Monopulations are.
Doing is we're taking the DNA.
Um.
Asper.
Gilles arising work.
Making a slice in it.
In inserting a specific.
Section of DNA that we're interested in or we're in.
Dozing a shift in the DNA that's already.
There.
So we're either taking a.
Um.
Basically a new segment and inserting it or we're.
Cutting the DNA to.
Take out.
Part that's.
There already.
So either inserting or.
Taking out.
Um, and there's essentially two.
Um, approaches that we can.
Use to do this.
This is either.
CRISPR.
Um, which I'm sure.
You probably heard of.
Um, it's very.
Common.
Um, in.
By only hearing and then.
Talons which are.
Um, essentially.
Um, and.
Zymes that we can.
Use to.
Um.
Caught in section.
Parts of the sequence.
So I'm.
Not going to go into the specific.
Mechanisms here at all.
Um, because there's a lot.
Um, there's a lot here.
I'm in a lot of.
Different.
Um, approaches.
But essentially.
CRISPR.
Cast nine is a commonly used technique in bioengineering to edit.
DNA.
And it allows us to be.
Very specific and very precise about the area of the.
Coge DNA that we're editing and it allows us to avoid off.
Target of.
Facts or to a.
Boy kind of unintended alterations that also allows us to do.
Modifications of multiple genes,
Simon.
Canus, we, which is extremely helpful in improving this.
Beed and efficiency of our.
Plosies that also.
Doesn't require us to have an auto.
The.
Trophic.
Newton.
So it doesn't allow us to have us.
Or it.
Sorry, it doesn't.
Require us to have a strain of cogey that isn't able to produce all of its own.
New trends in order to.
Do this engineering.
Um, so basically CRISPR cast nine at a.
Very high level allows us to do specific targeted.
Removal or insertion of a DNA sequence in.
Goji and answered.
Goa so rise.
So this is an example from an excellent paper on published in.
20.
20 one of a.
CRISPR.
Deletion and insertion.
So we're basically taking this original.
Gourine.
Colony here and we're.
Deleting a segment to restore.
And a.
Um, I.
But I know.
Mutants and we're inserting a segment that results in a yellow.
Mutants.
So this is just a very simple example of how.
CRISPR can be used to make these extremely interesting.
Extremely.
Powerful alterations.
So the next thing I'm going to talk about nine.
I know I'm almost at my time here.
Eric, but I'm going to talk about the applications of.
As for geosurizing to the challenges that.
We are currently having because we've talked about the.
reasons that aspirin.
Theosurizing is perfectly suited to tackle your challenges and the.
Different approaches that we can.
Use to help it be even.
Better adapted and to expand the.
Capable.
Buildies to handle.
Different types of.
What is but.
Next we're going to talk about how.
These can actually be applied to.
Food.
Waste and how it can be applied to practical applications.
So there are a incredible variety of.
Potential applications of genetically older genetically.
Mm.
A lot of.
Five.
Coji and I'm just going to talk to on a.
Couple of them and then I'm going to talk about.
One of our own systems.
Just as an example.
So alternative protein production isn't the area that.
Symbios specializes in, but it isn't incredibly important area in an area that's.
Seating a lot of attention.
And a lot of investment.
Recently.
And so there's two companies.
Forma which is producing a.
Dairy analog so they're producing.
Jesus.
Yogurt using.
Goji and using a genetically altered version of Koji that can produce.
Analogous.
Proteins to.
Those in dairy.
And then there's a company called.
Prime.
Roots which is a new.
Startup that is using Koji to produce.
Dairy.
Meat.
Analogs without any animals or without the.
Use of any animal.
Agre.
Culture and so this is an important area for.
Reducing and.
By our.
Metal impact and there's a lot of interesting.
Solutions happening here.
And one of the ways that symbiote is helping to collaborate with the alternative.
Protein industry is looking at ways that we can.
Use food.
Access and food.
Place as subs.
Durates.
For the production of alternative.
Proteins because even alternative protein products.
Um have an environmental impact based on the product that they.
Use as a subs.
Durate and um so using these alternative.
Feeds.
Docks um either pusks or um.
You know other type of.
By products has significant potential to help.
Make these products even.
More ecologically sustainable.
Let me get a simple water here.
Okay and then um.
Functional food.
They're also an interesting area.
Um so there's a lot of.
Research I think as.
Bernard is um saying in the chat about like potential.
Functional or mid.
Disinal applications and this is a huge area of.
Research about how we can use um engineer coge to.
Produce um functional food items um and um items with certain health attributes.
And I'm not going to go to deeply into that but there's.
There's a huge amount of interesting um.
Dough happening in that area and then obviously super exciting from those of us who are.
Chaps or who are um.
Coax at home is that these types of engineering.
Opens of the opportunity for.
Targeted and specific.
flavor engineering in ways that we haven't seen before.
And then the production of different flavor.
Pro.
Files from.
Foods um and it's a.
tremendously interesting area as well.
So I'm going to just give a brief example of.
One of our system so this is a system that takes access.
Go from a bakery and uses.
Coge as to geosarize and a different um.
Forganism um in coordination to produce an enzymatic solution that can.
Forced the go into um sugars and into a specific combination of.
And enzymes and sugars that actually increase the shelf life and the.
Coeration of the.
Gerad products and so the idea is that by implementing this system the bakery can take.
Third access though and convert it into.
A sugar and end of the solution that when added back in can improve shelf life and improve the actual.
Sensory after the.
Views of the dough and so this is just kind of an example of.
One of the types of systems and all of this.
dough that's being input into the system was previously um.
Just pulled.
To a land.
So they didn't get any additional.
Any additional.
Value out of it and so this from these thing that's super exciting is that out of a product that had previously.
been both an economic and a.
And fire.
Until issue we can create a product is actually improving.
The.
Production system.
And so super briefly I'm going to talk about a couple.
I'd be.
To do a netic approaches again.
This is just going to be very high kind of surface.
But I'll be happy to talk or answer any additional.
Questions.
So happy.
genetics is basically the changes in the expression of.
genes without altering the DNA sequence.
And so for those of us who are.
Producing cogea home or in a commercial.
What come a personal application that.
Don't in necessarily have a lab or don't necessarily have the ability to actually engineer the
organisms.
We can.
Labridge epigenetics to shift how the cogey.
Gros the types of enzymes that it creates in the types of second.
Dairy metabolites that it creates.
And so without doing any actual engineering.
We can influence the type of activity that the organisms have in.
So three kind of critical things to think about are the conditions of incubation.
So we're looking at solinity.
We're looking at.
Water activity or the amount of act of water in the subs.
The rate obviously temperature.
Oxygen.
And the other conditions of an accumulation.
Then we can look at selecting.
Terrain of cogey that are either.
The rad or selected for specific applications.
So the cogey gene producers offer.
Often times of variety of types that produce higher amolese or higher.
Brodias and but by selecting us.
Drain this suited to.
Your application.
You can achieve drastically.
Different.
Andre.
So even if.
You don't actually alter the organisms itself.
And then the last thing to think about is the characteristics of the subs.
The rate that you're inoculating.
So the amount of nutrients.
The amount of.
Different chemical compounds present in the substrate.
If you can get a better idea of.
What is present in your substrate.
You can be.
Into particular.
Dict.
How cogey will.
React and how it will.
reproduce.
And so just as any sample.
I'm going to pull from this awesome.
Paper that was published.
Recently by a team at the.
Mask.
Coiner at the to and by.
I'm.
Pia.
Sorenson who's at Harvard.
And basically they use.
Cogey was.
bent up cycle.
Grain to per.
Duce.
Miso and what they.
Found is that by simply alter it.
Altering the pH deal.
Water activity.
And this specific composition of the subs.
The rate they were able to.
Dramaticly change the.
And sensory.
Attributes.
And so if they're interested into these type of at home.
Appied.
Dramatic approaches.
I think this paper isn't.
Excellent kind of hopping off.
Point because it isn't.
Terribly technical.
And it offers some super kind of simple things that you can alter at home.
It's a kind of.
Get a different.
And.
Re-sold.
And I believe that's all I have.
I see some.
Things in the chat.
But I think that's all I have.
I'll be happy to answer any questions that anyone has.
Hopefully it was in two.
Two hard for people to understand.
I was trying.
It's always hard to kind of.
Balance beats.
Queen.
Giving enough technical information while still keeping it easy to understand.
Thank you everyone and I'll be happy to answer anything.
And that was so cool.
That was awesome.
Just want to throw this up there hard to go.
There we go.
Want to throw that up there as well.
Awesome tossing that up there too.
All right so.
There are.
There were.
I do want to touch on this question from earlier.
So this is from Lou.
Yeah.
So look to know about any experiments that you've done to test like what the lowest protein
substrate that asked for you to realize that I can grow on.
Yeah so the easy answer is it depends.
There isn't really a simple kind of.
To lose some answer that we've been able to come up with.
But what we have found is that by supplementing with other
nutrients it's able to grow at a lower protein.
But it's also depending on the.
Drain and on a lot of other.
Factors but it is something I'm hoping to kind of.
Look at obviously depending on the.
Temperature also can impact the.
It's.
Topalism so obviously if the subs.
Dure has a smaller amount of.
Protein you can do it at a.
Forward.
Temperature to basically increase the amount of.
Amalase and.
That could have an impact but yeah I don't have an easy answer.
Okay and that I'm actually that sort of ties.
And this one not more just like a comet.
Yeah but yeah protein levels are low when you don't have like a hot summer.
Lower temperamentation seems like a awesome solution to that.
Yeah absolutely and.
Definitely if if any one is interested in talking.
Or about any of these slides or any.
Questions or anything just.
Go to our site or shoot me an email.
And I'll be happy to answer.
Gosh I awesome appreciate that.
Okay so I had a couple questions.
Yeah.
So my first one.
So what parts of like the food sector do you think have the most potential for reducing their food
way? So like restaurants, grocery stores, farms like.
Yeah you think that can be seen the most.
So that's actually.
Question in in the stuff that we do we work primarily with.
Agre cultural companies and food manufacturers.
Simply because at those pages in the production process, the.
Access that's produced is easier to handle.
It isn't can.
Daminated.
Whereas in like a direct to consumer or in like a consumer.
Facing business.
Sometimes we can have issues with can.
Tamination.
But yeah that's sort of got us sweet.
And then.
All right I'm trying to think of which question to ask next.
All right.
Can you so are you like.
I'm I'm not combined news to you question.
So what experiments like are you in the team like currently working on?
And then to sort of like follow that like what those your day to day look like how
often you like in the lab versus like your team and the lab and you doing like the business stuff
behind your business.
Yeah well to answer the.
First part.
Or actually okay I would.
Like to be in the lab every day I'm not.
But ideally I would only be in the lab but unfortunately I also have a company I need to run.
But I I do about half and half.
And I don't mean I like all but it's all amazing.
It's such an amazing opportunity to.
Or work in this sector.
But yeah it's about half and half and then as.
For is the the projects that we're currently doing I have.
Here's some.
Cocoa husk out see if I can you know put some that my hand and I'll bring it up onto.
Green it's like basically the husk from the Coco beans.
And it makes up about 20% of the actual.
So being that shipped.
And so it it adds up and so what we've been looking at is how to use.
Coge to can.
Brought it into um sugars and.
Use coge to interact the antioxidant out of it so that we can create antioxidant.
But averages and antioxidant additives because actually these Cocoa husks have.
A lot of potential health.
Health impacts because they can.
Pain higher amounts of a lot of the.
Functional compounds.
Then the actual.
Droke with self and so if we can.
Use coge to.
To enable the.
Biowab absorption of these.
Compounds there's a lot of interesting.
Dapplic.
Cations.
I'm so that's a project that we've been.
Working on we we also.
Work with a citrus.
Farm and we've been looking at ways of using the.
Peel of the citrus because obviously there's a lot of.
The fact in and and.
Coge can actually miss.
Tavilize.
Pectin and so we've been looking at how to.
Release the aroma.
Compounds out of the.
Peel for.
Coge.
So those are just.
Two of them but we've kind of been.
Doing things in all areas.
And if anybody here has any interesting issues that they're having.
I would love to hear about it even if it isn't something that simply can help.
I would love to hear.
So just shoot me an email if you go to our site.
It's easy to just send us an email on there.
Yeah.
Simply.
I see perfect.
Yeah.
Awesome.
I'm just going to scroll through our comments.
Make sure I didn't miss anything.
But Elliot, thank you so much.
This is such a great clock.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Thanks everyone that showed up and obviously.
I'm going to put in the science section of the.
This go word, I'll put some other um.
papers.
I'm in some.
Re sources.
The European.
Me so that's the two also has an excellent um selection of.
papers.
I mean, you go to their site.
They have a lot um there but I'll throw some also in the science area.
Gotcha.
Appreciate that.
Thank you so much, Elliot.
Perfect.
It's a great way to end our afternoon today.
Yeah.
Cool.
Well, thanks everyone.
Awesome.
All right.
So um.
Wow.
It's interesting.
Question and let's chat.
That one just can't be heard about the the.
Negative input.
Cation of the.
Right now, the I actually.
Thank you for asking.
This is something that I had in.
Pended to.
Touch on.
Yes, there are potential.
Negative implications and that's part of the reason that.
We have been super a.
And.
Gurazo v.
Biowefics.
And in our biowefics.
Policy for the company.
Because any type of tech.
The technology that handles the alteration of the N.A.
The alteration of.
Toonetic, but.
Terial has the potential to have unintended.
Negative impacts.
And so the control of our organism, the intentional.
Testing of our organism is critically important.
And so if you go to our site, you can see our of a.
Biowefics.
Policy.
But it's incredibly important to us that not only our organism.
Safe for human.
Food, but that we.
Done comprehensive.
Testing of any puts.
Tensual impacts in the environment potential ecological impacts.
Be for an organism is implemented into a commercial system.
It's super important.
And if anyone here is a.
Biowefics.
We're currently.
Looking to a higher of.
Biowefics as an advisor.
So if anyone has any.
Body that.
They know I'm just sending them our.
But super important and something that's always on our mind.
Awesome.
Yeah, with all so much things with technology nowadays.
Yeah, I'm sure everything is safe without us really important.
Absolutely.
Oh, I do see one other question come in.
Do you have time to answer one more question?
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay, so do you.
Epigenetic effects explain why things can taste different when made in different places.
So this is basically like the science behind Terwar.
Yes.
Um, I don't like.
Terri or as an idea for a lot of reasons.
Um.
But yes, the epigenetic effects is essentially is what people talk about as.
Terri or it's a component of it.
There are other things that can come.
Terribute.
But yes, I mean, if you make the same.
I'm a.
Zake with the same.
Koji and the same.
In.
Gouridians in two different places with different human.
Medidi different.
Temperature different amounts of air.
Clothe that absolutely.
These are the kind of epigenetic alterations I was.
Touching on earlier.
Gosh, I sweet.
Thank you.
And just to throw this up there as well.
All right.
Elliot, thank you so much for joining us this afternoon.
I really appreciate that.
Absolutely.
Thank you for having me.
All right.
Um, so we'll wrap up for the afternoon.
I'm just going to remove you from the stream.
Um, and then I'll do our all wrap up.
Cool.
Thanks everyone.
All righty folks, another great day of Koji.
45 and down the wall 25 to get three hours at a.
I hope work.
We're all ready.
We're going to put a great day under the.
We're going to right as we can keep playing.
But the whole day with the
I would begin with it with the turn of.
Android Parker and how will you for a presentation called
Framitation for Mental Health,
A Cogean Conversation between Friends,
Pau, Roy, and Morit.
So be sure to tune into that as well.
And as always, if you want to learn more about what we're doing
over here at the Yellow Farmhouse Education Center,
you can check out our website at YellowFarmhouse.org.
And also check out our Instagram to keep up to date on all the things
that we're doing over here.
If you want to say up to date on all things Cogean,
be sure to follow our Instagram at Cogean.com.
If you have any questions at all about the conference so far,
just feel free to shoot us an email at info at YellowFarmhouse.org.
So with that, I shall sign off for the day.
And I'll see everyone bright and early tomorrow morning at 8am
for a presentation with the O'HANA Scharner.
All right, peace everyone.