red miso, white miso.
miso is made with different kind of kouji, rice kouji, balikouji,
soybean kouji.
And we also grouped them by color.
So red miso, red is aka in Japanese, so we call this aka miso.
So aka miso often uses soybean kouji, with more salt and longer fermentation.
That's why it's dark and rich and packed with umami.
White miso, white is shirou, so we call it shiromiso.
So shiromiso usually has more rice kouji or balikouji.
And less salt and shorter fermentation time.
More kouji means more sweetness, so this miso is very sweet.
But depending on the region, even rice miso can be made less kouji and more salt.
For better ah, for better preservation and hard humid climates.
Rice miso is a long enough and gets darker.
It can even call red miso, aka miso.
Miso leh who explore learn, they are over 20 types of regional miso across Japan.
20.
Which one do you like or which one do you want to try?
Let me know in the comment.