The following is a conversation all about the state of the art in artificial intelligence,
including some of the exciting technical breakthroughs and developments in AI that happened
over the past year.
And some of the interesting things we think might happen this upcoming year.
At times, it does get super technical, but we do try to make sure that it remains accessible
to folks outside the field without ever dumbing it down.
It is a great honor and pleasure to be able to do this kind of episode with two of my
favorite people in the AI community.
Sebastian, Rashka, and Nathan Lambert.
They are both widely respected machine learning researchers and engineers who also happen
to be great communicators, educators, writers, and Twitterers, exposters.
Sebastian is the author of two books.
I highly recommend for beginners and experts alike.
First is build a large language model from scratch and build a reasoning model from scratch.
I truly believe in the machine learning computer science world, the best way to learn and
understand something is to build it yourself from scratch.
Nathan is the post-training lead at the Allen Institute for AI and author of the definitive
book on reinforcement learning from human feedback.
Both of them have great ex-accounts, great sub-stacks.
Sebastian has courses on YouTube, Nathan has a podcast, and everyone should absolutely
follow all of those.
This is the Lex Friedman podcast to support it.
Please check out our sponsors in the description where you can also find links to contact me,
ask questions, get feedback, and so on.
And now dear friends, here's Sebastian, Rashka, and Nathan Lambert.
So I think one useful lens to look at all of this through is the deep seek, so-called
deep seek moment.
This happened about a year ago in January 2025.
In the open-weight Chinese company, deep seek, released deep seek R1 that I think it's
fair to say surprised everyone with near or at state-of-the-art performance with allegedly
much less compute for much cheaper.
And from then to today, the AI competition has gotten insane.
Both on the research level and the product level, it's just been accelerating.
Let's discuss all of this today.
And maybe let's start with some spicy questions if we can.
Who is winning at the international level?
Would you say it's a set of companies in China or the set of companies in the United States?
And Sebastian, Nathan, it's good to see you guys.
So Sebastian, who do you think is winning?
So winning is a very broad term.
I would say you mentioned the deep seek moment, and I do think deep seek is definitely winning
the hearts of the people who work on open-weight models because they share these as open
models.
Winning, I think, has multiple timescales to it.
We have today, we have next year, we have in 10 years.
One thing I know for sure is that I don't think nowadays, 2026, that there will be any company
who is, let's say, having access to a technology that no other company has access to.
And that is mainly because researchers have frequently changing jobs, changing labs,
they rotate.
So I don't think there will be a clear winner in terms of technology access.
However, I do think there will be, the differentiating factor will be budget and hardware
constraints.
So I don't think the ideas will be proprietary, but the way or the resources that are needed
to implement them.
And so I don't see currently the ticket wall scenario where a winner takes it all.
I can't see that at the moment.
Nathan, what do you think?
You see the labs put different energy into what they're trying to do.
And I think to demarcate the point in time when we're recording this, the hype over
Anthropics, Cloud Opus 4.5 model has been absolutely insane, which is just, I mean, I've
used it and built stuff in the last few weeks.
And it's almost gone to the point where it feels like a bit of a meme in terms of the
hype.
And it's kind of funny because this is very organic.
And then if we go back a few months ago, we can get the release date.
And the notes is Gemini 3 from Google got released.
And it seemed like the marketing and just like wow factor of that release was super high.
But then at the end of November, Cloud Opus 4.5 was released and the hype has been growing.
But Gemini 3 was before this and it kind of feels like people don't really talk about
it as much.
And when it came out, everybody was like, this is Gemini's moment to retake kind of Google's
structural advantages in AI.
And Gemini 3 is a fantastic model and I still use it.
It's just kind of differentiation is lower.
And I agree with Sebastian, what you're saying with all these, like the idea space is very
fluid, but culturally anthropic is known for betting very hard on code, which is Cloud
Code thing is working out for them right now.
So I think that even if the ideas flow pretty freely, so much of this is bottlenecked
by human effort and kind of culture of organizations where anthropic seems to at least be presenting
as the least chaotic.
It is a bit of an advantage and if they can keep doing that for a while.
But on the other side of things, there's a lot of ominous technology from China where
there's way more labs than deep sea, deep sea kicked off a movement within China.
I say kind of similar to how chat you be kicked off a movement in the US where everything
had a chatbot.
There's now tons of tech companies in China that are releasing very strong frontier open
weight models to the point where I would say that deep sea is kind of losing its crown
as the preeminent open model maker in China and the likes of Z.ai's with their GLM models,
Mini Max's models, Kimi Moon shot, especially in the last few months have shown more brightly.
The new deep sea models are still very strong, but that's kind of a, it could look back
as a big narrative point where the 2025 deep sea came and then all that kind of provided
this platform for way more Chinese companies that are releasing these fantastic models to
kind of have this new type of operation.
So these models from these Chinese companies are open weights and depending on this trajectory
of business model said these American companies are doing could be at risk.
But currently a lot of people are paying for AI software in the US and historically in
China and other parts of the world.
People don't pay a lot for software.
So some of these models like deep sea have the love of the people because they are open
weight.
How long do you think the Chinese companies keep releasing open weights models?
I would say for a few years, I think that like in the US there's not a clear business
model for it.
I have been writing about open models for a while and these Chinese companies have realized
it.
So I get him down from some of them and they're smart and realize the same constraints
which is that a lot of US companies and other IT companies won't pay for a API subscription
to Chinese companies for security concerns.
This has been a longstanding habit in tech and the people of these companies then see open
weight models as an ability to influence and take part of a huge growing AI expenditure
market in the US.
And they're very realistic about this and it's working for them and I think that the government
will see that that is building a lot of influence internationally in terms of uptake of the
technology.
So there's going to be a lot of incentives to keep it going.
Building these models and doing the research is very expensive.
So at some point I expect consolidation but I don't expect that to be a story of 2026
where there will be more open model builders throughout 2026 and there were in 2025 and
a lot of the notable ones will be in China.
You're going to say something.
Yes, you mentioned deep sea losing its crown.
I do think to some extent yes but we also have to consider though they are still I would
say slightly ahead and the other ones it's not that deep sea got worse.
It's just like the other ones are using the ideas from deep sea for example you mentioned
Kimmy same architecture they're training it and then again we have this leapfrogging
where they might be at some point in time a bit better because they have the more recent
model and I think this comes back to the fact that there won't be a clear winner.
It will it will just be like like that.
One person really says something the other one comes in and the recent the most recent
model is probably always the best model.
We'll also see the Chinese companies have different incentives so deep sea is very secretive
where some of these startups are like the mini maxes and Zoday eyes of the world those
two literally have filed IPO paperwork and they're trying to get Western mind share and do
a lot of outreach there so I don't know if these incentives will kind of change the
model development because deep sea famously is built by a hedge fund high flyer capital
and we don't know exactly what we don't know what they use the models for or if they
care about this.
First you go in terms of communication they're not secretive in terms of the technical
reports that describe how their models work they're still open on that front and we should
also say on the opus 45 hype there's the layer of something being the darling of the X
echo chamber on Twitter echo chamber and the actual amount of people they're using the
model.
I think it's probably fair to say that Chagypeti and Gemini are focused on the broad user
base that just want to solve problems and their daily lives and that user base is gigantic.
So the hype about the coding may not be represented the actual use.
I would say also a lot of the usage patterns are like you said name recognition brand
and stuff but also muscle memory almost where you know like Chagypeti has been around
for a long time people just got used to using it and it's kind of like almost like a flywheel
they recommended to other users and that stuff.
One interesting point is also the customization of elements for example Chagypeti has a memory
feature right and so you may have a subscription and you use it for personal stuff but I don't
know if you want to use that same thing at work you know because it's a boundary between
private and work if you're working at a company they might not allow that you may not want
that and I think that's also an interesting point where you might have multiple subscriptions.
One is just clean code it keeps it's nothing of your personal images that you or hobby projects
in there it's just like the work thing and then the other one is your personal thing.
So I think that's also something where two different use cases and it doesn't mean you only
have to have one it's I think the future is also multiple ones.
What model do you think one 2025 and what model do you think is going to win 26?
I think in the context of a consumer chatbot as a question of are you willing to bet
on Gemini over chat GPT which I would say in my gut feels like a bit of a risky bet because
opening eye has been the incumbent and there's so many benefits to that and tech that I think
the momentum if you look at 2025 was on Gemini side but they were starting from such a low
point I think on RIP barred and these earlier attempts of getting started I think huge credit
for them for powering through the organizational chaos to make that happen but also it's hard
to bet against chat to open AI because they always come off cast as so chaotic but they're very good
at landing things and I think like a personally I have very mixed reviews of GPT-5 but I had to
have saved them so much money with the high line feature being a router where most users are no
longer charging like charging their GPU costs as much so I think it's very hard to dissociate
the things that I like out of models versus the things that are going to actually be a general
public differentiator. What do you think about 2026 who's going to win? I'll say something even
though it's risky I will say that I think Gemini will continue to take progress on chat GPT I think
Google scale when both of these are operating at such extreme scales and like Google has the ability
to separate that research and product a bit better where you hear so much about what
AI being chaotic operationally and chasing the high impact thing which is a very startup culture
and then on the software and enterprise side I think inthropic we'll have continued to success
as they've again and again been set up for that and obviously Google's cloud has a lot of
offerings but I think this kind of like Gemini name brand is important for them to build and
Google's cloud will continue to do well as but that's kind of a more complex thing to explain
in the ecosystem because that's competing with the likes of Azure and AWS rather than on the
model provider side. So infrastructure you think you can use given advantage largely because the
margin on Nvidia chips is insane and Google can develop everything from top to bottom to fit
their stack and not have to pay this margin and they've had a head start and building data centers
so all of these things that have both high lead times and very hard margins on high costs Google has
just kind of a historical advantage there and if there's going to be a new paradigm it's most likely
to come from open AI where they're kind of their research division again and again has kind of shown
this ability to land a new research idea or a product I think like deep research so we're
oh one thinking models like all these definitional things have come from open AI and that's
got to be one of their top trades as an organization so it's kind of hard to bet against that but
I think a lot of this year will be about scale and optimizing what can be described as low
hanging fruit and models and clearly there's a trade-off between intelligence and speed this is
what Jaguar Pt 5 was trying to solve behind the scenes is like do people actually want intelligence
the broad public or do they want speed I think it's a nice variety actually are the option to have
a toggle there I mean first for my personal usage most of the time when I look something up I use
Jaguar Pt 2 ask a quick question get the information I wanted fast for you know most daily tasks I
use the quick model nowadays I think the auto mode is pretty good where you don't have to
specifically say thinking or you know non-thinking and stuff then again I also sometimes want the
promote very often what I do is when I have something written I put it into a Jaguar Pt and say hey
do a very thorough check is all my references correct all my thoughts correct did I make any
formatting mistakes and are the figure numbers wrong or something like that and I don't need that
right away it's something okay I finish my stuff maybe have dinner let it run come back and
go through this and I think see that's the way I think it's important to have this option I would
go crazy for each query I would have to wait 30 minutes or 10 minutes you know that's me yeah
yeah I'm like saying over here losing my mind that you use the router and the non-thinking model I'm
like how do you how do you live with how do you live with that yeah like my reaction I'm
Ben heavily on tragedy Pt for a while never touched five non-thinking I find it it's tone and
then it's propensity of errors it's just like I have a higher likelihood of errors some of this is
from back when opening I released 03 which was the first model to do this deep search and find
many sources and integrate them for you so it became hit bituated with that so I will only use
GPT 5.2 thinking or pro when I'm finding any sort of information query for work whether that's a
paper or some code reference that I found and it's just like I I will regularly have like five
pro queries going simultaneously each looking for one specific paper or feedback on equation or
something I have a fun example of what I just needed to answer as fast as possible for this podcast
I was going on the trip I have a local GPU running at home and I wanted to run along our
RL experiment and usually I also unplug things because you never know if you're not at home you don't
want to have things plugged in and I accidentally unplugged the GPU it was like my wife was already
in the car and it's like oh dang and then basically I wanted as fast as possible a bash script that
runs my different experiments in the evaluation and I did something I know I learned how to use the
bash interface or bash terminal but in that moment I just needed like 10 seconds give me the
command there's a hilarious situation but yes what did you use so I did the non-thinking fastest
model it gave me the bash command I to chain different scripts to each other and then the thing
is like you have the T thing where you want to route this to a lock file top of my head I was just
like in a hurry I could have thought about it myself by the way I don't know if there's a
representative case wife waiting in the car you have to run the GPU you get to generate a bash
curve this sounds like a movie I use Gemini for that so I use thinking for all the information stuff
and then Gemini for fast things or stuff that I could come times Google which is like it's good at
explaining things and I trust that it has this kind of background of knowledge and it's simple and
the Gemini app has got a lot better and it's good for that sort of things and then for code and then
you sort of philosophical discussion I use cloud opus 4.5 also always with extended thinking
extended thinking and inference time scaling is just a way to make the models marginally smarter
and I will always edge on that side when the progress is very high because you don't know in that
all I'm walking you use case and then sometimes use GROC for real time information or finding
something on AI Twitter that I knew I saw and I need to dig up and I just fixated on although I
when GROC 4 came out the GROC for what is super heavy which was like their pro variant was
actually very good and I was pretty impressed with it and that was just kind of like muscle memory
lost track of it with having the chat to be T. app open so I use my different things.
Yeah I actually do use GROC for heavy for debugging for like hardcore debugging and the other ones
can solve it I find that it's the bus and I it's interesting because you say the chat
you be the best interface for me for that same reason but this could be just momentum.
Gemini is the better interface for me I think because I found love with their
best needle in the haystack if I ever put something that has a lot of contacts but I'm looking
for a very specific kind of information to make sure it tracks all of it I find at least
Gemini for me has been the best so it's funny with some of these models if they win your heart over
for one particular feature at one on a one particular day for that particular query that prompt
you're like this model is better and so you'll just stick with it for a bit until it does something
really dumb there's like a threshold effect some smart thing and then you fall in love with it and
then it does some dumb thing and you're like you know what I'm going to switch to try a cloud
and a chat GPT and all that kind of stuff. This is exactly like you use it until it breaks until you
have a problem and then then you change the LM and I think it's the same how we use anything like
our favorite text editor operating systems or the browser I mean there are so many browser
options Safari Firefox Chrome all the characterly similar but then there are ex ex cases maybe
extensions you want to use and then you switch but I don't think there is any one who types the
same thing like the website into different browsers and compares them you only do that when the
website doesn't render if something breaks I think so that's a good point I think you use it
until it breaks and then you explore other options I think on the long context thing I was also a
Gemini user for this but the GPT 5.2 release blog had like crazy long context scores where a lot of
people were like did they just figure out some algorithms like change it went from like 30% to like
70% or something in this minor model update so it's also very hard to keep track of all of these
things but now I'm look more favorable at GPT 5.2's long context it's just kind of like how do I
actually get to testing this never ending battle it's interesting that none of us talked about the
Chinese models from a user usage perspective what does that say does that mean the Chinese models
are not as good or does that mean we're just very biased and us focused I do think that that's
currently the discrepancy between just a model and the platform so I think the open models they
are more known for the open weights not that platform yet there are also a lot of companies that are
willing to sell you the open model and for instead of very low cost I think like open router it's
easy to do the like a multi model things you can run deep seek on perplexity I think all of us
sitting here are like we use open AI GPT 5 pro consistently we're all willing to pay for the marginal
intelligence gain and anyone that's like these models from the US are better and in terms of
the outputs I think the question is will they stay better for this year and for years going but
it's like so long as they're better I'm going to pay for you to use them I think there's also
analysis that shows that like the way that the Chinese models are served this you could argue due
to expert controls or not is that they use fewer GPUs for replica which makes them slower and have
different errors and it's like speed and intelligence if these things are in your favor as a user I
think in the US a lot of users will go for this and I think that that is going thing that will
spur these Chinese companies to want to compete in other ways whether it's like free or substantially
lower costs or it'll breed creativity in terms of offerings which is good for the ecosystem but I
just think of the simple thing is the US models are currently better and we use them and I try Chinese
try these other open models and I'm like fun but not going to I don't go back to it we didn't
really mention programming that's another use case that a lot of people deeply care about so I
use basically half and half cursor and clogged code because there I find them to be like fundamentally
different experience and both useful what do you guys you program quite a bit so what do you use
what's the current vibe so I use the codex plugin for VS code you know it's very convenient it's
just like a plugin and then it's a chat interface that has access to your repository I know that
cloud code is I think a bit different it's a bit more agentic it touches more things it does a whole
project for you I'm not quite there yet where I'm comfortable with that because maybe I'm a
control freak but I still would like to see a bit what's going on and codex is kind of like right
now for me like the sweet spot where it is helping me but it is not taking completely over I should
mention one of the reasons I do use cloud code is to build the skill of programming with English I mean
the experience is fundamentally different you're as opposed to micromanaging the details of the
process of the generation of the code and looking at the diff which you can in cursor if that's the
idea you use and and changing altering looking and reading the code and understanding the code deeply
as you progress versus just kind of like thinking in this design space and just guiding it at this
macro level which I think is another way of thinking about the programming process also we should
say that cloud code it just seems to be somehow a better utilization of cloud opus 45 it's a good
side by side for people to do so you can have cloud code open you can have cursor open you can have
the s code open and you can select the same models on all of them and ask questions are very interesting
like the cloud code is way better and that domain it's remarkable all right we should say that both
of you are are legit on multiple fronts researchers programmers educators tweeterers
and on the book front too so Nathan at some point soon hopefully has an RLHF book coming out it's
available for preorder and there's a full digital preprint just making it pretty and better
organized for the physical thing which is a lot of why I do it because it's fun to create things
that you think are excellent in the physical form when so much of our life is digital I should say
going to propuxity here Sebastian Roshka is a machine learning researcher and author known for
several influential books a couple of them that I wanted to mention which is a book I highly
recommend build a large language model from scratch and the new one build a reasoning model from
scratch so I'm really excited about that building stuff from scratch is one of the most powerful
honestly building an element from scratch is a lot of fun it's also a lot of to learn and like
you said it's probably the best way to learn how something really works because you can look at figures
but figures can have mistakes you can look of concepts explanations but you might misunderstand them
but if you see the code there is code and the code works you know it's correct I mean there's no
misunderstanding it's like it's precise otherwise it wouldn't work and I think that's like kind of
like the beauty behind coding it is kind of like it doesn't lie it's math basically so even though
with math I think you can have mistakes in a book you would never notice because you're not running
the math when you are reading the book you can't verify this and with code but what's
nice is you can verify it yeah I agree with you about the element from scratch book it's nice to
tune out everything else the internet and so on and just focus on the book but you know I read
several like you know history books it's just less lonely somehow it's really more fun like
out for example on the programming front I think it's genuinely more fun to program with an LLM
and I think it's genuinely more fun to read with an LLM but you're right like this distraction
should be minimized so it's you use the LLM to basically enrich the experience maybe add more
context maybe the I just the rate of a half moments for me in a small scale is really high with
their arms 100% I would I also want to correct myself I'm not suggesting not to use LLM's I suggest
doing it in multiple passes like one pass just offline focus mode and then after that I mean I
also take notes but I I try to resist the urge to immediately look things up I do a second pass
it's just like for me more structured this way and I get I mean sometimes things are answered
in the chapter but sometimes also it just helps to let it sink in and think about it other people
have different preferences I would highly recommend using LLM's when reading books for me it's just
it's not the first thing to do it's like the second pass by way of recommendation as to say I do the
opposite I like to use the alarm at the beginning to lay out the full context of like what is this world
that I'm now stepping into but I try to avoid clicking out of the LLM into the world of like
Twitter blogs and because then you're now down this rabbit hole you're reading somebody's opinion
there's a flame war about a particular topic and also and you're no longer you're now in the
in the realm of the internet and read it and so on but if you're purely letting the LLM give
you the context of why this matters what are the big picture ideas but sometimes books themselves
are good at doing that but not always so this is why I like the chat GPT happy that gives the AI
a home in your computer when you are folk you can focus on it rather than just being another tab in
my mess of internet options and I think cloud code in these particular does a good job of making
that a joy where it seems very engaging as a product design to be an interface that your AI will
then go out into the world and there's something that is very kind of intangible between it and
codex is that it just feels kind of warm and engaging where codex can often be as good from open AI
but it just kind of like feels a little bit rougher on the edges where it's like cloud code is makes
it fun to build things particularly from scratch where you just don't like you don't have to care
but you trust that it'll make something like obviously it's good for websites and kind of refreshing
tooling and stuff like this which I use it for or data analysis so I my blog we scrape hug and
face we keep the download numbers for every data set and model over time now so we have them and
it's like cloud was just like yeah I've made use of that data no problem and I'm like that would have
taken me days and I was like then I have enough situational awareness to be like okay these trends
obviously make sense and you can check things because that's just a kind of wonderful interface
where you can have an intermediary and not have to do the kind of awful low level work that you
would have to do to maintain different web projects and do the stuff all right so we just talked about
a bunch of the closed weight models let's talk about the open ones so tell me about the landscape
of open LL models which are interesting ones which stand out to you and why where do you match deep
seek do you want to see how many we can name off with the top of our head yeah without looking at notes
deep seek kimi mini max z dot ai antling we're just going Chinese let's throw in mistroly i
jema yeah GPT OSS the open source model by chat GPT actually Nvidia Nemo Tron had a or Nvidia had a
very cool one a Nemo Tron 3 there's a lot of stuff especially at the end of the year Quinn one
maybe the one oh yeah Quinn was the net the obvious name of this thing I was trying to get to the
you can get at least 10 Chinese and at least a 10 western I think that I'm in opening I release
their first open model since GPT 2 that was when I when I meant talk when I was writing about
opening eyes open model release they're all like don't forget about GPT 2 which I thought it was
really funny because that is such a different time but GPT OSS is actually a very strong model and
does some things that the other models don't do very well and I think that selfishly I'll promote
a bunch of like western companies so both in the US and Europe have these like fully open models
so I work at Alan Institute for AI we've been building Olmo which releases data and code and all of
this and now we have actual competition for people that are trying to release everything so that
are people can train these models so there's the Institute for Foundation models or slash LM360
which is like had their k2 models of various types aparatists is a switch research consortium
hugging face has small lm which is very popular in Nvidia's name or trying to start
releasing data as well and then Stanford's marine community project which is kind of making it so
there's a pipeline for people to open a GitHub issue and implement a new idea and then have it run
in a stable language modeling stack so this space that list was way smaller in 2024 so I think
it was like just AI too so that's a great thing for more people to get involved and to understand
language models which doesn't really have a like a Chinese company that has an analog while I'm
talking I'll say that the Chinese open language models tend to be much bigger and that gives some
this higher peak performance as M.O.E. is where a lot of these things that we like a lot whether it was
Gemma Indie Matron have tended to be smaller models from the US which is which is starting to change
from US in Europe Mr. Lard's three came out which was a giant M.O.E. model very similar to Deep Seek
architecture in December and then a startup RCAI and both Nima Tron have Nima Tron and Nvidia
have teased M.O.E. models of this way bigger than 100 billion parameters like this 400 billion
parameter range coming in this like Q1 2026 timeline so I think that's kind of balances set to
change this year in terms of what people are using the Chinese versus US open models for which
which I'm personally so it can be very excited to watch first of all huge props for being able to
name so many of these did you actually name Lama now feel like all right P.Lama all right can you
mention what are some interesting models that stand out so you mentioned Q1 3's obviously standout
so I would say the years almost book ended by both Deep Seek version 3 and R1 and then on the
other hand in December deep seek version 3.2 because what I like about those is they always have
an interesting architecture tweak that others don't have but otherwise if you want to go with
you know like the familiar but very good performance Q3 and like Nathan said also GPT OSS and I
think GPT OSS what's interesting about it is kind of like the first public or like open weight
model that was really trained with tool use in mind which I do think is kind of a little bit of a
paradigm shift where the ecosystem was not quite ready for it so with tool use I mean that the
LLM is able to do a web search to call Python interpreter and I do think this it's a standout
because I think it's a huge unlock because one of the most common complaints about LLMs are
for example hallucinations right and so in my opinion one of the best ways to solve hallucinations
is to not try to always remember information or make things up for math why not use a calculator
app or Python if I asked the LLM who won the soccer world cup in 1998 instead of just trying to
memorize could go do a search I think mostly it's usually still Google search so GPT
GPT OSS they would do a tool call to Google maybe find a FIFA website find okay it was France
it would get you that information reliably instead of just trying to memorize it so I think it's
a huge unlock which I think right now is not fully utilized yet by the open source open
wait ecosystem a lot of people don't use tool call modes because I think it's first is a trust
thing you don't want to run this on your computer where it has access to tools could wipe your hard drive
or whatever so you want to maybe contain containerize that but I do think you know that that is like
a really important step for the upcoming years to have this ability yeah so a few quick things first
thank you for defining what you mean by tool use I think that's a great thing to do in general
for the concepts we're talking about even things that sort of well established as MOE's you have to say
that means make sure x person you kind of have to build up an intuition for people what that means
how it's actually utilized what are the different flavors so what does it mean that there's this
such explosion of open models what's your intuition if you're releasing an open model you want people
to use it is the first and foremost thing and then after that comes things like transparency and trust
I think when you look at China the biggest reason is that they want people around the world to use
these models and I think a lot of people will not if you look outside of the US a lot of people
will not pay for software but they might have computing resources or you can put a model on it and
run it I think there can also be data that you don't want to send to the cloud so this the number one
thing is getting people to use models use AI or use your AI that might not be able to do it without
having access to the model I guess which state explicitly so we've been talking about these Chinese
models and open weight models oftentimes the way they're run is locally so it's not like you're sending
your data to China or to whoever developed to Silicon Valley whoever developed the model a lot of
American startups make money by hosting these models from China and selling them selling token
it's called like selling tokens which means somebody will call the model to do some some piece of
work I think the other reason is for us companies like Ted open AI is so GPU to pry like they're so
they're at the limits of the GPUs whenever they make a release they're always talking about like our
GPUs are hurting and I think there's like in one of these like GPT OSS release sessions and
Maltman said like oh we're releasing this because we can use your GPUs we don't have to use
don't have to use our GPUs and open AI can still get distribution out of this which is another
very real thing doesn't cost them to anything and for the user I think also I mean there are users who
just use the model locally how they would use a GPT but also for companies I think it's a huge
unlock to have these models because you can customize them you can train them you can
add post training add more data and specialize them into let's say law medical models whatever
you have and the appeal you mentioned Lama the appeal of the open weight models from China is
that the open weight models are also the licenses are even friendlier I think they are just unrestricted
open source licenses where if you use something like Lama or Gemma there are some strings attached
I think it's like a upper limit in terms of how many users you have and then if you exceed I don't
assume so many million users you have to report your finance situation to let's say meta or something
like that and I think well it is a free model but there are strings attached and people do like
things where strings are not attached so I think that's also one of the reasons besides performance
why the open weight models from China are so popular because you you can just use them there is no
there's no catch in that sense yeah the ecosystem has gotten better on that front but mostly
downstream of these new providers providing such open licenses that was funny when you pulled up
perplexity it said Kimmy K2 thanking hosted in the US which is like an exact I've never seen this
but it's an exact example of what we're talking about where people are sensitive to this
but Kimmy K2 thanking and Kimmy K2 as a model that is very popular people say that has very good
like creative writing and also in doing some software things such as these little quirks that people
pick up on with different models that they like what are some interesting ideas that some of these
models have explored that you can speak to like that particular interesting to you maybe we can
chronologically I mean there was of course deep seek deep seek r1 that came out in January if we
just focus on 2025 however this was based on deep seek version three which came out the year before
in December 2024 the multiple things on the architecture side what is fascinating is you can still
I mean that's what I do with my from scratch coding projects you can still start with GPT2 and you
get you can add things to that model to make it into this other model so it's all still kind of like
the same lineage the same it is a very close relationship between those but top of my head deep
seek what was unique there is the mixture of x I mean they were not inventing mixture of experts we
can maybe talk a bit more what mixture of experts means but just to list these things first before
we dive into detail mixture of experts but then they also had multi head latent attention which is
a tweak to the attention mechanism where this was I would say 2025 the main distinguishing
factor because between these open weight models different tweaks to make inference or kv cache size
we can also define kv cache in a few moments but to kind of make it more economical to have long
context to shrink the kv cache size so what are tweaks that we can do and most of them focused
on the attention mechanism there is multi head latent attention in deep seek there is a group query
attention which is still very popular it's not invented by any of those models it goes back a few
years but that would be the other option sliding window attention I think almost reuses it if I
remember correctly so there are these different tweaks that make the models different otherwise
I put them all together in article once where I just compared them they are very surprisingly similar
it's just different numbers in terms of how many repetitions of the transformer block you have in
the center and like just little little knobs that people tune but but what's so nice about it is
it's it works no matter what you can tweak things you can move the normalization layers around
you get some performance gains and I almost always very good in appellation studies showing what
actually what it does to the model if you move something around the appellation studies doesn't make
it better or worse but there are so many let's say ways you can implement a transformer and make
it still work big ideas that are still prevalent is mixed of experts multi head latent attention
sliding window attention group query attention and then at the end of the year we saw a focus on
making the attention mechanism scale linearly with inference token prediction so there were
quen 3 next for example which added a gated delta net it's it's like kind of like inspired by
state space models where you have a fixed state that you keep updating but it makes essentially
this attention cheaper or it replaces attention with a cheaper operation and it may be as
a useful to step back and talk about transform architecture in general yeah so maybe we should start
with the gpt 2 architecture the transformer that was derived from the attention is all you need
paper so the attention is all you need paper had a transformer architecture that had two parts
and encoder and a decoder and gpt went just focusing in on the decoder part it is essentially a
still a neural network and it has this attention mechanism inside and you predict one token at a
time you pass it through an embedding layer there's the transformer block the transformer block has
attention modules and a fully connected layer and there are some normalization layers in between but
it's essentially neural network layers with this attention mechanism so coming from gpt 2 when we
move on to gpt oss there is for example the mixture of experts layer it's not invented by gpt oss it's
a few years old but it is essentially a tweak to make the model larger without consuming more compute
in each forward path so there is this fully connected layer and if listeners are familiar with
multi layer perceptrons you can think of mini multi layer perceptron a fully connected
neural network layer inside the transformer and it's very expensive because it's fully connected if
you have 1000 inputs 1000 outputs that's like a 1 million connections and it's a very expensive part
in this transformer and the idea is to kind of expand that into multiple feed forward network so
instead of having one let's say you have 256 but it would make it way more expensive because now you
have 256 but you don't use all of them at the same time so you now have a router that says okay
based on this input token it would be useful to use this fully connected network and in that context
it's called an expert so a mixture of experts means you have multiple experts and depending on
what your input is let's say it's more math heavy it would use different experts compared to let's
say translating input text from english to spanish it would maybe console different experts it's
not quite clear I mean not as clear cut to say okay this is only an expert for math and for
spanish it's a bit more fuzzy but the idea is essentially that you pack more knowledge into the
network but not all the knowledge is used all the time that would be very wasteful so you're kind of
like during the token generation you have more selective there's a router that selects which tokens
should go to which expert it's more complexity it's harder to train there's a lot of you know that
can go wrong like collapse and everything so I think it's by almost three still uses dense I
mean you have I think all models was mixed off experts but dense models where dense means also
also it's jargon there's a distinction between dense and spars so mixed off experts is considered
sparse because we have a lot of experts but only few of them are active so that's called sparse
and then dense would be the opposite where you only have like one fully connected module and it's
always you know utilized so maybe maybe it's a good place to also talk about kvcash but actually
before that even zooming out like fundamentally how many new ideas have been implemented from
from GPT-2 today like how different really are these architectures picture like the mixture of
experts on the attention mechanism in GPT OSS that would be the group query attention mechanism
so it's a slight tweak from multi head attention to group query attention so that we have two
think they replaced layer norm by rms norm but it's just like a different normalization
layer not a big change it's just like a tweak the non-linear activation function people familiar
in with deep new networks I mean it's the same as changing sigmoid with relu it's it's not changing
the network fundamentally it's just like a tweak like a little little tweak and that's about it
I would say it's not really fundamentally that different it's still the same same architecture so
you can convert one from one you can go from one into the other by just adding these these
changes basically this fundamentally is still the same architecture yeah so for example you mentioned
my book earlier that GPT-2 model in the book because it's simple and it's very small so 124
120 million parameters approximately but in the bonus materials I do have almost three from
scratch Gemma three from scratch and other types of from scratch models and I always started with
my GPT-2 model and just you know tweak the well edit different components and you get from one
to the other it's like it's kind of like a lineage in a sense yeah can you build up an intuition
for people because sort of when you zoom out you look at it there's so much rapid advancement in the
AI world and at the same time fundamentally the architectures have not changed so where is all
the turbulence the turmoil of the advancement happening where where's the gains to be had so
there are the different stages where you develop the network or train the network you have the
pre-training now back then they was just pre-training with GPT-2 now you have pre-training mid-training
and post-training so and I think right now we are in the post-training focus stage I mean pre-training
still gives you advantages if you scaled it up to better higher quality data but then we have
capability unlocks that we're not there with GPT-2 for example chat GPT it is basically a GPT-3
model and GPT-3 is the same as GPT-2 in terms of architecture what was new was adding the supervised
fine tuning and the reinforcement learning with human feedback so it's more on the algorithmic
site rather than the architecture I would say that the systems also change a lot I think if you listen
to Nvidia's announcements I talk about these things like you now do FP8 you can now do FP4 and
what is happening is these labs are figuring out how to utilize more compute to put it into one
model which lets them train faster and that lets them put more data in and then you can find better
configurations faster by doing this so you can look at like the essentially the tokens per second
per GPU is a metric that you look at when you're doing large scale training and you could get you
can go from like 10k to 13k by turning on FP8 training which means you're using less memory per
parameter in the model and by saving less information you do less communication you can train faster
so all of these like system things underpin way faster experimentation on data and algorithms
that is kind of like it's this it's this kind of loop that keeps going where it's kind of hard to
describe when you look at the architecture and they're exactly the same but the code base used to
train these models is going to be vastly different and you could probably like I don't the GPUs
are different but you probably train GPT OS has 20B way faster and walk-along time than GPT2
was trained at the time. Like you said they had for example in the mix of experts this NVFP4
optimization for example where you get most throughput but I do think this is for the speed
this is true but it doesn't give the model new capabilities in a sense it's just how much can we
make make the computation coarser without suffering in terms of model performance degradation
but I do think I mean there are alternatives popping up to the transformer there's text diffusion
models completely different paradigm and there's also I mean the text diffusion models might use
transformer architectures but it's not an auto-regressive transformer and also Mamba models it's a
state space model but they do have trade-offs and what's right is there's nothing that has replaced
the auto-regressive transformer as state of the art model so like for state of the art you would still
do that go with that thing but there are no alternatives for the cheaper and like alternatives that
are kind of making compromises but it's not just one architecture anymore there are little ones
coming up but if we talk about the state of the art it's pretty much still the
the transform architecture auto-regressive derived from GPT-2 essentially I guess the big question
here is we talked quite a bit here on the architecture behind the pre-training are the scaling
laws holding strong across pre-training post-training inference contact size data synthetic data
I like to start with the technical definition of scaling laws it kind of forms all this the
scaling laws a power law relationship between you can think of the x-axis so kind of what you are
scaling is a combination of compute and data which are kind of similar and then the y-axis is like
the held out prediction accuracy over next tokens we talked about models being auto-regressive it's
like if you keep a set of text that the model has not seen how accurate will get when you will train
and the idea of scaling laws came when people figured out that that was a very predictable
relationship and I think that that technical term is continuing and then the question is like
what do users get out of it and then there are more types of scaling where open AI's O1 was
famous for introducing inference time scaling and I think less famously for also showing that you
can scale reinforcement learning training and get kind of this log x-axis and then a linear increase
in performance on y-axis so there's kind of these three axes now or the traditional scaling laws
are talked about for pre-training which is how big your model is and how big your data set is
and then scaling reinforcement learning which is like how long can you do this trial and error
learning that we will talk about we'll define more of this and then this inference time compute which
is just letting the model generate more tokens on a specific problem so I'm kind of bullish where
they're all really still working but the low-hanging fruit has mostly been taken especially in the last
year on reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards which is this RLVR and then inference time
scaling which is just why these models feel so different to use were previously you would get that
first token immediately and now they'll go off for seconds minutes or even hours generating these
hidden thoughts before giving you the first word of your answer and that's all about this inference
time scaling which is such a wonderful kind of step function in terms of how the models change
abilities they kind of enabled this tool use stuff and enabled this much better software engineering
that we were talking about and this is when we say enabled almost entirely downstream of the fact that
this reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards training just kind of let the models pick up
these skills very easily so let the models learn so if you look at the reasoning process when the
models are generating a lot of tokens what it'll be often doing is it tries a tool it looks at what
it gets back it tries another API it sees what it gets back and if it solves the problem so the models
when you're training them very quickly learn to do this and then at the end of the day that gives
this kind of general foundation where the model can use CLI commands very nicely in your repo and
handle get for you and move things around and organize things or search to find for information
which if we're sitting in these chairs a year ago it's something that we didn't really think of the
models being doing so this is just kind of something that has happened this year and is totally
transformed how we think of using AI which I think is very magical is such an interesting evolution
and just so unlock so much value but it's like it's not clear what the next avenue will be in terms
of unlocking stuff like this I think that there's there's we'll get to continue learning later but
there's a lot of buzz around certain areas of AI but no one knows when the next step function will
will really come so you you've actually said quite a lot of things there and said profound things
quickly it would be nice to unpack them a little bit you say your bullish basically on every
version of scaling so we just even started the beginning pre-training are we kind of
implying that the low hanging fruit on pre-training scaling has been picked is is a
pre-training hit a plateau or is even pre-training still your bullish on pre-training has
gotten extremely expensive I think to scale up pre-training it's also implying that you're
going to serve a very large model to the users so I think that it's been loosely established the
likes of GPT4 and similar models were around one trillion like this order of trillion parameters
at the biggest size there's a lot of rumors that they've actually gotten smaller as training has
gotten more efficient you want to make the model smaller because then your costs of serving go
down proportionally these models the cost of training them is really low relative to the cost
of serving them to hundreds of millions of users I think deep sea kept this famous number of
about five million dollars for pre-training at cloud market rates I think almost three
section 2.4 in the paper we just detailed how long we had the GPU clusters sitting around for
training which includes engineering issues multiple seeds and it was like about two million dollars
to rent the cluster to like deal with all the problems and headaches of training a model so
these models are pretty like a lot of people could get one to ten million dollars to train a model
but the recurring costs of serving millions of users is really billions of dollars of compute I think
that you can look at close like a thousand GPU rental you can pay a hundred grand a day for and
these companies could have millions of GPUs you can look at how much these things cost to sit around
so that's kind of a big thing and then it's like if scaling is actually giving you a better model
is it going to be financially worth it and I think it will kind of slowly will push it out as AI
solves more compelling tasks so like the likes of cloud opus 4.5 making cloud code just work for
things I think I launched this project called like the Adam project which is like American truly open
models in July and that was like a true vibe coded website and like I have a job make plots and
stuff and then I came back to refreshing the last few weeks and it's like cloud opus 4.5 versus
whatever model at the time was like just crushed all the issues that it had from building in June
July and like might be a bigger model there's a lot of things that go into this but that's like
there's still progress coming so what you're speaking to is the nuance of the why access of the
scaling laws that the way it's experienced versus on a benchmark the actual intelligence might
be different but still you're intuition about pre-training of your scales the size of compute
will the models get better not whether it's financially viable but just from the law aspect of it
do you think the models will get smarter yeah and I think that there's and this sometimes comes off
as like almost like disillusioned from people leadership like AI companies saying this but they're
like it's held for 13 orders of magnitude of computers or something like why would it ever end
so I think fundamentally it is pretty unlikely to stop it's just like eventually we're not
even going to be able to test the bigger scales because of all the problems that come with more
compute I think that there's a lot of talk on how 2026 is a year when very large blackwell compute
clusters like giggle-ot scale facilities that hyperscalers are coming online and these were all
contracts for power and data centers that were assigned and sought out in like 22 and 2023 so before
or right after chat GPT so it took this two to three or lead time to build these bigger clusters to
train the models well there's obviously immense interest in building even more data centers on that
so that is like kind of the crux that people are saying is like these new clusters are coming the labs
are going to have more compute for training they're going to utilize this but it's not a given and it's
like I I've seen so much progress that I expect it and I expect a little bit bigger models and I expect
I would say it's more like we will see a two thousand dollar subscription this year we've seen
two hundred dollar subscriptions it's like that can 10x again and these are the kind of things they
could come and they're all downstream of this like bit bit bigger model that offers just a
little bit more cutting edge so you know it's reported that XAI is going to hit that one giggle-ot scale
early 26 and full two giggle-ot by year and how do you think they'll utilize that
in the context of scaling laws there's a lot of that inference there's a lot of that training
it ends up being all of the above so I think that all of your decisions when you're training a model
come back to pre-training so if you're going to scale our own model you still need to decide on
your architecture that enables this we're talking about like other architectures then using
different types of attention we're also talking about mixture of experts models this sparse nature
of MME models makes it much more efficient to do generation which becomes a big part of
post-training and it's like you need to have your architecture ready so that you can actually
scale up this compute and still think most of the compute is going in at pre-training because you
can still make a model better you still want to go and revisit this you still want the best
base model that you can and in a few years that I'll saturate and the the RL compute will just
go longer is there people would disagree with you that say basically pre-training is dead
it's all about scaling inference scaling post-training scaling context continuing learning
scaling data synthetic data people vibe that way and describe it in that way but I think it's not
the practice that is happening it's just a general vibe of people saying this thing's dead
is elsewhere so the low-hanging fruit in RL is elsewhere like for example we released our model in
November for every company has deadlines our deadline was like November 20th and our for that
our RL run was five days which compared to 2024 is a very long time to just be doing post-training
at a model of like 30 billion parameters it's not a big model and then in December we have another
release which is just we let the RL run for go for another three and a half weeks and the model
got notified better so we release it and like that's a big amount of time to just allocate to like
something that is going to be your peak for the year so it's like the types of decisions that
happen when they're training a model where they just like can't they can't leave it forever you have
to keep you have to keep pulling in the improvements you have from your researchers so that's like
you redo pre-training you'll do this post-training for a month but then you need to give it to your
users you need to do safety testing so it was kind of just like I think there's a lot in place
that reinforces the cycle of just keep updating the models there's things to improve you get a new
compute cluster that's let's you do something maybe more stable or faster it's like you hear a lot
about black well having rollout issues where at AI2 most of the models were pre-training around like
one to 2000 GPUs but when you're pre-training on 10,000 or 100,000 GPUs you hit very different
failures so GPUs are known to break in weird ways and doing 100,000 GPU run is like you're
pretty much guaranteed to always have at least one GPU that is down and you need to have your
training code handle that redundancy which is just a very different problem whereas like what we're
doing like I'm playing with post-training on djx bark or you have your book is like or people
learning ML it's like what they're battling to train these biggest models is just like
mass distributed scale and it's a very different but that's somewhat different than like are
like that's a systems problem in order to enable the scaling laws especially a pre-training you
need all of these GPUs at once when we shift to reinforcement learning it actually lends itself
to heterogeneous compute because you have many copies of the model and to do a primer for a language
model reinforcement learning what you're doing is you have two sets of GPUs one is you can call it
the actor and one you call the learner the learner is where your actual reinforcement learning
updates are going to do these are traditionally policy gradient algorithms proximal policy
optimization ppo and group relative policy optimization grpo are the two popular classes
and on the other side you're going to have actors which are generating completions and these
completions are the things that you're going to grade so reinforcement learning is all about
optimizing reward and in practice what you can do is that you can have a lot of different actors
in different parts of the world doing different types of problems and then you send it back to this
highly network compute cost to do this actual learning where you take the where you take the gradients
and you need to have a tightly mesh network where you can do different types of parallelism and
spread out your model for efficient training so there's just like a lot of every different type of
training and serving has these considerations you need to scale like we talked about pre-training we
talked about rl and then inference time scaling is like how do you serve a model that's thinking for
an hour to a hundred million users like i don't really know about that but i know that's a hard
problem in a order to give people this intelligence there's all the systems problems and we need more
compute and you need more stable compute to do it but your bullish on all of these kinds of
scaling is what i'm hearing on the inference on the reasoning even on the pre-training yeah so that's
a big kind of worms here but so that basically two the knobs are the training and the inference
scaling where you can get gains and so in a in a world where we had let's say infinite compute
resources you want to do all of them about like so you have training you have inference scaling
and training is like a hierarchy it's pre-training mid-training post-training changing the model size
more training data making training a bigger model gives you more knowledge in the model then the model
let's say it has a better it's like a better base model back in the day or we
still we call it foundation model and it unlocks so you but you don't let's say have the model
be able to solve your most complex task tasks during pre-training or after pre-training you
still have these other unknock phases where you have mid-training or non-context for example
post-training with a lot we are that unlocks capabilities that the model has in terms of just
knowledge in the pre-training and I think sure if you so do more pre-training you get a
better base model that you can unlock later but like Nathan said it just becomes too expensive so
we don't have infinite compute so you have to decide do I want to spend that compute more on
making the model larger but you know it's like a trade-off it's like in an ideal world you want to
do all of them and I think in that sense scaling is still pretty much alive you would still get a
better model but like we saw with GPT 4.5 it's just not worth it I mean it's like because you can
let's say you can unlock more performance with other techniques at that current moment especially
if you look at inference scaling that's one of the biggest gains this year with 01 where it took
a smaller model further than pre-training a larger model like GPT 4.5 so it's like I wouldn't say
pre-training scaling is that it's just like there are other more attractive ways to scale right now
at the moment but at some point you know you will still want to make some progress on the pre-training
the thing is also to consider where you by do you want to spend your money if you spend it more
on the pre-training it's like a fixed cost you train the model and then it has this capability
forever you can always use it and so forth with inference scaling you don't spend money during
training you spend money later per query and then it's also like the math how long is my model
going to be on the market if I replace that in half a year maybe it's not worth spending
5 million 10 million 100 million dollars on the training it longer maybe it's just I will just
do more inference scaling and get the performance from there it may cost me two million in terms
of user queries it becomes a question of how many users you have and then doing the math and I
think that's also where it's interesting where GPD is in a position I think they have a lot of users
where they need to go a bit cheaper where they have that GPT 5 model that is a bit smaller other
companies that have as if your customers have other other trade-offs for example there was also
the math Olympiad or some of these these math problems where GPD or maybe they had a proprietary
model and I'm pretty sure it's just like a model that has been maybe fine tuned a little bit more
but most of it was during inference scaling to achieve the peak performance in certain task where
you don't need that all the time and but yeah long story short I do think all of these pre-training
mid-training post-training inference scaling they are all still things you want to do it's just
finding at the moment in this year it's finding the right ratio that gives you the best bang for
the bark basically I think this might be a good place to define pre-training mid-training and post-training
so pre-training is the classic training one next token prediction at a time you have a big
corpus of data and Nathan and I probably also have some very interesting insights there because of
almost three it's a big portion of the paper focuses on the right data mix so pre-training is
essentially just you know trained across entropy loss training on next token prediction on a
vast corpus of internet data books papers and so forth it has changed a little bit over the years
in a sense people used to throw in everything they can now it's not just raw data it's also synthetic
data where people read let's say rephrase certain things so synthetic data doesn't necessarily
mean purely AI made up data it's also taking something from an article Wikipedia article and then
rephrasing it as a Q&A question or summarizing it re-wording it and making a better data that way
because I think of it also like with humans if someone let's say reads a book compared to a messy
I don't know offense but like read it post or something like that I do think you learn
I think it's going to be a post about this
well read it data is very coveted excellent for training you just have to filter it yeah
yeah and I think that's the idea I think it's like if someone took that and rephrases that in a
let's say it's a more concise and structured way I think it's higher quality data that gets the
and maybe the same you get the same a lot of it at the end but it gets there faster it trains faster
because the let's say if the grandma and the punctuation is correct it already learns the correct
wave versus getting information from a messy way and then learning later how to correct that and
stuff like that so I think that is how pre-training evolved and how how still while
while scaling still works is that it's not about just the amount of data it's also the tricks to
make that data better for you in a sense and then mid-training is I mean it used to be called
pre-training it's I think it's called mid-training because it was awkward to have pre-training
and post-training but nothing in the middle right it sounds a bit weird you have pre-training and
post-training but what's the actual training so the mid-training is usually similar to
pre-training but you know it's a bit more I would say specialized in pre-training it's the same
algorithm but what you do is you focus for example on long contact like it's one example you have
long context documents the reason you don't do that during just pre-training is because you don't
have that many long context documents we have a specific phase and one problem of LLM's is also
still it's a neural network it has the problem of catastrophic forgetting so you teach it something
it forgets other things and you want to it's not 100% forgetting but you know it's like no
freelance you can it's also the same with humans if you ask me some math I learned 10 years ago I
don't know I would have to look at it again Nathan was actually saying that he's consuming so
much content that there's a catastrophic forgetting issue yeah I'm like trying to learn so much
about AI I was like I was learning about pre-training parallelism I'm like I lost something and I
don't know what it was I don't want to unvermorphize LLMs but it's I think the same kind of in that
sense how humans learned I mean the quantity is not always better because yeah it's like being
selective and I in the mid-training is being selective in terms of quality content at the end so
the last thing the LMS scene is the quality stuff and then post-training is all the fine tuning
supervised fine tuning DPO reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards with human feedback and
so forth so the refinement stages and it's also interesting it's like the cost thing right I mean
it's like pre-training you spend a lot of money on that right now RL a bit less RL you don't really
I would say teach it knowledge it's more like unlocking the knowledge it's more like a skill
learning like how to solve problems with the knowledge that it has from pre-training there are
actually three papers this year or last year 2025 on RL for pre-training but I I mean I don't
think anyone does that in production toy examples for now for example it's right but to generalize
how RL post-training is more like the skill unlock where pre-training is like soaking up the
knowledge essentially a few things that could be helpful for people a lot of people like
they have think of synthetic data as being bad for training the models you mentioned like the
deep sea get a almost OCR which is optical character recognition paper a lot of labs did AI2 had one
had multiple and the reason that each of these labs have these is because there's vast amounts
of PDFs and other digital documents on the web that are in formats that aren't encoded with
text easily so use these almost these or deep sea OCR and we called our almost ER to extract
what can be trillions of tokens of candidate data for pre-training and pre-training data set
size is on the order of trillions is measuring trillions of tokens smaller models from researchers
can be something like five to ten trillion when is documented going up to like 50 trillion and
there's rumors that these closed labs can go to like a hundred trillion tokens and just getting
this potential data to put in I think they they have a very big funnel and then the data you actually
train the model on is a small percentage of this like the since this character recognition data
would be described as synthetic data for pre-training in a lab and then there's also the things like
chat GPT now gives wonderful answers and you can train on those best answers and that's synthetic data
it's very different than like early chat GPT lots of hallucinations data when people became
grounded in synthetic data one interesting question is if I recall correctly almost three was trained
with less data than specifically some other open weight models maybe even almost two but you
still got better performance and that might be one of the examples how the data help it's mostly
down to data quality I think if we had more compute we would train for longer I think we ultimately
see that as a like just like something we would want to do and especially with big models you need
to have more compute because we talked about having more parameters we talked about knowledge and
essentially there's a ratio where big models can absorb more from data and then you're going to
you get more benefit out of this it's it's it's like one of these any logarithmic graph in your
mind is like a small model will level off sooner if you're measuring trends of tokens and bigger
bigger models need more but mostly is we aren't training that big of models right now AI2 and getting
the highest quality data we can is the natural starting point is there something to be said about
the topic of data quality is there some low hanging fruit there still where the quality could be
improved it's like turning the crank so I think historically in the open there's been like a canonical
best pre-training data set that has moved around between who has the most recent one or the best
of the recent effort like AI2's dolmo was very early with the first olmo and hugging face
side fine web and there's a DCLM project which has been kind of like a which is it stands for
data comp language model there's been data comp for other machine learning projects and they have
had a very strong data set and a lot of it is the internet is becoming fairly closed off so we have
common crawl which I think is hundreds of trillions of tokens and you filter it and it looks like
being a lot of scientific work where you're training classifiers and making decisions based on
how do you prune down this this data set into the highest quality stuff and the stuff that suits
your tasks so previously language models were tested a lot more on like knowledge and just kind
of conversational things but now they're expected to do math and code so to train a reasoning model
you need to remix your whole data set and there's a lot of actually wonderful scientific methods here
where you can you can like take your gigantic data set you sample a lot of really tiny things from
different sources you say you have GitHub stack exchange reddit Wikipedia you can sample small
things from them and you train small models on each of these mixes and measure their performance
on your evaluations and you can just do like basically an ear regression and it's like here's your
optimal data set but if your evaluations change your data set changes a lot so a lot of umote 3 was
new sources for reasoning to be better at math and code and then you do this mixing procedure
and it gives you the answer and I think that's a lot of that's happened at labs this year's like
there's new hot things whether it's like coding environments or web navigation and you just
need to bring in new data you need to change your whole pre-training so your post-training can work
better and stuff like this and this like the constant read revolution and the re-determining of what
they care about as they're for their models are there fun anecdotes of what sources of data
are particularly high quality that we wouldn't expect you mentioned reddit sometimes can be a source
reddit was very useful I think that um like pdf's is definitely one especially archive yeah so like
a i2 has run semantics call it for a long time which is a um like I would you can say as a competitor
google scholarly with a lot more features and to do this a i2 has found and scraped a lot of pdf's
for openly accessible papers that might not be um like behind the closed paid garden of us are
in publisher so like truly open scientific pdf's and if you like you sit on all of these and you
process it and you can get value out of it and I think that like a lot of that style of work has been
done by the frontier labs much earlier and it's just like you need to have a pretty skilled researcher
that understands how things change models and they bring it in and they clean it and it's
that's a lot of labor that like I think of a lot of frontier labs when they scale researchers a lot
more goes into data you have people like if you want to if you join a frontier lab and you want to
impact this best way to do it is just make find new data that's better and then like the fancy
glamorous algorithmic things like figuring out how to make a one is like the sexiest thought of a
scientist if like oh I figured out the scale rl and there's a group that did that but I think
in most of the contributions is like I'm going to make the data better or I'm going to make
the infrastructure better so that everybody in my team can run experiments 5% faster at the same time
I think it's also one of the closest guarded secrets what your training data is for legal reasons
and so there's also I think a lot of work that goes into hiding what your trading data was
essentially like trying the model to not give away the sources because of legal reasons the other
thing to be complete is that some people are trying to train on only licensed data where common
crawls is a scrape of like the whole internet so if I host multiple websites I'm happy to have them
train language models but I'm not explicitly licensing what governs it and therefore this
like the common crawls largely unlicensed which means that your consent really hasn't been provided
for how to use the data there's another idea where you can train language models only on data that
has been licensed explicitly so that the kind of governing contract is provided and I'm not sure
if Aprodis is the copyright thing or the license thing I know that the reason that they did it was for
an EU compliance thing where they wanted to make sure that their model fit one of those checks
and also on that note also for example there's also the distinction between the licensing so
some people like you said they just purchased the license I'd say they buy a book online let's say
an Amazon Kindle book or let's say a mining book or something and then use that in a training
data and that is like the gray zone because you paid for the content and you might want to train it
but then there are also restrictions where even that shouldn't be allowed and so that it is like
where where it gets a bit fuzzy and yeah I think that is right now it's still a hot topic and
also big companies like OpenAI they approached private companies for their proprietary data and
private companies they become more and more that's a protective of that data because they know
this is going to be my mode in a few years and I do think that's like the interesting question where
if LMS become more commoditized and I think a lot of people learn about LMS that there will be
more people able to train alarms of course they are infrastructure challenges but if you think of
big industries like pharmaceutical industries law finance industries I do think they at some point
will hire people from other frontier labs to build their in-house models on their proprietary data
which will be then again another unlock with pre-training that is currently not there because even if
you want to do you can't get that data you can't get access to clinical trials most of the time in
these types of things so I do think scaling in that sense might be still pretty much alive if you
also look in domain-specific applications because we are still right now in this year just looking
at general purpose LMS on on chatchipd and throttpick and so forth they are just general purpose they're
not even I think scratching the surface of what an LMS can do if it is really specifically
trained and designed for a specific task I think on the data thing this is one of the things
where like this happened in 2025 we totally forget it is in throttpick lost in court and was owed
at $1.5 billion to authors and throttpick I think bought thousands of books and scanned them and was
cleared legally for that because they bought the books and that is kind of going through the system
and on the other side they also tormented some books and I think this torrenting was the path
where the court said that they were then culpable to pay this billions of dollars to authors
which is just like such a mind-boggling lawsuit that kind of just came and went like that is so much
money from the VCE ecosystem these are court cases that will define the future of human civilization
because it's clearly that data drives a lot of this and there's this very complicated human
tension of I mean you can empathize you're both authors yeah yeah there's some degree to which
I mean you put your heart and soul and your sweat and tears into the writing that you do
uh it feels a little bit like theft for somebody to train your data without giving you credit
and they're like Nathan said also two layers to it someone might buy the book and then train on it
which is could be argued fair or not fair but then the three straight up companies who
use pirated books where it's not even compensating the author is that that is I think where
people got a bit angry about it specific it has to be some kind of competition scheme this is like
moving towards towards something like Spotify streaming did originally for music you know what
that competition look like you have to define those kinds of models you have to think through all of that
one other thing I think people are generally curious about it I'd love to get your thoughts
as LLM's are used more and more if you look at even archive but GitHub more and more of the data
is generated by LLM's what do you do in that kind of world is how big of a problem is that
larger just problems in infrastructure and systems but from an AI point of view it's
kind of inevitable so it's basically LLM generated data that's curated by humans essentially right
yes and I think that a lot of open source contributors are legitimately burning out if you have
a popular open source repo somebody's like oh I want to do open source AI it's good for my career
and they just vibe code something they throw it into the you might get more than an idea
so I have a case study here I have a repository called ml extend did I develop as a student
around 15 years 10 years ago and there's some reasonably popular libraries still for certain
algorithms I think especially like frequent data mining stuff and there was recently I think
two or three people who submitted a lot of PRs in a very short amount of time I do think
LLM's have been involved in submitting these PRs me as the maintainer that two things first
I'm a little overwhelmed like I don't have time to read through it because especially it's an
older library that is not a priority for me at the same time I kind of also appreciated because
I think something people forget is it's not just using the LLM there's still a human you have a
human layer that verifies something and and that is in a sense also how data is labeled right so
that's like one of the most expensive things is getting labeled data for RL back in human feedback
phases and this is kind of like that where it goes through phases and then you get actually higher
quality data out of it you know it's all I don't mind it in a sense it can feel overwhelming but
I do think there is also value in that it feels like there's a fundamental difference between raw
LLM generated data and LLM generated data with human and loop that does some kind of verification
even if the verification is a small percent of the lines of code I think this goes with anything
like where people think also sometimes oh yeah I can just use an LLM to learn about xyz which
is true you can but there might be a person who is an expert who might have used an LLM to write
a specific code there is kind of like this human work that went into it to make it nice and
throwing out the not so nice part to make it to kind of like pre-digest it for you and that saves you
time and I think that's that's the value add where you have someone filtering things or even using
the LLM correctly I think this is still labor that that you get for free with you for example read
an article let's say sub-stake article I could maybe ask an LLM to give me opinions on that but I
wouldn't even maybe know what to ask I think there is still value in reading that article compared to
me going to the LLM because you are the expert you select what knowledge is actually spot on should
be included and you give me this very this this executive summary and this is kind of a huge value
add because now I don't have to waste three five hours to go through this myself maybe get some
incorrect information and so on and so I think that's also where the future still is for writers even
though they are LLMs that expert can kind of like save you time it's kind of fascinating actually watch
I did and I'm sure you guys do this but for me to look at the difference in the summary
and the original content even if it's a page long summary of a page long content
it's interesting to see how the summary LLB summary takes the edge off like what what is the signal
it removes from the thing the voice this what I talk about a lot voice well voice I'd love to hear
what you mean by voice that's really powerful but sometimes there's like literally insights
like in removing an insight you're actually fundamentally changing the meaning of the thing
so I continuously disappointed how bad LLMs are at really getting to the core insights which is
what a great summary does yeah even if you go and I have these extensive extremely elaborate
problems where I'm like really trying to dig for the insights and it's still not quite there which
I mean that's a whole deep philosophical question about what is human knowledge and wisdom and
what does it mean to be insightful and so on but when you talk about the voice what do you mean
so when I write I think a lot of what I'm trying to do is take what you think as a researcher which
is very raw which a researcher is trying to encapsulate an idea at the frontier of their understanding
and they're trying to put what is a feeling into words and I think that my writing I tried to do
this is the writing which makes it come across as raw but also high information in in a way that
is like some people will get it in some won't and that's kind of the nature of research and I think
this is something that language models don't do well particularly they're all trained with
this reinforcement learning from human feedback which is designed to take feedback from a lot of people
and in a way average how the model behaves from this and I think that there's it's going to be hard
for a model to be very incisive when there's that sort of filter in it and I think this is kind of a
wonderful fundamental problem for researchers in RLA Jeff is like this provides so much utility
in making the models better but also the problem formulation is kind of like there's this not in it
that you can't get past so that's what I think of is like these language models don't have this
prior and their deep expression that they're trying to get at I don't think it's impossible to do
I think there's stories of models that really shock people and I think of like I would love to have
tried Bing Sydney and does like does that have more voice because it would so often go off the
rails on people and what is historically obviously a scary way like telling a reporter to leave
its wife is a crazy model to potentially put in general general adoption but that's kind of like
a trade off like is this RLA Jeff process like in some ways adding limitations. That's a terrifying
place to be as one of these frontier labs and companies because millions of people are using them
there was a lot of backlash last year with the GPT-40 getting removed and I personally never
used the model but I've talked to people at OpenAI were there to the point where they like get emails
from users that might be detecting subtle differences in the deployments in the middle of the night
and they email them and they're like my friend is different and they like find these people
employ emails and send them things because they're so attached to this set what is a set of
model weights and a configuration that is deployed to the users we see this with TikTok you open it
I don't use TikTok it's supposedly in like five minutes the algorithm gets you it's like it's
locked in and I don't like those are language models doing recommendations like I think there are
ways that you can do this with a language model within like five minutes of chatting with it the
model just gets you and that is something that people aren't really ready for like I think like
like don't give that to kids like don't give that to kids at least until we know what's happening.
There's also going to be this mechanism what's going to happen with these LLMs is they're used
more and more unfortunately the nature of the human condition is such that people commit suicide
and so what journalists would do is they would report extensively on the people who commit suicide
and they would very likely link it to the LLMs because they have that date about the conversations
if you're really struggling in your life if you're depressed if you're thinking about suicide
you're going to probably talk to LLMs about it and so what journalists will do is they will say
well the suicide was committed because of the LLM and that's going to lead to the companies
because of legal issues and so on more and more and more taking the edge off of the LLM
so it's going to be as generic as possible it's so difficult to operate in this space because of
course you don't want an LLM to cause harm to humans at that level but also
this is also the nature of the human experience is to have a rich conversation, a fulfilling
conversation and one that challenges you from which you grow you need that edge and that that's
something extremely difficult for AI researchers on the RLHF front to actually have to solve
because you're actually dealing with the human condition. Like a lot of researchers at these
companies are so well motivated and they definitely they like some anthropic and open AI or
culturally so want to do good through this for the world and there is it's such a like I'm like
I don't want to work on this because on the one hand a lot of people see AI as a health ally is
somebody they can talk to about their health confidentially but then it bleeds all the way into this
like talking about mental health and things where it's heartbreaking that this will push
like be the thing where somebody goes over the edge but other people might be saved and I'm like I
there's things that as a researcher training models it's like I don't want to train image
generation models and release them openly because I don't want to enable somebody to have a tool
on their laptop that can harm other people like I don't have the infrastructure of my company to do
that safely but it's like like there's a lot of the areas like this which just it needs people that
will approach it with the complexity and just kind of conviction of like it's just such a hard problem.
But also we as a society as users of these technologies need to make sure that we're having the
complicated conversation about it versus just fear, mongering. Big tech is causing harm to humans
or stealing your data all that kind of stuff. It's more complicated than that and you're right.
There's a very large number of people inside these companies, many of which you know,
many of which I know they're deeply care about helping people. They are considering the full human
experience of people from across the world not just Silicon Valley. People across the United States,
people across the world what that means, what their needs are. It's really difficult to design
one system that is able to help all these different kinds of people across the different age groups,
cultures, mental states, mental conditions, all that kind of stuff.
I wish that the timing of AI was different with their relationship of big tech to the average
person. So like big tech's reputation was so low and with how AI is so expensive, it's like
inevitably going to be a big tech thing where it takes so many resources and people say that US
quote unquote betting the economy on AI with this build out. And it's like to have these V
intertwined at the same time. It just makes versus such a hard communication environment. It would
be good for me to go talk to more people in the world that hate big tech and see AI as a continuation
of this. And one of the things you actually recommend one of the antidotes that you talk about
is to find agency in this whole system as opposed to sort of sitting back in a powerless way
consuming the AI slop as quickly rapidly takes over the internet. More fine agency by using it to
build stuff, build apps, build. So you want that actually helps you build the intuition, but
to it's empowering because you can understand how it works, what the weaknesses are, it gives
your voice power to say like this is fucked up, this is bad, this is bad, use of the technology,
this is good use of technology. And you're more plugged into the system then. So you can understand
a better and you can steer it better as a specific. I think it's a good point. You brought up
agency. I set off ignoring it and saying, okay, I'm not going to use it. I think it's probably
long term healthier to say, okay, it's out there. I can't put it back, you know, like internet
computers back then when they came out. How do I make best use of it? And how does it help me to
up level myself? The one thing I worry here though is like if you just fully use it for something
you love to do, the thing you love to do is not no longer there. And that could potentially
have here like lead to burnout. For example, if I use an LM to do all my coding for me, now there's
no coding. I'm just managing something that is coding for me two years. Let's say later if I just
do that eight hours a day, I have something called for me. Do I feel fulfilled still like, is this like,
yeah, I mean, is this like hurting me in terms of being excited about my job, excited about
what I'm doing. Am I still proud to build something? So there's on that topic of enjoyment. It's
quite interesting, which is just throw this in there that there's this recent survey of about 791
professional developers, professional meaning 10 plus years of experience. That's a long time.
Yeah. That's a junior developer. Yeah, and this day and age. So there's also here many fronts are
surprising. So they break it down by junior senior developers, but I mean, it just shows
that both junior senior developers use AI generated code in code day ship. So this is not just for fun,
sort of intermediate kind of learning things. This is code day ship. And so it's 25% meant like
most of them use around 50% or more. And what's interesting is for the category of over 50%
of your code that your ship is AI generated senior developers are much more likely to do so. But
you don't want AI to take away the thing you love. I think it speaks to my experience. These
particulars also I'm about to say. So together about 80% of people find it either somewhat more
enjoyable or significantly more enjoyable to use AI as part of the work. I think it depends on the
task from my personal usage, for example, I have a website where I sometimes tweak things on
the website. I personally don't enjoy this. So in that sense, if the AI can help me to implement
something on my website, I'm all here for it. It's great. But then at the same time when I solve a
complex problem, well, if there's a bug and I hunt this bug and I find the bug, it's the best feeling
in the world. It's like you get so much joy like, oh, it's like you feel like great. But now if you
don't even think about thinking about the bug, you just go directly to the LLM, well, you never have
this kind of feeling, right? But then there could be the middle ground where well, you try yourself,
you can't find it, you use the LLM and then you don't get frustrated because it helps you and you
move on to something that you enjoy. And so I think looking at these statistics, I think also the
difference is what is not factor in its averaging over all the different scenarios where we don't
know if it's for the core task or if it's for something mundane that people would not have enjoyed.
Otherwise, so in a sense, AI is really great for doing mundane things that take a lot of work.
So for example, my wife the other day, she has like a podcast for like book discussions, a book club,
and she was like transferring the show notes from Spotify to YouTube. And then the links somehow broke.
And she had in some episodes because it is custom many books like 100 links or something
and it would have been really painful to go in there and fix each link manually. And so I suggested,
hey, let's try Chatchy-Bity, we copied the text into Chatchy-Bity and it fixed them. And instead of
two hours going from link to link fixing that, you know, it made that type of work much more seamless,
there was no frustration fixed. I think everyone has a use case where AI is useful for something
like that that would be really boring, really mundane. I, for me personally, since we're talking about
coding, and you mentioned debugging, a lot of the sources in the enjoyment for me on the
more in the cursor side than the clogged code side is the, I have a friend, I have a co, what's that
called, a pair programmer, like it's less lonely. You made debugging sound like this great joy.
No, I would say debugging is like a drink of water after you've been going through a desert
for days. So like you skip the whole desert part where you're suffering. So like there,
sometimes it's nice to have a friend who can't really find the bug but can give you some
intuition about the code and you're together with that friend going to the desert and then
together find that drink of water. So at least for me, maybe speaks to the loneliness of the
programming experience, it's that is a source of joy. It's maybe also related to delayed
gratification. I'm a person who, you know, even as a kid, I like the idea of Christmas presents,
having them getting them better than actually getting the presents. I would look forward to the day
I get the presents, but then it's over and I'm disappointed and maybe it's something like also
with, let's say food. I think food tastes better when you're really hungry. And with, yeah, you're
right with debugging, it is not always, you know, great. It's like often frustrating, but then if
you can solve it, then it's great. But there's also like a sweet goldy lock zone, if it's too
hard and it's, you know, wasting your time. But I think that is another challenge though. How will
people learn? I mean, the chart we looked at, we saw that more senior developers are shipping more
AI generated code than the junior ones. And I think it's very interesting because intuitively,
you would think it's the junior developers because they don't know, let's say, how to do the thing
yet because they are more junior. And so they use AI to do that thing. It could either mean the AI is
good enough yet to solve that task, but it could also mean experts are more effective at using it.
They know where and better how to use it and review the code and they trust the code then more.
And so I think one issue in the society in the future will be though, how do you become an expert
if you never try to do the thing yourself? And I think one way that's always like for me,
how I learn is by trying things myself like math textbooks. If you look at the solutions,
yeah, you learn something, but I think you learn actually better if you try first and then
you appreciate the solution differently because you know how to put it into your mental framework.
And if elements are here all the time, would you actually go through the length at struggling? Would
you be willing to struggle? Because struggle is not nice, right? I mean, it's struggling. And
if you use the element to do everything at some point, you will never really take the next step.
And then you will maybe not get that unlock that you would get as an expert using an LLM.
So it's like, you know, it's like, I think there's like a goalie locks with spot where maybe
maybe the trick here is you make dedicated offline time where you study two hours a day and the rest
of the day use LLMs. But I think it's important also for people to still invest in themselves in my
opinion, to not just, you know, LLM everything. Yeah, there is. And we together a civilization that we
each individually have to find that goalie locks on and in the program and context as developers.
Now we've had this fascinating conversation that started with pre-training and mid-training.
Let's get to post-training. A lot of fun stuff in post-training. So what are some of the interesting
ideas in post-training? The biggest one from 2025 is learning this reinforcement learning with
verifiable rewards. You can scale up the training there, which means doing a lot of this kind of iterative,
generate grade loop. And that lets the models learn both interesting behaviors on the tool use
and software side. This can be searching, running commands on their own and seeing outputs and then
also that training enables this inference time scaling very nicely. And it just turned out that this
paradigm was very nicely linked in this where it's this kind of RL training enables inference
time scaling. But inference time scaling could have been found in different ways. So it's kind of
this perfect storm of the models change a lot. And the way that they're trained is a major factor
in doing so. And this has changed how people approach post-training dramatically. Can you describe
RLVR popularly by deep seek R1? Can you describe how it works? Yeah, fun fact. I was on the team that
came up with the term RLVR, which is from our two-lead-three work before deep seek, which is we don't
take a lot of credit for being the people to popularize the scaling RL. But it is fun as
what academics get as an aside is the ability to name and influence the discourse because the closed
labs can only say so much that one of the things you can do as an academic is like you might not have
the compute to train the model, but you can frame things in a way that ends up being. I describe it
as like a community can come together around this RLVR term, which is very fun. And then deep seek is
the people that did the training breakthrough, which is they scaled the reinforcement learning,
which was you'd have the model generate answers and then grade the completion if it was right. And then
that accuracy is your reward for reinforcement learning. So reinforcement learning is
classically an agent that acts in an environment and the environment gives it a state and a
reward back. And you try to maximize this reward. In the case of language models, the reward is
normally accuracy on a set of verifiable tasks, whether it's math problems, coding tests,
and it starts gippling with things like factual domains like that is also in some ways verifiable
or constraints on your instruction like respond only with words that start with A. Like all of these
things are verifiable in some way. And the core idea of this is you find a lot more of these
problems that are verifiable and you let the model try it many times while taking these RL steps,
these RL gradient updates, the infrastructure evolved from this reinforcement learning from human
feedback. Where in that era, the score they were trying to optimize was a learned reward model
of aggregate human preferences. So you kind of change the problem domains and that let the
optimization go on to much bigger scales, which kind of kickstarted a major change in what the
models can do and how people use them. What kind of domains are of the RL amenable to?
Math and code are the famous ones and then there's a lot of work kind of on what is called a
verabrix, which is related to a word people might have heard as L on as a judge, which is like for
each problem, all of a set of problems in my trading data set. I'll then have another language model
and ask it, what would a good answer to this problem look like? And then you could try the
problem a bunch of times over and over again and assign a score based on this rubric. So that's
not necessarily verifiable like a math and code domain, but this rubric's idea and other scientific
problems that it might be a little bit more vague is where a lot of the attention is where they're
trying to push this set of methods into these kind of more open-ended domains where the models
can learn a lot more. I think that's called reinforcement running with AI feedback, right? That's the
older term from it that was coined and and thropics constitutional AI paper. So it's like a lot
of these things come in cycles. Also just one step back for the RL VR. So I think the interesting
beautiful thing here is that you you asked the LM let's say a math question and then you know
the correct answer and you let the LM like you said figure it out, but how it does it? I mean you
don't really constrain it much. There are some constraints you can add like use the same language,
don't switch between Spanish and English, but let's say you're pretty much hands off you only
give the question and the answer and then the LM has to you know just the task to arrive at the
right answer, but the beautiful thing here is what happens in practice is that the LM will do a step-by-step
description like you know like a student or like a mathematician how you would derive the solution,
it will give you or it will use those steps and that helps actually the model to improve its own
accuracy. And then like you said the inference scaling. So inference scaling loosely means basically
spending more compute during using the LM during inference and here the inference scaling is
that the model would use more tokens and also I think in the R1 paper they showed the long
are they trained the model the longer the responses are, they grow over time they use more tokens.
So it becomes more expensive, becomes more expensive for simple tasks, but these explanations they
help the model with the accuracy. They're also interesting lot of papers showing but the model
explains does not necessarily have to be correct or maybe it's even unrelated to the answer,
but for some reason it still helps the model like this is the fact that it is
explaining and I think it's also again I don't want to unthroploma-fice these LM's but it's kind
of like how we humans operate right. If there's a complex math problem let's say in a math class
you usually have a notebook paper and you do it step-by-step you cross out things and the model also
self-corrects and that that was I think the aha moment in the R1 paper they called it aha moment
because the model itself recognized it made a mistake and then said oh I did something wrong and
so let me try and I think that's just so cool that this falls out of just giving it the correct
answer and having it figure out how to do it that it kind of does in a sense what a human would do
although LM don't think like humans it's kind of like an interesting coincidence and then
another nice side effect is it's great for us humans often to see these steps it builds trust
but also we learn we can double check things. There's a lot in here I think some of the debate
there's been a lot of debate this year on if the language models like these aha I think the aha
moments are kind of fake because in pre-training you essentially have seen the whole internet so you
have definitely seen people explaining their work even verbally like a transcript of a math lecture
you try this oh I messed this up and what reinforcement learning is this RLVR is very good at doing
is amplifying these behaviors because they're very useful in enabling the model to think longer
and to check its work and I agree that it is very beautiful that this training kind of the model
learns to amplify this in a way that is just so useful at the final answers being better.
I can give you also a hands on example I was training the Grand 3 base model with RLVR on math 500
the base model had an accuracy of about 15% just 50 steps like in a few minutes with RLVR
the model went from 15% to 50% accuracy and the model you can't tell me it's learning anything
about fundamentally what math in the plan. The plan example is weird because there's been two
papers this year one of which I was on that talks about data contamination in plan and specifically
that they train on a lot of this special mid-training phase that we just have like a minute on
and it's weird so they train on problems that are almost identical exactly and so you can see
that basically the RL it's not teaching the model any new knowledge of what math you can't do
that in 50 steps so the knowledge is already there and the pre-training you're just unlocking it.
I still disagree with the kind of premise because there's a lot of weird complexities that you
can't prove because one of the things that points to weirdness is that if you take the Quen 3 so
called base model and you could you could google on the screen you could google like math data set
hugging phase and you could take a problem and what you do if you put it into Quen 3 base
the all these math problems have a word so be like Alice has five apples and takes one and gives
three to whoever and there these word problems with these Quen base models why people are suspicious
of them is if you change the numbers but keep the words Quen will produce like a very high death
without tools will produce a very high accuracy like decimal representation of the answer which means
at some time it was shown problems that were almost identical to the test set and it was using
tools to get a very high precision answer but a language model without tools will never actually
have this so it's kind of been this big debate in the research community is like how much of these
reinforce learning papers that are training on Quen and measuring specifically on this like math
benchmark where there's been multiple papers talking about contamination is like how much can
you believe them and I think this is what caused the reputation of our LVR being about formatting
because you can get these gains so quickly and therefore must already be in the model but there's
a lot of complexity here that we it's not really like controlled experimentation so I mean don't
really know but if it weren't true I would say distillation wouldn't work right I mean distillation
can work to some extent but the thing is that is I think the biggest problem and I'm research
this contamination because we don't know what's in the data it's unless you have a new data set
it's really impossible and the same you mentioned on math or the math data set which is
give a question and an answer and an explanation is given but then also even something simpler like
mmu which is a multiple choice benchmark if you just change the format slightly like I don't know
you use a dot instead of a parenthesis or something like that the model accuracy will vastly
differ I think that that could be like a model issue rather than a general issue it's not even
malicious by the developers of the LLM like hey we want to cheat at that benchmark it's just
it has seen something at some point and I think the only fair way to avoid an LLM is to have a new
benchmark that is after the cutoff date when the LLM was deployed.
Kimmelayow what would be the sort of the recipe of all those things that would be going to
post-training and you mentioned our LLVR was a really exciting effective thing maybe we should
elaborate RLHF still has it a really important component to play what kind of other ideas are
they're on post-training. I think you can kind of take this in order I think you can
view it as what made 01 which is this first reasoning model possible or what will the latest model be
and they actually have you're going to have similar interventions at these where you start with
mid-training and the thing that is rumored to enable 01 and similar models is really careful data
curation where you're providing a broad set of like what is called reasoning traces which is just
the model generating words in a forward process that is reflecting like breaking down a problem
into intermediate steps and trying to solve them so mid-training you need to have
data that is similar to this to make it so that when you move into post-training
primarily with this verifiable rewards it can learn and then what is happening today is your
figuring out which problems to give the model and how long you can train it for and like how
much inference you can enable the model to use when solving these verifiable problems so as models
get better certain problems are no longer like the model will solve them 100% of the time and
therefore there's very little signal in this if we pull if we look at the GRPO equation this one
is famous for this because essentially the reward given to the agent is based on how good a given
action action is a completion is relative to the other answers to the same problem so if all the
problems get the same answer there's no signal in these types of algorithms so what they're doing is
they're finding harder problems which is why you hear about things like scientific domains which is
like that's so hard like getting anything right there if you have a lab or something it just
generates so many tokens or much harder software problems so the frontier models are all
pushing into these harder domains and they can train on more problems and the model will learn more
skills at once the early Jeff link to this is kind of like early Jeff has been and still is kind
of like the finishing touch on the models where it makes the models more useful by improving the
organization or style or tone there's different things that resonates to different audiences like
some people like a really quirky model and early Jeff could be good at enabling that personality
and some people hate this like markdown bulleted list thing that the models do but it's actually
really good for quickly parsing information and early Jeff this human feedback stage is really great
for just get putting this into the model at the end of the day so it's what it made chat you
B.T. so magical for people and that use is actually remained fairly stable this formatting can also
help the models get better at math problems for example so it's like the border between style
and formatting and like the method that you use to answer a problem is actually they're all very
closely linked in terms of when you're training these models which is why early Jeff can still say
make a model better at math but these verifiable domains are much more direct process to doing this
because it's kind of makes more sense with the problem formulation which is why it kind of ends up
all forming together but to summarize it's like mid-training is give the model the skills it needs
to then learn rl and verify four words is let the model try a lot of time so put a lot of compute into
trial and error learning across hard problems and then early Jeff would be like finish the model make
it easy to use and kind of just round the model out can you comment on the model compute required for
rl the r it's only gotten up and up so I think grok four was famous for saying they use a similar
amount of compute for pre-training and post-training back to the scaling discussion they involve very
different hardware for scaling pre-training is very compute bound which is like this flops
discussion which is just how many matrix multiplications can you get through one time and because rl
you're generating these answers you're trying the model in the real world environments it ends up
being much more memory bound because you're generating long sequences and the attention mechanisms have
this behavior where you get a quadratic increase in memory as you're getting to longer sequences
so the compute becomes very different so you when in pre-training we would talk about a model I think
we go back to like the Biden administration executive order it's like 10 to the 25th flops to
train a model and if you're using flops in post-training it's a lot weirder because the reality is just like
how many hours are you allocating how many GPUs for and I think in terms of time the rl compute is
getting much closer because you just can't put it all into one system like pre-training is so
computationally dense where all the GPUs are talking to each other and it's extremely efficient
where rl has all these moving parts and it can just take a long time to generate a sequence of
a hundred thousand tokens like if you think about gbt 5.2 pro taking an hour it's like what if
you're training run has a sample for an hour and you have to make it so that's handled efficiently
so I think in GPU hours or just like wall clock hours the rl runs are probably approaching the
number of days as pre-training but they probably aren't using as many GPUs at the same time
there's rules of thumb wherein labs it's like you don't want your pre-training runs to last more
than like a month because they fail catastrophically and if you were planning a huge cluster to be held
for two months and then it fails on day 50 the opportunity cost of just so big so you kind of don't
want to just you people don't want to put all their eggs in one basket which is like gbt 4 was
like the ultimate yellow run and nobody ever wanted to do it before where it took like three months
to train and everybody was shocked that it worked where I think people are a little bit more cautious
and incremental now so rl vr is more let's say unlimited how much you can train to get still
benefit where rl hf because it's a preference tuning it you reach a certain point where it doesn't
really make sense to spend more rl budget on that so just step back with preference tuning so
there are multiple people that can give multiple let's say explanations for the same thing and they
can both be correct but at some point you learn a certain style and then it doesn't make sense to
you know iterate on it my favorite example is like if relatives ask me what laptop they should buy
I give them an explanation or ask them like yeah what is your use case like they for example
prioritize battery life and storage other people like us for example we would prioritize RAM
and compute and so but both answers are correct but different people require different answers and
with preference tuning while you're trying to average somehow like you are asking the data label us
to give you the right or not the right to preferred answer and then you train on that but at some
point yeah you learn that average preferred answer and there's no I think reason to keep training
long around it because you know it's just a style where with rl vr you'd really give the model
well you let the lot model solve more and more complex difficult problems and so I think
it makes more sense to allocate more budget long term to lrbr and also that right now we are in
lrbr 1.0 land where it's still like that simple thing where we have a question and answer
but we don't do anything with the one stuff in between so there was a I mean multiple research
papers also by google for example on process reward models that also give scores for the
explanation how correct is the explanation anything that will be the next thing let's say rlbr2.0
for this year focusing in between question and answer like how to leverage that information
the explanation to improve the explanation and help it to get better accuracy but then so that's
one angle and there was a deep seek math version two paper where they also had interesting inference
scaling there where well first they had developed models that great themselves separate model and I
think that that will be one aspect in the other like Nathan mentioned it will be for rrbr2.0 branching
into other domains the place where people are excited are value functions which is very pretty
similar so process reward models are kind of like process reward models assign how good something is
to each kind of intermediate step in a reasoning process where value functions apply value to every
token the language model generates both of these have been largely unproven in the language
modeling in this reasoning model era people are more optimistic about value functions forever for
whatever reason now I think process reward models were tried a lot more in this pre-01 pre-reasoning
model era and a lot of people had a lot of headaches with them so I think a lot of it is the human
nature of like value models have a very deep history and reinforcement learning they're one of the
first things that were core to like deep reinforcement learning existing is like training value models
in this so right now the literature people are excited about trying value models but there's very
little proof in it and there are negative examples in trying to scale up process reward models these
things don't always hold in the future I think we came to this discussion by talking about scaling
and a simple way to summarize what you're saying with like you don't want to do too much rlhf
which is eventually the signal scales is people have worked on rlhf for language models for years
especially in intense interest after chat gbt and this the first release of a reasoning model trained
with rlvr open a eyes o1 had a scaling plot where if you increase the training compute logarithmically
you get a linear increase in evaluations and this has been reproduced multiple times I think deep c
had a plot like this but there's no scaling law for rlhf where if you log increase the compute you
get some performance in fact the seminal scaling paper for rlhf is scaling loss for reward model
over optimization so it's like that's a big line to draw with rlvr and the methods we have now
and in the future like they will follow the scaling paradigm which is like the best runs you can
let to run for an extra 10x and you get a few x performance but you can't do this with rlhf and
that is just going to be field defining and how people approach them where I'm a shill for people
academically to do rlhf and that's a good way to describe it is like to do the best rlhf you
might not need the extra 10 or 100 x of compute but to do the best rlvr you do so I think there's a
what I say is a seminal paper from what was a meta internship it's called it's like the art
of scaling reinforcement learning with language models there what they describe as a framework is
scale rl and their incremental experiment was like 10,000 b 200 hours which is like thousands or
tens of thousand dollars per experiment and they do a lot of them which is just like this cost is
not accessible to the average academic which is a hard equilibrium where it's trying to figure out
how to learn from each community I was wondering if we could take at this point a bit of a tangent
and talk about education and learning if you're somebody listening to this who's a smart person
interested in programming interested in AI so I presume building something from scratch is a good
beginning so can you just take me through like what you would recommend people do so I would personally
start like you said implementing a simple model from scratch that you can run on your computer the
goal is not if you build a model from scratch to have like something you use every day for your
personal projects like it's not going to be your personal assistant replacing an existing open
weight model or churchypd it's to see what exactly goes into the lm what exactly comes out of the
lm how the pre-training works in that sense on your own computer preferably and then you learn
about the pre-training the supervised fine tuning the attention mechanism you get a solid understanding
of how things work but at some point you will reach a limit because small models can only do so much
and the problem with learning about lm at scale is I would say it's exponentially more complex to
make a larger model because it's not that the model just becomes larger you have to now think about
charging your parameters across multiple GPUs even for the kvcache that multiple ways you can implement
it one is just to understand how it works just to grow the cache that's like a cache you grow step by
step by let's say concastitating lists growing it but then it wouldn't be optimal in GPUs you wouldn't
do that you would pre-allocate a tensor and then fill it in but that adds again another 20 30 line
lines of code and for each thing you add so much code and I think the trick with the book is basically
to understand how the lm works it's not going to be your production level lm but once you have that
you can understand the production of the lm so you're trying to always build an lm that's going to
fit on on GPU yes the most of them I have they've I have some bonus materials on some
MOE models I think one or two of them they may require multiple GPUs but the goal is to have it on
one GPU and the beautiful thing is also you can stuff verify it's almost like rlvr when you code
these from scratch you can take an existing model from the hugging phase transformer library
so the hugging phase transformer former library is great but if you want to learn about lm's I
think that's not the best place to start because the code is so complex because it has to full
has to fit so many use cases also some people use it in production has to be really sophisticated and
it's really intertwined and really hard it's not linear to read it was started as a fine tuning library
and then it grew to be like the standard representation of every model architecture and the way
is loaded so hugging phase like the default place to get a model and transformers is the software
that enables us so people can easily load a model and do something basic with it and all
frontier labs that have open weight models have a hugging phase transformer version of it like
from deep seek to GPT OSS that's like the canonical weight that you can load there but again also
even transformers the library is not used in production people use then SGlang or VLLM
and it's at another layer of complexity we should say that the transformer's library has like 400
models so it's a one library that tries to implement a lot of lm's and so you have a huge code base
basically it's like huge it's like it's I don't know maybe really it's kind of so lines of code and
the fine it's like understanding the part that you want to understand is finding the needle in the
haystack but what's beautiful about it is you have a working implementation and so you can work
backwards from it what I would recommend doing or what I also do is if I want to understand for
example how almost three is implemented I would look at the weights in the model hub the config
file and then you can see oh they used so many layers they use let's say group query attention
or multi head attention in that case and you see all the components in like a human readable I know
100 lines of config file and then you start let's say with your GPT 2 model and add these things you
know and the cool thing here is you can then load the pre-trained weights and see if they work
in your model and you want to match the same output that you get with a transformer model and then
you can use it as a basically as a verifiable reward to make your architecture correct and then
it's kind of sometimes it takes me a day to with almost three the challenge was a rope for the
position embeddings they had a yarn extension and there was some custom scaling there and I couldn't
quite match the these things and in this struggle you kind of understand things but the cool thing is
at the end you know you have it correct because you can unit tested you can check against the
reference implementation and I think that's maybe one of the best ways to learn really like
to basically reverse engineer something yeah I think that that is something that everybody that's
interested in getting to I today should do and I think that's what I liked your book is like I
came to language models from this rl and robotics field like I'd never had taken the time to just
learn all the fundamentals and this transformer architecture I described as being so fundamental
as deep learning was a thing that I had to learn in the past and people need to do this I think that
where a lot of people kind of get overwhelmed is how do I apply this to have impact or find like
a career path because like AI and language models make this fundamental stuff so accessible and
people with motivation won't learn it and then it's like how do I get the cycles on goal to
contribute to research and I think that I'm actually fairly optimistic in this because the field
moves so fast that a lot of times the best people like don't fully solve a problem because there's
a bigger lower like a bigger problem to solve that's very low-hanging fruits so they move on and I think
that a lot of what I was trying to do in the starly Jeff book is like take post trading techniques and
just describe how people think about them influencing the model and what people are doing and then
it's remarkable how many things I just think are just like people stop studying them or don't
so I think people trying to get narrow after doing the fundamentals is good and then
reading the relevant papers and being engaged in the ecosystem it's like you actually the
proximity that random people have online from the leading researchers like no one knows who all the
anonymous account on x and ml is very popular for whatever reason and no one knows who all these
people are like it could just be random people that study the stuff deeply especially with the AI
tools and just be like keep I don't understand this keep digging into it I think is a very useful thing
but there's a lot of research areas that just like are maybe three papers that you need to read
and then one of the authors will probably email you back but you have to put a lot of effort
into these emails to understand the field like I think it would be for a newcomer easily
weeks of work to feel like they can truly grasp like what is a very narrow area but I think going
narrow after you have the fundamentals be very useful to people because it's like I became very
interested in character training which is like how you make the model funny or sarcastic or
serious and like what do you do to the data to do this and it's like a student at Oxford reached
out to me it's like hey I'm interested in this and I advised him and it's like that paper now exists
and it's like I don't know there's like two or three people in the world that were very interested
in this he's a PhD student which gives you an advantage but like for me that was a topic I was
waiting for someone to be like hey I've time to spend cycles on this and I'm sure there's a lot
more very narrow things or you're just like oh it doesn't make sense that there was no answer to
this and I think that it's just like there's so much information coming that people are like I can't
grab on to any of these but if you just actually stick in an area I think there's a lot of interesting
things to learn yeah I think you can't try to do it all because there would be very overwhelming
and you would burn out if you try to keep up with everything for me for example I haven't kept
up with computer vision a long time just focused on LMS but coming back to your book for example
I think this is also a really great book and a really good bang for the back because you want to
learn about our hf I wouldn't go out there and read our hf papers because I would be you would be
spending two years to protect there's a I just edited the book and I was like there's the chapter
where I had to be like x papers say one thing and x papers say another thing and we'll see what
it comes out to be true what are some of the just to go through some of the table contest some of
the ideas we might have missed in the bigger picture of the post training so first of all you do
the problem set up training overview what a preference this preference is data in the optimization
tools reward modeling regularization instruction tuning rejection sampling reinforcement learning
I pause a gradients direct alignment algorithms then constitutional AI and AI feedback reasoning
and inference time scaling to use some function callings and third data and distillation evaluation
and then open question section over optimization style and information and then product UX
character and post training so what are some ideas worth mentioning that connect both the
educational component and the research component you mentioned the character training is pretty interesting
character training is interesting because they're so little out of it but we talk about how
people engage with these models and like we feel good using them because they're positive but
that can go too far it could be too positive and it's like essentially it's how do you change your
data and or decision making to make it exactly what you want and I open AI has this thing called
a model spec which is essentially their internal guideline for what they want to model to do and
they publish this to developers so essentially you can know what is a failure of open AI's training
which is like they have the intentions and they haven't met it yet versus what is something that
they like actually wanted to do and that you don't like and that transparency is very nice but all
the methods for curating these documents and how easy it is to follow them is not very well known
I think the way the book is designed is that the reinforcement learning chapter is obviously what
people want because everybody hears about it with RLVR and it's the same algorithms and the same map
but it's just like you can use it in very different documents so I think the core of RLHF is
like how messy preferences are is essentially rehash of a paper that I wrote years ago but this
is essentially the chapter that will tell you why RLHF is never ever fully solvable because like
the way that even RL is set up is that it assumes that preferences can be quantified and that
multiple preferences can be reduced to single values and I think it relates in the economics literature
to the Von Nomen Morganston Utility Theorem and like that is the chapter where all of that
philosophical, economic and like psychological context it tells you what gets compressed into doing
RLHF so it's like you have all of this and then later in the book it's like you use this RLMAT to
make the number go up and I think that that's why I think it would be very rewarding for people to
do research on is because it's like quantifying preferences is something that is just like
humans have designed the problem in order to make preferences studyable but there's kind of
fundamental debates on like an example is in a language model response you have different things
you care about whether it's accuracy or in style and when you're collecting the data they all get
compressed into like I like this more than another and it's like like that is happening and there's
a lot of those there's a lot of research in other areas of the world that go into like how should
you actually do this I think social choice theory is the subfield of economics around how you
should aggregate preferences and there's like I was I went to a workshop that published a white
paper on like how can you think about using social choice theory for RLHF so I mostly would
want people that get excited about the math to come and have things or they can stumble into and
learn this kind of broader context I think that's a fun thing I just keep a list of all the
tech reports that I like of reasoning models so in the in chapter 14 which is a kind of like a short
summary of RLVR there's just like a gigantic table where I just like list every single reasoning
model that I like so there's just like I think an education a lot of it needs to be like
at this point it's like what I like because the language models are so good at the math where it's
famous paper direct preference optimization which is like a much simpler way of solving the problem
than RL the derivations and the appendix skip steps of math and it's like I tried for this book like
I redid the derivations and I'm like what the heck is this log trick that they use to change the
math but doing it with language models they're like this is the log trick and I'm like I don't know
if I like this that the math is so commoditized I think like some of the struggle and reading this
appendix and following the math I think is good for learning and I guess so actually it returns to
this often just on the topic of education you both both have brought up the word struggle
quite a bit so there's value if you're not struggling as part of this process you're not fully
following the proper process for learning I suppose some of the providers are starting to work on
models for education which are designed to not give actually I haven't used them but I would guess
they're designed to not give all the information at once and make people work to do this so I think
you could train models to do this and it would be a wonderful contribution we're like all of this
stuff in the book you have to reevaluate every decision for it which is such a great example I
think those are the chance to work on an AI2 which I would try to like I think this would be so
great sense I do something like that did that the other day for video games for example I sometimes
for my pastime play video games like I like video games with puzzles you know like Zelda and
Metroid and there's this new game where I go to stuck and I really got stuck and was okay I you
know I don't want to struggle like two two days and so I use an LLM but then you say hey please
don't add any spoilers just you know I'm here and there what do I have to do next and the same
thing you can do I guess for math where you say okay I'm here at this point I'm getting stuck don't
give me the full solution but what is something I could try you know like where you kind of carefully
probe it but the problem here is I think it requires discipline and a lot of people do math for like
I mean a lot of people who enjoy math but there are also a lot of people who need to do it for their
homework and then it's like the shortcut and yeah we can develop an educational LLM but the other
LLM is still there and it's still a temptation to use the other LLM I think a lot of people especially
in college they they understand the stuff they're passionate about their self-aware about it and
they understand it shouldn't be easy like I think we just have to develop a good taste
because our research tastes like school taste about stuff that you should be struggling on
and stuff you shouldn't be struggling on which is tricky to know because sometimes you don't have
good long-term vision about what will be actually useful to you or in your career but you have
to you have to develop that taste and I was talking to me and I found say our friends about this
and it's like there's this brief 10-year window where all of the homework and there all the exams
could be digital but before that everybody had to do all the exams in blue book because there's
another way and now after AI everybody's gonna need to be in blue books in oral exams because
everybody could cheat so easily it's like this brief generation that had a different
education system that like everything could be digital and but you still couldn't cheat and now
she can go back that was just great funny you mentioned character training just zooming out on
more general topic for that topic how much compute was required and in general to contribute as a
researcher are there places where not too much compute is required where you can actually contribute
as an individual researcher for on the character training thing I think this research is built on
fine-tuning about seven billion parameter models with Laura which is like a essentially you're
only fine-tuned a small subset of the weights of the model I don't know exactly how many
GPU hours that would take but it's doable not doable for every academic so the situation for
some academics is like so dire that the only work you can do is doing inference where you have closed
models or open models and you get completions from them and you can look at them and understand the
models and that's very well suited to evaluation which you become it's you want to be the best at
creating representative problems that the models fail on or show certain abilities which I think
that you can break through with this so I've like I think that the top end goal for a researcher
working on evaluation if you want to have career momentum is the frontier lapse pick up your
evaluation so it's like you don't need to have every project do this but if you go from a small
universe and you're with no compute and you figure out something that Claude struggles with and
then the next Claude model has it in the blog post like there's your career rocket ship I think
that that's hard but it's like if you want to scope the maximum possible impact with minimum compute
it's something like that which is just get very narrow and it takes learning of where the models
are going so you need to like build a tool that tests where not Claude 4.5 will fail if you're
going to do a recent if I'm going to start a research project I need to think where the models
in eight months are going to be struggling but what about developing totally novel ideas
this is a trade-off I think that if you're doing a PhD you could also be like it's too risky to work
in language models I'm going way longer term which is like what is what is the thing that's going
to define language model development in ten years which I think that I end up being a person that's
pretty practical I mean I went to my PhD where it's like I got into Berkeley worst case I get a
master's and I go work in tech it's like I'm very practical about it so I'm like
the life afforded to people to work at these AI companies the amount of like opening
eyes average compensation is over a million dollars in stock a year for employee any normal person
in the US to get into this AI lab is transformative for your life some pretty practical of like
there's still a lot of upward humility working in language models if you're focused
and that comes just like look at these jobs but from a research perspective the transformative
impact and these academic awards that's like be the next y'all McHoon is from not working I'm not
caring about language model development very much it's a big financial sacrifice in that case
so I get to work with some awesome students and they're like should I go work at an AI lab and I'm
like like you're getting a PhD at a top school or you're gonna leave to go to a lab I'm like I don't
know like if you go work at a top lab I don't blame you don't go work at some random startup that
might go to zero but if you're going to open AI I'm like it could be worth leaving a PhD for
less more rigorously think through this where would you give a recommendation for people to do
a research contribution so the options are academia so get get a PhD then five years publishing
okay compute resources that constraint there's uh there's research labs that are more focused on
open weight models and so working there or closed frontier labs research labs they go open AI
and drop it xAi so on the two gradients are the more closed the more money you tend to get and
but also the will that you get less credit so in terms of building a like a portfolio of things
that you've done like it's very clear of what you have done as an academic and you have done
this and versus if you are gonna go be like trade this fairly reasonable progression for being a
cog in the machine which could also be very fun so I think it's a very different career paths
but the like the opportunity cost for being a researcher is very high because PhD students are
essentially nothing so I think it ends up rewarding people that have a fairly stable
safety net and they realize that they can operate in the long term which is they want to do very
interesting work and get a very interesting job so it is a fairly like it's a privileged position
to be like I'm gonna see out my PhD and figure it out after because I want to do this and I think
a lot of academic like at the same time the academic ecosystem is getting bombarded by funding
getting cut and stuff so there's just like so many different trade-offs around understand
plenty of people that are like I can't deal with this funding search I grant got cut for no
reason by the government or I don't know what's gonna happen so I think there's a lot of uncertainty
and trade-offs that in my opinion favor just like take the take the well paying job with meaningful
impact it's like not also like you're getting paid to sit around it openly I you're building like
the cutting edge of things that are changing millions of people's relationship to tech but
publication wise there be more secretive increasingly so so you're publishing less and less and
less and less and so you're you are having a positive impact that scale but it's your cognitive
machine I think it's big honestly it hasn't changed that much so I have been academia I'm not
in academia anymore at the same time I wouldn't want to miss my time in academia but what I wanted to
say before I get to that part I think it hasn't changed that much I was working in like I was using
AI or machine learning methods for applications and computational biology was collaborators and
a lot of people went from academia directly to Google and I think it's the same thing back then
professors were like you know sad that their students went into industry because they couldn't
carry on their legacy in that sense and I think it's the same thing I mean it's like it hasn't changed
I think that much the only thing that has changed is the scale but you know
cool stuff was always developed in industry that was close you couldn't couldn't talk about it
and I think the difference now is well your preference do you like to talk about your work publish
or you know you are more in a close-step that's one difference the compensation of course but
it's always been like that I think so it really depends on you know where you feel comfortable and
it's also nothing is forever the only thing right now is there's a third option which is
starting a startup that's a lot of people doing startups very risky move but can be high
is a high-risk high-reward type of situation where joining an industry lab I think is pretty safe
you know also upward mobility honestly I think if once you have been at an industry lab it will be
easier to find future jobs but then again you know it's like yeah how much do you enjoy
the team and working on proprietary things versus how do you like the publishing work I mean
publishing is stressful it is you know like acceptance rate that conferences can be arbitrary
can be very frustrating but also high reward if you have a paperplow to publish you feel good
because your name is on there you have a higher accomplishment and you know feel like my friends
who are professors same on average happier than my friends who work at a frontier lab to be totally
honest because that's just grounding and the frontier labs definitely do this 996 which essentially
is shorthand for work all the time can you describe 996 this culture that's I believe you could say
invented in China and adopted in Silicon Valley what's what's 996 it's 9am to 9pm 6 days a week
what is that 72 hours okay so what is this basically the standard in AI companies in Silicon Valley
more and more this kind of grind mindset yeah I mean not maybe not exactly like that but I think
there is a trend towards it and it's interesting I think it almost flipped because when I was in
academia I felt like that because as a professor you had to write grants you had to do you had to
teach and you had to do your research it's like three jobs in one and it is more than a full-time
job if you want to be successful and I feel like now like Nathan just said the professors in
comparison to a lab I think they have less like even maybe pressure or workload than at a frontier
lab because they work a lot they're just so fulfilled but like working with students and having a
constant runway of mentorship and like a mission that is very people oriented I think in an
arrow when things are moving very fast and a very chaotic it's very rewarding to people yeah and I
think at a startup I think it's a pressure it's like you have to make it and it's like it is really
important that people put in the time but well it is really hard because you have to deliver
constantly and I've been at a startup I had a good time but I don't know if I could do it forever
it's like an interesting pace and it's exactly like we talked about in the beginning these models
are leapfrogging each other and they are just constantly like trying to take the next step
compared to the competitors it's just ruthless I think right now I think this leapfrogging nature
in having multiple players is actually an underrated driver of language modeling process where
competition is so deeply ingrained to people and these companies have intentionally created
very strong culture like Anthropic is known to be so culturally deeply committed and organized
I mean like we hear so little from them and everybody's Anthropic seems very aligned and it's like
being at a culture that is super tight and having this competitive dynamic is like
talk about a thing that's going to make you work hard and create things that are better so I think
that this but that comes at the cost of human capital which is like you can only do this for so
long and people are definitely burning out I think I I wrote a post on burnout as I like I've
tried in and out of this myself especially trying to like be a manager of full mode training it's
crazy job doing this the book apple in china by Patrick McGee he talked about the how hard the
apple engineers work to set up the supply chains in china and he was like they had saving marriage
programs and he told in a podcast he was like people died from this level of working hard so I think
this is just like it's a perfect environment for creating progress based on human expense and I
it's there's going to be a lot there's a lot of the human expense is the 996 that we started this
way which is like people do really grind also read this book I think they had a quote word for
if someone had to go home to spend time with their family to save the marriage and it's crazy
and then colleagues honestly okay this is like read alert for this situation we have to let that
person go home this weekend and but at the same time I don't think they were forced to work it's
really they were so passionate about the product I guess that it is it is you you get into that mindset
and I had that sometimes as an academic but also as an independent person I have that sometimes
I overwork and it's unhealthy I had you know I had back issues I had negatives because I did not
take the breaks that I maybe should have taken but it's not because no one forced me to it's because
I wanted to work because that's why I didn't throw up like they want to do this work yeah but there's
also there's also a feeling a fervor that's building especially in Silicon Valley aligned with
the scaling laws idea where there's this hype where the world will be transformed in a scale of
weeks and you want to be at the center of it and then you know I have this great fortune
of having conversations with wide variety of human beings and from there I get to see all these
bubbles and echo chambers across the world and it's fascinating to see how we humans form them
and I think it's fair to say that Silicon Valley is a kind of echo chamber a kind of
silo and bubble I think bubbles are actually really useful and effective it's not necessarily a
negative thing because you could be ultra productive it could be the the Steve Jobs
reality distortion field because you just convince each other the breakthroughs are imminent and
by convincing each other of that you make the breakthroughs imminent.
Bernhobert wrote a book classifying bubbles but essentially one of them is financial bubbles which
is like speculation which is bad and the other one is like I don't know the term but effectively
for buildouts because it pushes people to build these things and I do think AI is in this
but I worry about it transitioning to a financial bubble which is like it's yeah but also in the
space of ideas that bubble you are doing a reality distortion field and that means you are deviating
from reality and if you go too far from reality while also working you know 996 and you might
miss some fundamental aspects of the human experience including in Silicon Valley this is a
common problem in Silicon Valley is like it's a very specific geographic area you might not understand
the Midwest perspective of the full experience of all the other different humans in the United
States and across the world and you speak a certain way to each other you convince each other
of a certain thing and that that gets you into real trouble whether AI is a big success and
becomes a powerful technology or it's not in either trajectory you can get yourself into trouble
so you have to consider all of that here you are a young person trying to say what you want to do
with your life the thing that is I don't even really understand this but the SF AI memes have
gotten to the point where permanent underclass was one of them which was the idea that the last six
months of 2025 was the only time to build a durable value in AI startup or model otherwise
all the value will be captured by existing companies and you will therefore be poor which
like that's an example of the SF thing that goes so far I still think for young people that
going to be able to tap into it if you are really passionate about wanting to have an impact in AI
like being physically an SF is the most likely place for you going to do this but it has trade-offs
I think SF is an incredible place but there is a bit of a bubble and if you go into that bubble
which is extremely valuable just get out also read history books read literature
visit other places in the world twitter is not and substack is not the entire world I think I would
say one of my one people I worked with is moving to SF and it's like I need to get a copy of the
season of the witch which is a history of SF from like 1960 to 1985 which goes through like the
hippie revolution like they all the gays kind of taking over the city and that culture emerging
and then the HIV AIDS crisis and other things and it's just like that is so recent and so much turmoil
and hurt but also like love and SF and it's like no one knows about this it's a great book
season of the witch I recommend a bunch of my SF friends who do get out recommended it to me and
I think that's just like living there like I lived there and I didn't appreciate this context and
it's just like I'm so recent yeah okay let's we talked a lot about we talked a lot about a lot of
things certainly about the things that were exciting last year but this year one of the
you guys mentioned this exciting is the scaling of Texas future models and it's just a different
exploration of Texas future can you talk about what that is and what the possibility holds
sort of different kinds of approaches than the current outcomes yeah so we talked a lot about
the transformer architecture and the auto regressive transformer architecture specifically like GPT
and it doesn't mean no one else is working on anything else so people are always on the let's say
look out for the next big thing because I think it would be almost like yes stupid not to because
sure right now the transformer architecture is the thing and it works best and as right now nothing
else out there but you know it's always a good idea to not put all your eggs into one basket so
people are developing other things alternatives to the auto regressive transformer one of them
would be for example text diffusion models and listeners may know diffusion models from the image
generation like stable diffusion popularized it there was like a paper on generating images back
then people used GANs a genitive adversarial networks and then there was this diffusion process where
you iteratively denoise an image and that resulted in really good quality images over time stable
diffusion was a company other companies build their own diffusion models and then people are now like
okay can we try this also for text doesn't you know make intuitive sense yet because it feels like
okay it's not something continuous like a picture that we can differentiate it's like a discrete text
so how do we implement that denoising process but it's kind of like similar to the birth models by
Google like when you go back to the original transformer and so there were like the encoder and
the decoder the decoder is what we are using right now in GPD and so forth the encoder it's more like
a parallel let's say technique where you have multiple tokens that you fill in in parallel instead
so GPD models they do auto regressive one token at a time you complete the sentence one token at a
time and in birth models you have a text that says sentence that has a gaps you like mask them out
and then one iteration is filling in these gaps and text diffusion is kind of like that where you are
starting with let's say some random text and then you are filling in the missing parts or you
are refining them iteratively in your multiple iterations and the cool thing here is that this
can do multiple tokens at the same time so it's kind of like the promise of having it more efficient
now the trade-off is of course well how good is the quality it might be faster and then now you
have this dimension of the denoising process the more steps you do the better the text becomes
and people you know I mean you can scale in different ways they try to see if that is maybe
valid alternative to the auto regressive model in terms of giving you the same quality for less compute
right now I think it's you know there are papers that suggest okay if you want to get the same
quality you have to crank up the denoising steps and then you end up spending the same
compute you would spend on an auto regressive model the other downside is well it's parallel
which sounds appealing but some tasks are not parallel like you know like reasoning tasks to use
maybe where you have to ask in quote interpretive to give you an intermediate result and that is kind
of tricky with diffusion models so there are some hybrids but the main idea is can we parallelize it
so interesting avenue I think right now there are mostly research let's say models out there like
Lara and some other ones I saw some I start up some the proit models there is no big diffusion
model at scale yet like you know like Gemini Chatchee PD scale in that level but there was an
announcement by Google like a side where they said they are launching Gemini diffusion and they
put it into context of their I think nano two model and then they said basically for the same
quality on most benchmarks we can generate things much faster so you mentioned what's next I
don't think the text diffusion model is going to replace auto regressive elements but it will be
something maybe for quick cheap at scale tasks maybe the free tier in future will be something
like that I think there's a couple examples where it's I've heard that it's actually been started
to be used I think to paint an example of why this is so much better for example when GPT-5 is
taking 30 minutes to respond is generating one token at a time and this diffusion idea is essentially
generate all of those completion all of those tokens in the completion in one batch which is why
it could be way faster and I think it could be suited the start of them hearing are like codes startups
where you have a code base and you have somebody that's effectively vibe coding and they say make
this change and a code diff is essentially a huge reply from the model but it doesn't have to have
that much external context and you can get it really fast by using these diffusion models so that's
what I've heard of one example is that they use these text diffusion to generate really long diffs
because doing it with a auto regressive model would take minutes and that time for like a user
facing product causes a lot of churn so like every second you lose a lot of users so I think
that's going to be this thing where it's going to grow and have some applications but I actually
thought that different types of models were going to be used for different things more sooner
sooner than they have been so I kind of trade off I think that the tool use point is the one that's
stopping them from being like most general purpose because like cloud code and this
this had GPT was search like the re the auto regressive chain is interrupted with some external
tool and I don't know how to do that with the diffusion setup so what's the future of tool use this
year and then the coming years do you think there's going to be a lot of developments there how that's
integrated to the entire stack I do think right now I mean it's mostly on the proprietary
at an M site but I think we will see more of that in the open source tooling and I think I mean it
is a huge unlock because then you can really outsource certain tasks from just memorization to actual
you know like instead of having the LM memorized what is 23 plus 5 just use a calculator so you
think that can help solve hallucination not solve it but reduce it so so the LM needs to know what
like when to ask for a tool call and the second one is well it doesn't mean the internet is always
correct you can do a web search but let's say I asked who won the World Cup in let's say 1998
it still needs to find the right website and get the right information so you can still go to the
incorrect website and give me incorrect information so I don't think it will fully solve that
but it is improving it in that sense and so another cool paper earlier this year I think was
generated this summer 31st it's not technically 2026 but close so like the recursive language model
that's a cool idea to kind of take this even a bit further so just to explain so Nathan you
also mentioned earlier it's harder to do cool research in academia because of the compute budget
if I recall correctly they did everything with GPT-5 so they didn't even use local models but the idea
is let's say if a long context task instead of having the LM solve all of it in like one shot or
even like in a chain you break it down into sub tasks you have the LM decide when like what is a
let's say sub task and then recursively call an LLM to solve that and I think something like that
also then adding tools and you know each one maybe you have like a huge Q&A task each one goes to
the web and gathers information and then you pull it at the end together and stitch it back together
like where I think there's going to be a lot of unlock using things like that where you
you're not necessarily improve the LLM itself you improve how the LLM is used and what the LLM can
use one downside right now with tool use is you have to give the LLM permission to use tools and
that will take some trust especially if you want to unlock things like having an LLM answer emails
for you a lot not even answer but just sort them for you or select them for you or something like that
I don't know if I would today give an LLM access to my emails right I mean this is like a huge risk
I think that's a cool one last point on the tool use thing I think that you hinted at this and
we both come at this in our own ways is that the open versus closed models use tools in very
different ways where open models people go to hugging face and you download the model and then
the person's going to be like oh what tool do I want and I don't know XS is my search preferred search
provider but somebody else might care for a different search startup where you release a model it
needs to be useful for multiple tools for multiple use cases which is really hard because you're making
like a general reasoning engine model which is actually what GPT OSS is good for but on the closed
models you're deeply integrating the specific tool into your experience and I think that open
models will struggle to replicate some of the things that I like to do with closed models which
will be like I don't know you can reference a mix of public and private information and
something that I keep trying every three to six months I try like codex on the web which is
just prompting a model to make an update to some GitHub repository that I have and it's just like
like that said it's a cure cloud environment is just so nice for just like send it off and do
this thing and then come back to me and these will probably help define some of the local open and
closed niches but I think initially because there was such a rush to get these tool use working
that the open models were on the back foot which is kind of inevitable I think there's so much
research that so many resources in these frontier labs but will be fun when the open models solve
this because it's going to necessitate like a bit more flexible and potentially interesting
model that might work with this recursive idea to like be an orchestrator and a tool used model so
hopefully the necessity drives some interesting innovation there. So continue learning this is a
longstanding topic important problem I think that increases and importance is the cost of training
of the models goes up so if you can explain what continue learning is how important it might be
this year and the coming years to make progress. This relates a lot to this kind of SF get zeitgeist
of what is a GI what is which is artificial general intelligence and what is ASI artificial super
intelligence and what are the language models that we have today capable of doing I think the
language models can solve a lot of tasks but if key milestone among the AI community is essentially
when AI could replace any remote worker taking in information and solving digital tasks and doing
them and the limitation that's highlighted by people is that a language model will not learn from
feedback the same way that an employee is so if you hire an editor the editor will mess up but you
will tell them and if you hire a good editor they don't do it again but language models don't have
ability to modify themselves and learn very quickly so the idea is if we're going to actually get
to something that is a truly general adaptable intelligence that can go into any remote work
scenario and needs to be able to learn quickly from feedback and on job learning I'm personally more
bullish on language models by being able to just provide them with very good context you said
like you may be offline said that like you can write extensive documents to models where you say
I have all this information here is all the blog posts I've ever written I like this type of writing
my voice is based on this but a lot of people don't provide this to models and the models weren't
designed to take this amount of context previously like the eagentic models are just starting so it's
this kind of tradeoff of do we need to update the weights of this model with this continual learning
thing to make them learn fast or the counter argument is we just need to provide them with more
context and information and they will have the appearance of learning fast by just having a lot of
context and being very smart so it was you mentioned the terminology here so continual learning
refers to changing the weights continuously so that the model adapts adjusts based on the
new incoming information does so continually and rapidly and frequently and so on
and then the thing you mentioned on the other side of it is generally we refer to as in context
learning as you learn stuff there's a huge context window you can just keep loading it with
extra information every time you prompt the system which I think both are legitimately can be
seen as learning it's just a different place where you're doing the learning I think to be honest
with you continual learning the updating of weights we already have that in different flavors I mean
if you think about how so I think the distinction here is do you do that on a personalized custom
model for each person or do you on a global model scale and I think we have that already with
going from GPT 5 to 5.1 and 5.2 it's maybe not immediate but it is like a curated update a quick
created update where there was feedback by the things that couldn't do feedback by the community they
updated the weights next model and so forth so it is I mean kind of like a flavor of that
other even finer great example a finer great example is like RLVR you run it updates the problem is
you can't just do that for each person because it would be too expensive to update the weights for
each person and I think that's the problem so unless you get I mean even at OpenEye scale building
the data centers it would be too expensive I think that is only feasible once you have something on
the device where the cost is on the consumer like what Apple tried to do with the Apple foundation
models putting them on the phone and then they learn from the experience a bit of a related topic
but this kind of maybe anthropomorphized term but memory what are different ideas on the mechanism
how to add memory to these systems as you're increasing things so so personalized memory especially
so right now it's mostly like context basically stuffing things into the context and then just
recalling that but again I think well it's expensive because you have to like I mean you can
cache it but still you spend tokens on that and the second one is you can only do so much I think
it's more like a preference and all style I mean a lot of people do that when they solve math problems
you say it's basically you can add previous knowledge and stuff but it also give it certain preference
pumps do what I preferred last time whatever like something like that but it does it doesn't unlock
new capabilities so for that one thing people do you still is Laura Laura adapters these are
basically instead of updating the whole weight matrix they are two smaller weight matrices that you
kind of have in parallel or overlay it's like the delta but yeah you can do that to some extent but
then again this economics so there were also papers for example Laura learns less but forgets less
it's like you know it's no free lunch if you want to learn more you need to use more weights but it
gets more expensive and then again if you learn more you forget more and it's like you have to find
that Goldilocks zone basically literally matching it much but implied in this discussion this
context length also is there a lot of innovations as possible there I think but colloquially
accepted thing is that it's a compute and data problem where you can and sometimes like small
architecture things which are like attention variance so if you have we talked about like hybrid
attention models which are essentially if you have what looks like a state space model within your
transformer and like those are better suited because you have to spend less compute to model the
furthest along token and I think that but those aren't free because they have to be accompanied by a
lot of compute or the right data so how many sequences of 100,000 tokens do you have in the
world and where do you get these and I think it just ends up being pretty expensive to scale them
so we've like gotten to pretty quickly to like a million tokens of input context length and I
would expect it to keep increasing and like get to like two million or five million this year but
I don't expect it to go to like a hundred million and that would be like a true breakthrough and I
think those breakthroughs are possible like the continual learning thing I think it was a research
problem where you could there could be a breakthrough that just makes transformers work way better at
this and it's cheap like these things could happen with so much scientific attention but
turning the crank it'll be consistent increases over time I think also looking at the extremes I
think there's again no free lunch so the one extreme to make a cheap you have a let's say an Rn
that has a single state a state where you save everything from the previous stuff is like a specific
fixed size things we never really grow the memory because it's you are stuffing everything into one
state but then the longer the context gets the more information you forget because you can't you
can't keep I mean compress everything into one state then on the other end you have the transformers
which try to remember every token which is great sometimes which we want to look up specific
information but very expensive because you have the kvcash that grows the on dot product that grows
but then yeah like you said the mamba layers I mean they kind of have the same problem I would say
like an Rn and you try to compress everything into one state you're a bit more selective there
but then I think it's like this goldilocks zone again with Unimotron 3 they found like a good ratio
of how many attention layers do you need for the global information where everything is accessible
compared to having these compressed states and I think that's how I think we will scale more
by finding better let's say ratios in goldilocks zone like between like compute making it cheap
enough to run but then also making it powerful enough to be useful and one more plug here the
recursive language model paper that is one of the papers that tries to kind of address the long
context thing so what they found is essentially instead of stuffing everything into this long context
if you break it up into the smaller multiple smaller tasks so you save memory by having multiple
smaller codes you can get actually better accuracy than having the LLM try everything all at once
I mean it's a new paradigm we'll see you know there might be other flavors of that so I think
with that we will still make improvement on long context but then also like Nathan said I think
the problem is for pre-training itself we don't have as many long context documents as other
documents so it's harder to study basically how LLM's behave and stuff like that on that level like
there are some rules of thumb where essentially you pre-trained a language model like although we
pre-trained like 8k context length and then extended the 32k with training and there's some
rules of thumb where you just like essentially doubling the training context length takes like
2x compute and then you can normally like 2 to 4x the context length again so I think a lot of it
ends up being kind of compute bound at pre-training which is in this link we talked about this
everyone talks about this big increase in compute for the top labs this year and that should
reflect in some longer context windows but I think on the post-training side there's some more
interesting things which is as we have agents the agents are going to manage this context on their
own where now people that use cloud codelot dread the compaction which is when cloud takes its
entire full 100,000 tokens of work and compacts it into bulleted list but what the next models will do
I'm just about a novel I'm sure people are already working on this is essentially the model can
control when it compacts and how so you can essentially like train your RL agger them where
compaction is an action where it shortens the history and then the problem formulation will be
I want to keep the maximum evaluation scores that I have gotten while the model compacts its
history to the minimum length because then you have the minimum amount of tokens that you need to do
this kind of compounding auto regressive prediction so there's actually a pretty nice problem setups
in this where the like these agentic models learn to use their context in a different way than just
plow forward one interesting also recent example would be deep seek version 3.2 where they had like
the sparse attention mechanism where they have essentially like a very efficient small lightweight
indexer and instead of attending to all the tokens it selects okay what tokens we actually need it's
I mean it's almost comes back to the original idea of attention where you are selective but
attention is always on you have maybe zero weight on some of them but you use them all but they
are even more like okay let's just mask that out or like not even do that and even with
sliding window attention all more that is also kind of like that idea you have that rolling window
where you keep it fixed because you don't need everything all the time you occasionally some
may as you might but it's wasteful but right now I think yeah if you use everything you're on the
safe side it gives you the best bang for the buck because you never miss information and right now
I think this year will be more also the year figuring out like you said how to be more smart about
I think right now people want to have the next state of the art and the state of the art is
happens to be the brute force expensive thing and then once you have that like you said keep that
accuracy but let's see how we can do that cheaper now like tricks you know yeah all the scaling
thing like the reason we get the quad 4.5 sonnet model first is because that you can train it
faster and you're not hitting these compute walls as soon and they can just try a lot more things
and get the model faster even though the bigger model is actually better I think we should say
that there's a lot of exciting stuff going on in the ice space my mind is recently been really
focused on robotics so we have today really almost entirely didn't talk about robotics there's a lot
of stuff on image gen video generation I think it's fair to say that the most exciting research work
in terms of the amount intensity further isn't the lm space which is why I think it's justified for
us to really focus on the lm that we're discussing but it'd be nice to bring in some certain things
that might be useful for example world models there's growing excitement on that do you think there
will be any use in this coming year for world models in the lm space yes I do think as well also
with lm what's an interesting thing here is I think if we unlock more lm capabilities it also
automatically unlocks all the other fields because or not unknucks but like makes progress faster
is because you know a lot of researchers and engineers use lm so like we said for coding so
even if they work on robotics if you like optimize these lm's that help you with coding you know
it's like it pays off but then yes world models are interesting it's basically where you have
the model run simulation of the world in a sense like a little toy thing of the real thing which
can again unlock capabilities like that are the lm is not aware of is can simulate things and I
think see this is like something I think lm's they just happen to work well by pre-training and
then doing the next token prediction but we could do this even a bit you know like sophisticated
in a sense so what I'm saying is like with there's like I think I was by meta a paper code of
world models so where they basically apply the concept of world models to lm's again where they
and so instead of just having next token prediction and verifiable rewards checking the answer
correctness they also make sure the intermediate variables are correct you know like it's kind of like
the model is learning basically a code environment in a sense and I think this makes a lot of
sense it's just like expensive to do but it is like making things more sophisticated like modeling
like modeling the whole thing not just the result so it can add more value I remember when I was a
grad student there is a so there's a competition called CASP I think where they doom protein
structure prediction like they predict the structure of protein that is not solved yet at that point
so in a sense this is actually great and I think we need something like that for lm's also where
you do the benchmark but no one does so you hand in the results but no one knows the solution and
then after the fact someone revealed that but alpha fold when it came out it crushed you know
the benchmark I mean there were also multiple iterations but I remember the first one I'm not an
expert in that subject by the first one explicitly modeled the physical interactions of the
physics of the molecule also the angles impossible angles and then in the next version I think
they got rid of this so and just with brute force scaling it up and I think with lm's we are
currently in this brute force scaling because it just happens to work but I do think also at some
point it might make sense to bring back this thing and I think with world models I think that is
where I think that might be actually quite cool I mean yeah and of course also for robotics that
is a completely unrelated from lm's yeah yeah aerobotics is very explicitly so there's the problem
of locomotion manipulation locomotion is much more solved especially in learning domain but
there's a lot of value just like with the initial protein folding systems bringing in the
traditional model based methods so you don't it's it's unlikely that you can just learn
the manipulation or the whole body local manipulation problem and to end that's the dream
but then you realize when you look at the magic of the human hand and the complexity of the real world
you realize it's really hard to learn this all the way through the way I guess alpha fold 2 did
I'm excited about the robotic learning space so I think it's collectively
getting like supercharged battle the excitement and investment in language models generally where
they're getting like the infrastructure for training transformers which is like a general modeling
thing is becoming like world class industrial tooling where any of wherever that was a limitation
for robotics it's just like way better there's where we're compute and then on top of like they
take these language models and use them as kind of central units where you can do interesting
explorative work around something that kind of already works and then I see it emerging is like
kind of like we talked about hanging face transformers and hugging face I think when I was a
hugging face I was trying to get this to happen but it was too early is like these open robotic
models on hugging face and be having people be able to contribute data and fine tune them I think
we're much closer now that the investment in robotics and I think self-driving cars is related
and enables this where it's like once you get to the point where you can have this sort of ecosystem
where somebody can download a robotics model and maybe fine tune it to their robot or share
datasets across the world and there's some data there's some work in this area like RTX I think
a few years ago where people are starting to do that but I think once they have this ecosystem it
will look very different and then this whole post-chatchip chat gbt boom is putting more resources into
that which I think is a very good area for doing research this is also resulting in much better
more accurate more realistic simulators being built closing the simple to real gap in the robotic
space but you know you mentioned a lot of excitement in the robotics space and a lot of investment
the downside of that which happens in hype cycles I personally believe most robotics people
believe that the it's not robotics is not going to be solved at the time scale as being kind of
implicitly or explicitly promised and so what happens when there's all these robotics companies
that spring up and then they don't have a product that works and there's going to be this kind of
crash of excitement which is nerve-racking there's hopefully something else will come in and keep
swooping in so that the the the continued development of some of these ideas keeps going.
It's also related to the continual learning issue essentially where the real world is so complex
with LLMs yeah you don't need to really have something learn for the user because there are a lot of
things everyone has to do everyone maybe wants to fix their grammar in their email or
code or something like that it's it's more constrained so you can kind of prepare the model for that
but preparing the robot for the real world that's harder I mean you have the foundation models
the robotic foundation models but you can learn certain things like grasping things but then again
I think every so everyone's house is different you know like it's so different and that is I think
where the world would have to learn on the job essentially and I think that I guess is the the
bottleneck right now like how to you know customizing it on the fly essentially I do I don't think
I can possibly understand the importance of the thing that doesn't get talked about almost
at all by robotics folks are anyone is safety all the interesting complexities we talk about learning
all the failure modes and failure cases everything will be talking about LLMs sometimes it fails in
interesting ways all of that is fun and games in the LLMs space in the robotic space in people's homes
across millions of minutes billions of interactions you really are almost allowed to fail never
when you have embodied systems that are put out there in the real world you just have to solve
so many problems you never thought you'd have to solve when you're just thinking about the
general robot learning problem and so bearish on in-home learned robots for consumer purchase
I'm very bullish on self-driving cars and I'm very bullish for robotic automation EG like Amazon
distribution where Amazon has built whole new distribution centers designed for robots for
Australian humans there's a lot of excitement in AI circles about AI enabling automation and
like mass scale manufacturing and I do think that the path to robots doing that is more reasonable
where it's like a thing that is designed and optimized to do a repetitive task that a human
could conceivably do but doesn't want to and then I'm much much so but it's also going to take
a lot longer than people probably predict I think that the leap from AI singularity to
we can now scale up mass manufacturing in the US because we have a massive AI advantage is one
that is troubled by a lot of political and other challenging problems let's talk about timelines
specifically timelines to AGI or ASI is it fair like as a starting point to say that nobody really
agrees on the definitions of AGI and ASI I kind of think there's a lot of disagreement but
among I've been getting pushed back where a lot of people kind of say the same thing which is like a
thing that can reproduce most digital economic work so like the remote workers are fairly reasonable
example and I think open AI's definition is somewhat related to that which is like an AI that
can do a lot of like a certain number economically valuable tasks which I don't really love as a
definition but I think it could be a grounding point because language models today what
immensely powerful are not this remote worker drop-in and there are things that you could think of
that are could be done by an AI that are way harder than or won't work which are like solving a
finding an unexpected scientific discovery that you couldn't even posit which would be an example
of something that somebody says is like an artificial super intelligence problem or like
saw taking in all medical records and finding linkages across certain illnesses that people
didn't know or figuring out that some common drug can treat some niche cancer like they would say
that that is like a super intelligence thing so these are kind of natural tiers by problem with it
is that it becomes deeply entwined with like the quest for meaning of AI and this religious
aspects to it so there's kind of different there's different paths you can take it and I don't even
know if the remote work is a good definition because what exactly is that it's like perfect to use
I actually I mean I like I don't know if you like the originally titled AI27 report they focus
more on code and research tastes so the the target there is the superhuman coder so they have several
several milestone systems superhuman coder superhuman AI researcher then super intelligent AI
researcher and then the full ASI artificial super intelligence but the after you develop the super
human coder everything else follows quickly there the task is to have a fully autonomous like
automate coding so any kind of coding need to do in order to perform research is fully automated
and from there humans would be doing AI research together with that system and they will quickly
be able to develop a system that's actually can do the research for you that's the idea and then
initially their prediction was 2027 28 and now they've pushed a bag by three to four years to
2031 mean prediction probably my prediction is you would be on 2031 but at least you can get
concrete way think about how difficult it is to fully automate programming yeah I disagree with
some of their presumptions and dynamics on how it would play out but I think they did a good they did
good work in the scenario defining milestones they were concrete and to tell a useful story which is
why they reach for this AI27 document well transcended Silicon Valley is because they told a good
story and they did a lot of rigorous work to do this I think the camp that I've fallen to is that
like AI is like so called jagged which will be excellent at some things and really bad at some
things I think that when they're close to this automated software engineer but it will be good at
is that traditional ML systems in front end the model is excellent at but the distributed ML the
models are actually really quite bad at could there's still little training data on doing large scale
distributed learning and things and this is something that we already see and I think that this
is just get amplified and then it's kind of messier in these trade-offs and then there's like how do
you think AI research works and so on so you think basically superhuman coders almost not
achievable meaning like because of the jagged nature of the thing you're just always going to have
gaps in capabilities I think it's assigning completeness to something where the models are kind
of superhuman at some types of code and I think that will continue and people are creative so they'll
utilize this like incredible abilities and like to fill in the weaknesses of the models and move
really fast they'll always kind of be this I've received for a long time this dance between the
humans are enabling this thing that the model can't do and the best the best AI researchers and
ones that can enable this superpower and I think this aligns like to what we already see I think
like cloud code for building a website you can stand up a beautiful website in a few hours or do data
analysis and I don't think it's going to keep getting better at these things and it'll pick up some
new code skills and stuff that it'll get along the way and kind of linking to what's happening and
big tech is like this AI 2027 report is like it leans into the singularity idea where I think
research is messy and social and largely in the data in ways that AI models can't process but
like what we do have today is really powerful and these tech companies are all collectively buying
into this with tens of billions of dollars of investment so like we are going to get some much
bread or version of chat GPT a much better version of cloud code than we already have I think that
it's just like hard to predict where that is going but the like bright clarity of that future is
why some of the most powerful people in the world are putting so much money into this and I think
it's just kind of small differences between like we don't actually know what a better version of
chat GPT is but also like can it automate AI research I would say probably not at least in this
time frame like big tech is going to spend a hundred billion dollars much faster than we get a
automated AI researcher that enables a AI research singularity so you think your prediction would be
what like if this is even a useful milestone were more than 10 years out I would say less than that
on the software side but I think longer than that on the things like research let's just like
for fun try to imagine a world where all software writing is fully automated like can you imagine
that world by the end of this year the amount of software that'll be automated will be so high
but it's like it'll be the things of like you're trying to train a model with RL and you need to have
multiple bunches of GPUs communicating with each other that'll still be hard but I think it'll
be much easier one of the ways to think about this so the full automation of programming is just
think of like lines of useful code written the fraction of that to the number of humans in the loop
so presumably there'll be for a long time humans in the loop of software writing is just be fewer and
fewer relative to the amount of code written right and that the the SC superhuman code I think the
the presumption there is it goes to zero the number of humans in the loop what does that world look
like when the number of humans in the loop is in the hundreds not in the hundreds of thousands I
think software engineering will be driven more to system design and goals of outcomes
where I do think software is largely going to be come on I think this has been happening over
the last few weeks where people have gone from a month ago of like oh yeah agents are kind of
slop which is a famous carpety quote to like the what is a little bit of a meme of like the industrialization
of software when anyone can just create software at their fingerprints like I do think we are
closer to that side of things and it takes direction and like understanding how the systems work
to extract that best from the language models and I think it's hard to like accept the gravity of
how much is going to change the software development and how many more people can do things without
ever looking at it I think what's interesting is to think about whether these systems will be
independent like completely independent in the sense that well I've no doubt that a lot of
times will kind of at some point solve coding in a sense like calculators solve cake relating right
so at some point humans develop the tool that you know you never need a human to calculate that
number you just type it in and it's not a algorithm you you can do it in a in that sense and I
I think that's the same probably for coding but the question is so I think what will happen is yeah
you will just say build that website it will make a very good website and then you maybe refine it
but will it do things independently where so will you be still having humans asking the AI to do
something like will there be a person say build that website or will there be AI that just builds
the website so something or whatever I think using talking about building websites is the
too simple it's just like the the the problem with websites and the problem with the web you know
HTML and all that kind of stuff it's very resilient to just slop yeah it will show you slop it's
good as showing slop I would rather like think of like safety critical systems like asking AI to end
generate something that manages logistics or manages cars fleet of cars all that kind of so
so and to end yeah generate stuff for you I think a more intermediate example is take something
like slacker Microsoft Word I think if the organization's a loud AI could very easily
implement features and to end and do a fairly good job for like things that you want to try you
want to add a new like tab and slack that you want to use and I think AI will be able to do that
pretty well actually has a really great example how far away are we from that like this year see I don't
I don't know I don't know I don't know how bad production code bases are but I think that
within like on the order of low years a lot of people are going to be pushed to be more of like
a designer and product manager where you have multiple of these agents that can try things for you
and they might take one to two days to implement a feature or attempt to fix a bug and you have
these dashboards which I think slack is actually a good dashboard for your agents will talk to you
and you'll then give feedback but things like like I make a website it's like you want to make a logo
that's passable like I think these like cohesive design things and this style is going to be very hard
for models and deciding on what to add at the next time I just okay so I hang out with a lot of
programmers and some of them are a little bit on the skeptical side in general that's just
vibe wise there like that I just think there's a lot of complexity involved in adding features to
complex systems like if you look at the browser Chrome if I wanted to add a feature if I wanted to
have tabs as opposed to up top I want them on the left side interface right you I think we're not
is not a next year thing one of the clawed releases this year one of their tests was we give it a
piece of software and leave clawed to run to recreate it entirely and it can all really almost rebuild
scrap like slack from scratch just given the parameters of the software and left in a sandbox
from the scratch part I like almost better so it might be that the smaller newer companies are
advantage and they're like we don't have to have the bloat and complexity and therefore this
feature exists and I think it gets to the point that you mentioned that some people are you talk
to us skeptical and I think that's not because the LLM can't do xyz it's because people don't
want it to do it this way some of that could be a skill issue on the human side unfortunately
you have to could be honest with ourselves and some of that could be an underspecification issue so
programming like you're like you're just assuming this is like in in relationships
communication type issue you're assuming the LLM somehow supposed to read your mind I think
this was respect driven designs really important like you just using natural language specify
like what you want I think I think if you talk to people at the labs they use these in their
training and production code like clawed code is built with clawed code and they all use these
things extensively and Dario talks about how much of clods code oh and it's like these people
are slightly ahead in terms of the capabilities they have and they probably spend on inference
they could spend 10 to 100 plus x as much as we're spending like we're on a lowly a 100 or 200
dollar month plan like they truly let it rip and I think that that like with the pace of progress
that we have it seems like like we're a year ago we didn't have a clawed code and we didn't
really have reasoning models and it's like the difference between sitting here today and what we
can do with these models and it seems like there's a lot of like there's a lot of low hanging fruit
to improve them the failure modes are pretty dumb it's like clawed you tried to use the CLI command
I don't have installed 14 times and then I sent you the command to run it's like that thing from
a modeling perspective is pretty fixable so I agree with you I've been becoming more and more bullish
in general speaking to what you're articulating I think it is a human skill issue
so anthropic is leading the way in or other companies in understanding how to best use the
models for programming therefore they're effectively using them I think there's a lot of programmers
on the outskirts they're like they don't I mean there's not a really good guide and how to use
them people trying to figure it out exactly it might be very expensive like it might be that the entry
point for that is $2,000 a month which is only tech companies and rich people just like like
that could be it but it might be worth it I mean if the final result is a working software system
will they be worth it but by the way it's funny how we converge from the discussion of time
on to AGI to a something more pragmatic and useful is there anything concrete and interesting
and useful that profound to be said about timeline to AGI and ASI or these discussions a bit to
detach from the day to day there's interesting bets so there's a lot of people trying to do
reinforce learning with verifiable rewards but in real scientific domains where there's startups
that are spending like they have hundreds of millions of dollars of funding and they have wet labs
where they're having language models proposed hypotheses that are tested in the real world and I
I would say that I think they're very early or they're early but with the pace of progress it's like
yeah maybe they're early by six months and they make it because they were their first or maybe
they're early by eight years you don't really know so I think that that type of moonshot to
branch this momentum into other for other sciences is like okay like that would be very transformative
if like alpha-fold moments happen in all sorts of other scientific domains by like A startup
solving this I think there are startups I think maybe harmonic is one where they're going all in
on language models plus lean format and you got another podcast or you've talked about this
recently and it's like we don't know exactly what's going to fall out of spending a hundred
million dollars on that model and most of them will fail but a couple of them might be big breakthroughs
that are very different than chat gpt or cloud code type software experiences like a tool that's
only good for a PhD mathematician but makes them 100x effective like okay well I agree I think this
will happen in a lot of domains especially also like domains that have a lot of you know resources
like finance and legal and pharmaceutical companies but then again is it really agi again because
we are now specializing it again and then again is it really that much different from big in the
day how we had specialized algorithms is I think it's just the same thing more way more sophisticated
but I don't know is there threshold when we call it agi I guess I think the the real cool thing is
here that we have like the foundation models that we can specialize I think that that's like the
breakthrough at some point right now I think we are not there yet because well first it's too expensive
but also you know like chat gpt doesn't just give away that chat gpt to customize it I think the
ones that's going to be true in a some way and I think I can imagine this as a business model that
chat gpt op me I says at some point like hey you know bank of america for 100 million we will do
your custom model or something like that and I think that will be the huge economic value add
the other thing though is also companies I mean right now what is the differentiating factor I mean
if everyone uses the same lm if everyone uses chat gpt they will all do the same thing again I mean
then well it's everyone is moving in lockstep but usually companies they want to have a competitive
advantage and I think there's the no way around using some of their private data and experimenting
and maybe specializing it's going to be interesting yeah sitting in the pace of progress it does just
feel like things are coming I don't think the agi and as i thresholds are particularly useful
I think I guess the real question then this takes us to the remote worker thing is when I will
go into see a big obvious leap in economic impact because currently there's not been an obvious
leap in economic impact of a lot of models for example and that's you know aside from agi or
asi or all that kind of stuff there's a real question of like when are we going to see a gdp like
junk yeah it's like what is the gdp made up of like a lot of it's like financial services so like
I don't I don't know what this is it's just hard for me to think about the gdp bump but like
I would say that software development becomes valuable in a different way when you no longer have to look
at the code anymore so when when it is like cloud will make you a small business which is essentially
cloud can set up your website your bank account your email and your whatever else and like you just
have to express like what you're trying to put it into the world like that's not just a
enterprise market but it is a hard like I don't know how you get people to try doing that I guess
some chat gpt can do it like people are trying chat gpt I think it boils down to the the
scientific question of how hard is tool used to solve there's a lot of the stuff you're
applying the remote work stuff is tool use it's like how computer use like how you have an
element that goes out there this agentic system and does something in the world and only screws up
1% of the time computer use is a good example of what labs care about and we haven't seen a lot
of progress on we saw multiple demos and 2025 of like cloud can use your computer or opening I had
Kua and they all suck yeah so like they're also investing money in this and I think that will be
a good example where it's actually something where it just seems pretty like taking over the whole
screen seems a lot harder than having an API that they can call in the back end and some of that
is yet to then set up a different environment for the model to work in like they're not working
on your MacBook they are individually interfacing with Google and Amazon and Slack and they handle all
these things in a very different way than humans do so some of this might be structural blockers
also like specification wise I think the problem is also for you know arbitrary tasks
well you still have to specify what you want your LLM to do and how do you do that in a
what is the environment how do you specify you can say what the end goal is but
if it can't solve the end goal with LLMs if you ask it for text you can always you know clarify
do sub steps what is how do you put that information into a system that let's say books a travel
trip for you you can say well you screwed up my credit card information but even to get it to
that point like how do you like as a user guide the model before like it can even attempt that I
think the interface is really hard yeah it has to learn a lot about you specifically and about
this goes to continue continuing about the general mistakes that are made throughout and then
mistakes that are made through you all day I interfaces are getting set up to ask humans for input
I think cloud code we talked about a lot it asks we'd back on questions if it doesn't have enough
specification on your plan or you're desired it starts to ask questions would you rather we talked
about memory which saves across chats which it's first implementation is kind of odd where it'd be
like it'll mention my dog's name or something like in a chat I'm like you didn't need to be subtle
about this like I don't care but the like things that are emerging our chat to be T has the pulse feature
which is like a curated couple paragraphs with links to something to look at or to talk about and
people talk about how the language models are going to ask you questions which I think is a very
it's probably going to work with a language model is like it knows you had a doctor appointment or
something it's like hey how are you feeling out of that which is like again goes into the territory
of humans are very susceptible to this and there's a lot of social change to come but also like
they're experimenting with having the models engage some people really like this pulse feature
which is it processes your chats and automatically searches for information and puts it in the
chat to be T app so there's a lot of things coming I use that feature before and I always feel bad
because it does that every day and I really check it out it's like how much money like I mean
compute is burned on something I don't even look at you know where it's like there's also a lot of
vital compute in the world so I don't feel too bad okay do you think new ideas might be needed
is it possible that the path to a GI whatever that is however we define that the solve computer use
more more generally to solve biology and chemistry and physics sort of the Dario definition of
a GI or Parflé a do you think is possible the totally new ideas are needed non LLM non RL ideas what
might they look like this is we're not going into philosophy land a little bit for something
like a singular need to happen I would say yes and the new ideas can be architectures or training
algorithms which is like fundamental deep learning things but there's the in that nature
pretty hard to predict and I but I think we will get very far even without those advances like we
might get this software solution but it might stop at software and not do computer use without
more innovation so I think that it's like a lot of progress would be coming but in if you're
going to zoom out like there's still ideas in the next 30 years that are going to look like
those in major like scientific innovation that enabled the next chapter of this and I don't know
if it comes in one year or in 15 years yeah well I wonder if the bitter lesson holds true for the
next hundred years with that looks like if scaling laws are fundamental and deep learning I think
the bitter lesson will always apply which is compute will become more abundant but even within
abundant compute the ones that have a steeper scaling loss loop or a better offset like this
is a 2d plot of performance and compute and like even if there's more compute available the ones
that get a hundred x out of it will win it might be something like literally compute clusters
orbiting earth with solar panels the problem with that is heat dissipation so you get all the
radiation from the sun and you don't have any air to dissipate heat but there is a lot of space to
put clusters there's a lot of solar energy there and you could figure out the heat dissipation
but there is a lot of energy and there probably could be engineering will to solve the heat problem
so there could be is it possible and we should say that it definitely is possible how like there is
is the question that we're basically going to be plateauing this year not in terms of the system
capabilities but what the system capabilities actually mean for human civilization so on the
coding front really nice websites will be built very nice autocomplete very nice way to understand
code bases and maybe help the bug but really just a very nice helper on the coding front
it can help research mathematicians do some math it can help you with shopping it can help you
it could help it's a nice helper it's clipy on steroids what else it may be a good education
tool and all that kind of stuff but computer use turns out extremely difficult to solve
so I'm trying to be I'm trying to frame the cynical case in all these domains where it kind of
there's not a really huge economic impact we realize how costly is the training systems
at every level both the pre-training and the inference how costly the inference is the reasoning
all of that like is that possible and how like there's that do you think when you look at the models
so much obvious things to improve and it take a long time to train these models and to do this
art and that it'll take us with the ideas that we have multiple years to actually saturate in
terms of whatever benchmark or performance we are searching for it might serve very narrow
niches like the average tragedy BT 100 million user might not get a lot of benefit out of this
but it is going to serve different populations by getting better at different things
but I think what everybody's chasing now is the is a general system that's useful to everybody
so okay so if that's not that completo right I think that dream is actually kind of dying
as you talked about with the specialized models where it's like
and multimodal is authentic like video generation is a totally different thing
that dream is kind of dying is a big statement because I don't know if it's dying I don't know
every I don't if you ask the actual fans your lab people they I mean they're still chasing it right
I do think they are still like rushing to get the next model out which will be much better than the
much is a not a relative term but will be better than the previous one and I I can't see them
slowing down I just think the gains will be made or felt more through not only scaling the model
but now fine so I feel like there's a lot of tech that is like well let's just put the better
model in there and better model and better model and now people okay let's also at the same time
improve everything around it to like you know like the engineering of the context and inference
scaling and the big labs will still keep doing that and now also the smaller labs will catch up
with that because now it's just like they are hiring more there will be more people LLMs it's kind
of like you know like a circle they also make them more productive and it's just it's like amplify
I think what we can expect is amplification but not like a change of like a paradigm change
I don't think that is true but everything will be just amplified and amplified and amplified and
I can see that continuing for a long time yeah I guess my saving with the dream is dying depends
on exactly what you think it's going to be doing like cloud code is a general model that can do a
lot of things but it's not like necessarily like it depends a lot on integrations and other things
like I bet cloud code can do a fairly good job of doing your email and the hardest part is
figuring out how to give the information to it and how to get it to be able to send your emails
and stuff like this but that's just kind of like I think it goes back to like what is the
one model to rule everything eat those which is just like a thing in the cloud that
handles your entire digital life and is way smarter than everybody it's like it's operating in a
yeah so it's an interesting leap of faith to go from cloud code becomes that which like in some
ways is there's some avenues for that but I do think that like the rhetoric of the industry is
a little bit different I think the immediate also thing we will feel next as a normal person
using add-ons is will will probably be related to something like also trivial like making figures
right now elements are terrible at making figures is it because we are getting served the
cheap models with very less like less inference compute than behind the scenes maybe some
like there are some cranks we can already get better figures but if you ask today I don't
draw a flow chart of xyz it's most of the time terrible and it is kind of like a very simple
task for a human I think it's almost easier sometimes to draw something then to write something
yeah the multi-modal understanding that's feeling something that is odd that it's not better solved
I think we're not saying one actually obvious thing that we're not actually realizing
it's a gigantic thing that's hard to measure which is making all of human knowledge accessible to
the entire world like we I one of the things that I think is hard to articulate but there's
just a huge difference between google search and an llm like I feel like I can basically ask an
lm anything and get an answer and less is doing less and less and less hallucination and that
means understanding my own life figuring out a career trajectory figuring how to solve the problems
all around me learn about anything through human history that like I feel like nobody's really
talking about that because they just immediately take it for granted that it's just this is awesome
that's why everybody's using it is because you get answers for stuff and like the impact of that
across time like think about this is not just the United States is all across the world like kids
throughout the world being able to learn these ideas like the impact that has across time is
probably that's where the real like G talk about gdp it won't be like a leap it'll be that's how we
get to Mars that's how we build these things that's how we have a million new open a i's all the
kind of innovation that happens from there and that's just this quiet force to permeate everything
right human knowledge i do agree with you and in a sense you make it makes knowledge more accessible
but it also i think depends on what the topic is for something like math in a sense you can ask
it questions it answers but if you want to learn a topic from scratch i think that again like we
talked about this earlier i think the sweet spot is i mean there are really good math textbooks where
someone laid it out linearly and that is like a let's say proven strategy to learn this topic and
it does make sense if you start from zero to ramp up to get like a like a information dense text to
soak it up but then you use the lm to make infinite exercises like you you have problems in a certain
area and or have questions something's uncertain or like you are uncertain about certain things
you ask it to generate example problems you solve them and you have questions and then
maybe you need you need more background knowledge and you ask it to to generate that and i think but
then the it won't give you anything let's say that is not in the the textbook it's just packaging
it differently if that makes sense but then there are things i feel like where it also adds value
in a more i mean timely sense where there is no good alternative besides a human doing it on the
for example if you i don't like let's say you're planning to go to Disneyland and you try to figure out
which tickets to buy for which park when well there is no textbook on that there is no
information then resource on that there's only the sparse internet and then there is a lot of value
in the lm you just ask it it has you have the constraints i'm traveling these in these days i want
to go there and there please figure out what i need when and from where what what it costs and
stuff like that and it is very customized on the fly package and then this is like one of the
thousand examples and exercise personalized personalization is essentially like pulling
information from the sparse internet the non-information dense thing where there is no better
version that exists it just doesn't exist you make it from scratch almost and if it does exist it's
full of speaking of Disney world like full of what would you call it ads slum like you just
it's impossible here you go any city in the world what are the top 10 things to do lm is just
way better to ask than anything in the internet for now that's because they're massively subsidized
and they're going to be paid for by ads i don't want to get it it's coming no oh i hope they're i mean
i'm hoping there's a very clear indication what's in it what's not in that context i did a little
you know that's something i mentioned a few years ago it's like uh i don't know if you are looking for
new running shoe mom is this a coincidence that Nike maybe comes up first maybe maybe not
and but i think there are clear laws around this you have to be clear about that but i think that's
what everyone fears it's like the subtle um you know subtle message in there or something like that
but it also brings us to the topic of i guess ads where i think this was the thing hope me i try to
launch in 2025 and uh just to because i think it's still not uh making money in that other way
right now so that like having really like ads spots in there and then the thing though is they
couldn't because well uh alternatives without ads and people would just flock to the other products
and it also is it's just like crazy how yeah like they're one upping each other spending so much
money to just get the users i think so like some instagram ads i don't use instagram but i understand the
appeal of paying a platform to find users who will genuinely like your product and that is the
best case of things like instagram ads but there are also plenty of cases where advertising is very
awful for incentives and i think that a world where the power of AI can integrate with that
positive view of like i am a person and i have a small business and i want to make the best i don't
know damn steak knives in the world and i want to sell them to somebody who needs them and if like
if AI can make that sort of advertising thing work even better that's very good for the world
especially with like digital infrastructure because that's how like the modern web has been built
but that's not to say like addicting feeds so that you can show people more content
is a good thing so i was like i think that's even what opening i would say is they want to find a way
that can make the monetization upside of ads while still giving their users agency and i'm
personally would think that google is probably going to be better at figuring out how to do this
because they have they already have ad supply and they figure out how to turn this demand in their
Gemini app into useful ads then they can turn it on and somebody will figure i don't know if
i think it's this year but there will be experiments with it i do think about holds companies back
right now is really just that the competition is not doing it it's more like more like a reputation
thing it's just like i think people are just afraid right now like ruining or like losing the
reputation and losing users because it is it would make headlines if someone launched these ads
and most they were great but the first ads won't be great because it's a hard problem that we
don't know how to solve yeah i think also the first version of that will likely be something like
on x like the timeline where you have like a promoted post sometimes in between it would be
something like that where it will say like promoted or something like small and then it will be an
image or something i think right now the promise makes the first move if we go 10 years out the
proposition for ads is that you will make so much money on ads by having so many users that you
can use this to funnel better r&d and make better models which is why like youtube is dominating
the market for any like Netflix is scared of youtube like they have the ad like they make i don't
i pay $28 a month for premium they make at least $28 a month off of me and many other people and
they're just like creating such a dominant position in video so i think that's the proposition which
is that ads can make you have a sustained advantage in what you're spending per user but
there's so much money in it right now that it's like like somebody's starting that flywheel is
scary because it's a long term but uh do you think there'll be some like crazy big moves this year
business-wise like somebody like google or apple acquiring and thropic or something like this
Dario will never sell but we are starting to see some types of consolidation with like
rock for $20 billion and um scale AI for almost 30 billion and countless other deals like this that
they're structured in a way that is actually detrimental to the Silicon Valley ecosystem which is
this sort of licensing deal where not everybody gets brought along rather than a full acquisition
that benefits the rank and file employee by getting their stock vested like that's a big issue for
Silicon Valley culture to address because the startup ecosystem is the lifeblood where
if you get a if you join a startup even if it's not that successful your startup very well might
get acquired on a cheap premium of it and you'll get paid out for this equity and these licensing
deals are essentially taking the top talent a lot of the times i think gerox they deal for gerox
to Nvidia as a reminder to be better to the employees but it is still this antitrust avoiding
thing but i think that this trend of consolidation will continue i've been
me and many smart people i respect have been expecting consolidation to have happened sooner
but it seems like some of these things are starting to turn which but at the same time you have
companies raising ridiculous amounts of money for reasons that you don't like i'm like i don't
know why you're taking that money so it's maybe like mixed this year but some consolidation
pressure is starting what kind of surprising consolidation do you think we'll see she's saying
that's not big his is a never i mean grop is a big one and grop with a q by the way yeah
there's just a lot of startups and there's a very high premium on AI startups so there's a lot of
like there can be a lot of stuff yeah 10 billion range acquisitions which is a really big acquisition
for a startup that was maybe founded a year ago i think main s ai from this company has based in
Singapore that met a founded was founded eight months ago and then had a two billion dollar exit
and i think that there will be some other big like many billion dollar acquisitions like
perplexed yeah people rumored them to apple i think there's a lot of pressure and liquidity in AI
there's pressure on big companies to have outcomes and i would guess that a big acquisition gives
people will be way to then tell the next chapter of that story i mean yeah isn't i guess cursor
we can talk about code and somebody quires cursor they're in such a good position by having so
much user data yeah and we talked about continual learning and stuff they had one of the most
interesting like two sentences in a blog post which is that they had their new composer model
which was a fine tune of one of these large mixture of expert models from china you can know that
by asking gossip or because the model sometimes are fonts in chinese which none of the american
models do and they had a blog post where they're like we're updating the model weights every 90
minutes based on real world feedback from people using it which is like the closest thing to real
world rl happening on a model it's just like in one of their blog posts that's super cool and by
the way i should say i use composer log is one of the benefits it has is just fast i need to try
because everybody says us and there'll be some ipos potentially you think and thropic open AI
xai they can all raise so much money so easily that they don't feel i need to like so long as
fundraising is easy they're not going to ipo because public markets apply pressure i think we're
seeing in china that the ecosystems a little different with both mini max and zi. i
applying for filing ipo paperwork which will be interesting to see how the chinese market reacts
actually would guess that it's going to be like similarly hypey to the us so long as all this is
going and not based on the realities that they're both losing a ton of money i wish more of the
american gigantic AI startups were public because it would be very interesting to see how they're
spending their money and have more insight and also just to give people access to investing in these
because i think that there's some of the most like format like they're the companies of the era
and the tradition is now for some many of the big startups in the us to knock it up like it's
like we're still writing for stripe and it's an ipo but databric definitely didn't they raise
like a series g or something and i just say like it's a kind of a weird equilibrium for the market
where it's like i would like to see these companies go public and evolve in that way that a company
can using ten years from now some of the frontier model companies are still around and thropic open AI
i definitely don't see it to be a winner takes all unless there truly is so algorithmic secret that
one of them finds like less is flywheel because the development path is so similar for all of them
google and open AI have like all the same products and then like and thropics more focused but
when you talk to people it sounds like they're solving a lot of the same problems so i think
and there's offerings that'll spread out there's a lot of it's a very big cake that's being made
that people are going to take money out of i don't want to trivialize it but
so open AI and and thropica primarily lm service providers and some of the other companies like
google and xai linked to x does other stuff too and so it's very possible if AI because more
commodified that the companies that are just providing lm will die i think they will the
advantage they have they have a lot of users and i think they will just pivot i think um
then uh if they figure out it's a like and thropic i think pivot it i don't think they originally
plan to work on code but it happened that they found okay this is like a nice niche and now we
are comfortable in this niche and we push on this niche and i can see the same thing once
maybe let's say hypothetically speaking i i'm not sure it will be true but let's say google
takes all the market share of the general chatbot maybe open AI will be then
focused on some other topic like the there have too many users to go away and foreseeable future
i think i think google is always ready to say hope might be over the AI mode i think that the
question is if the companies can support the valuations i think i'd see the AI companies being
looked at in some ways like a did us azure and gcp are all competing in the same space in all very
successful businesses there's a chance that the api market is so unprofitable that
they go up and down the stack to products and hardware they have so much cash that they can build
power plants and build data centers which is a durable advantage now but there's also just a
reasonable outcome that these apis are so valuable and so flexible for developers that they become
the likes of like it something like a db usb a ws nager also going to have these apis so there's some
like that's a like five or six people competing in the api market is hard so maybe like that's
what it gets squeezed out you mentioned r ip llama is there a path to winning for meta i think nobody
knows they're moving a lot so they're signing licensing deals with black forest labs which is an
image generation or mid-journey or applying main main so i think it's some ways it's on the product
and like consumer facing a i front it's too early to tell i think they have some people that are
excellent and very motivated being close to zarkaburg so i think that there's still a story
ton fold there llama is a bit different where llama was the most focused expression of the organization
and i don't see llama being supported to that extent i think it was a very successful brand for them
so they still might do some part of participation in the open ecosystem or continue the llama brand
into a different surface if you know what llama is you think there's a lot more five
not an open weight one it's interesting i think also just to recap a bit i think i mean llama was the
i would say pioneering open weight model and then llama one two three lot of love but i think then
i think what happened just hypothesizing was speculating i think the leaders at meta like the
upper executive state i think they got really excited about llama because they saw how popular it
was in the community and then i think the problem was trying to let's say monetize the open
i don't monetize the open source but i kind of used the open source to make a bigger splash
in a set like to kind of force it almost it felt forced like developing these very big llama
four models to have like the best like to be on the top of the benchmarks but i don't think the
goal of llama models is to be on top of the benchmarks beating let's say chattrapidio or other
models i think the goal was to have a model that people can use trust modify and ascend it so
that includes having smaller models they don't have to be the best models and what happened was
just these models were of course like the benchmarks suggested they were better than they were
because i think they had like specific models trained on preferences that they perform well
on the benchmarks it's kind of like this overfitting thing to kind of force it to be the best but then
at the same time all they didn't do the small models that people could use anything that no one could
run these big models then and then it was kind of like a weird thing and i think it's just because
people got too excited about headlines pushing the frontier i think and too much like on the
benchmarks and said yeah yeah i think i imploded under political pre like internal political
fighting and misaligned incentives so i think the researchers want to build the best models but there's
a layer of organization and manager that is trying to demonstrate that they do these things and then
there's lots of there's a lot of pieces and rumors were how like some horrible technical decision was
made and how that comes in and it just seems like that kind of got too bad where it all just
crashed out we should we should also like give huge props to Mark Zuckerberg
i think it comes from mark actually from mark Zuckerberg from the top of the leadership saying
open source is important i think that's like that if the the fact that that exists means there
could be a llama five where they learn the lessons from the benchmarking and say we're going to
be GPT OSS and provide really awesome library of open source what people say is that
there's a debate between mark and Alexander Wang who is very bright but much more against open
source and to the extent that he has a lot of influence over the AI or it seems much less likely
because it seems like mark brought him in for like a fresh leadership aid in directing AI
and if the like opener closed is no longer the defining nature of the model i don't expect that
to be a defining argument between mark and Alex like they're both very bright but i just like
i have a hard time understanding all of it because mark wrote this piece in July of
2020 for maybe which was like probably the best blog post at the time saying the case for open source
AI and then July 2025 came around and it was like we're re-evaluating a relationship with open
source so it's just kind of like but i think also the the problem not the problem but i think
well we may have been a bit also too harsh i think and that caused some of that because i think
i mean we as open source developers or the open source community because i think even though
the model was maybe not what everyone hoped for it got a lot of backlash and i think that was a
bit unfortunate because i can see that as a company now they were hoping for positive headlines and
instead of just getting no headlines or not these positive headlines in turn they got negative
headlines and then all it kind of reflected bad on the company and i think that is also something
where it's maybe a spy reaction i was like okay we have not we we tried to do something nice we
tried to give give you something cool like an open source model and now you are like you know
kind of like be negative about us even like like for the company so in that sense it looks like well
maybe then we'll change our mind i guess i don't know yeah that's that's where the
uh the dynamics of discourse on x can lead us as a community astray because sometimes it feels
random people pick the thing they like they don't like maybe you can see the same thing with groc
for one and groc code fast one i don't think vy wise people
well love it publicly but a lot of people use it so if you look to read it and x they don't
really give it praise from the programming community but like they use it and the same thing
with probably with llama i don't understand i don't understand the dynamics of either positive hype
or negative hype i don't understand it i mean the story of one of the stories of 2025 is the US
feeling the gap of llama which is like all the rise of these chinese open weight models to the
point where i'm like that was the single issue i've spent a lot of energy on the last five months
is like trying to do policy work to get the u.s to invest in this it's like tell me the story of
atom atom project is it started as me calling it the american deep seek project which doesn't really
work for dc audiences but it's the story of like what is the most impactful thing i can do with my
career which is that lids chinese open weight models are cultivating a lot of power and there is
a lot of demand for building on these open models especially in enterprises in the us that are
very cagey about these chinese models going to proplexity the atom project american truly open
models as a us based initiative to build and host high quality genuinely open weight ai models
and supporting infrastructure explicitly aimed at competing with and catching up to china's
advancing open source ai ecosystem i think the one sentence summary would be that are two sentences
one is a proposition that open models are going to be an engine for ai research because that is
what people start with therefore it's important to own them and the second one is therefore the us
should be building the best models so that the best researcher happens in the us and the us
companies take the value from being the home of where ai research is happening and without more
investment in open models we have all the plots on the website where it's like quen quen quen quen
and it's all these models that are excellent from these chinese companies that are cultivating
influence in the us in china and internationally and i think the us is spending way more on ai
and the ability to create open models that are half a generation or a generation beyond
but the cutting edge of the closed lapses costs orders of like hundred million dollars which is a lot
of money but not a lot of the money to these companies so therefore we need a centralizing force
of people who want to do this and i think we got signed engagement from people pretty much across
the full stack whether it's policy so there has been support from the administration i don't think
anyone in the like technically in government has like signed it publicly but i know that people that
in the ai policy both in Biden and Trump administration are very supportive of trying to promote open
source models in the us i think for example ai2 got a grant from the nsf for a hundred million
dollars over four years which is like the biggest cs grant the nsf has ever awarded and it's for the
ai2 to attempt to this and i think it's a starting point but the best thing happens when there are
multiple organizations building models because they can cross pollinate ideas and kind of build
this ecosystem like i don't think it just works if it's just moma releasing models to the world
because then you can see moma can go away the same thing applies for ai2 where it's like i can't
be the only one building models and i think that it's like that it becomes a lot of time spent on
talking to people whether they're in policy i know in videos very excited about this i think
jensen long has been specifically talking about the urgency for this and they've changed they've
done a lot more in 2025 where the nematron models are more of a focus they've started releasing some
data along with nvides open models and like very few companies do this especially if nvides size so
like there is there is signs of progress and they're we hear about reflection ai where they say
they're two billion dollar fundraises dedicated to building us open models and i feel like their
announcement tweet is like a reen's like a blog post-celt right and i think that that cultural tide is
starting to turn i think in in july it was when we had like four or five deep-seed caliper
chinese open-weight models in zero from the us and that's that's the moment where it was released
this almost like i guess i have to spend energy on this because nobody else is going to do it
so it takes a lot of it takes a lot of people contributing together and i don't say that
like the atom project isn't like the thing that's helping to move the ecosystem but it's people
like me doing the sort of thing to get the word out do you like the the 2025 american's
a i action plan that includes open source stuff the white house a i action plan includes a dedicated
section titled the encourage open source and open-weight a i defining such models and arguing
that unique value for innovation startups yeah i mean like the a i action plan is a plan but
largely i think it's like maybe the most coherent policy document that has come out of the
administration and i hope that it largely succeeds and i know people that have worked on the a
action plan and the challenge is taking policy and making it real and i have no idea how to do this
as an a i researcher but like like largely a lot of things and that were very real and there's a
huge build out of a i in the country and it's like there are a lot of issues that people are
hearing about from water use to whatever and like we should be able to build things in this country
but also we need to not ruin places in our country in the process building it and it's a worthwhile
to spend energy on i think that's a role that the federal government places like they set the agenda
and with a i setting the agenda that open-weight should be a first consideration is like that's a
large part of what they can do and then people think about it also for education and talent for
these companies it's i think very important because otherwise you know if they're only closed
models how do you get the next generation of people contributing at some point because otherwise
you will at some point only be able to learn after you joined a company but then at that point
like how do you hire talented people how do you identify talented people and i think open source is
that's even a lot of things but also even just for educating the population and training the
next generational researchers it's the way or the only way the way that i could have gotten this
to more go more viral is was to tell a story of chinese ai integrating with an authoritarian state
in being as i and taking over the world and therefore we need our own american models but it's very
intentional for why i talk about innovation and science in the us because i think it's
both more realistic as an outcome but just like it's like it's a world that is so blank to manifest
i would say though also even like let's say any open weight model i do think is a variable model
yeah i'm i mean as that we should be in a leading position but i think that it's
worth saying it's so simply because there are still voices in the AI ecosystem that's
say we should consider banning releasing open models due to the safety risks and i think it's worth
adding that i think effectively that's impossible without making the us like it have its own
great firewall which is also known to not work that well because the cost for training these models
whether it's one to a hundred million dollars is attainable to a huge amount of people in the
world that want to have influence so these models will be getting trained all over the world and
these we want the models especially when like i mean there are safety concerns but we want these
information and tools to flow freely across the world and into the us so that we people can use
them and learn from them and we like stopping that would be such a restructuring of our internet that
it seems impossible do you think maybe in that case the big open weight models from china are actually
a good thing in a sense like for the us companies because maybe the us companies you you mentioned
earlier they are usually one generation behind in terms of what they release open source versus what
they are using for example gpto ss might not be the cutting edge model jema three might not be
but they do that because they know this is safe to release but then when they see these come at gc for
example there is deep seek version 3.2 which is really awesome and it gets used and there is no
backlash there is no security risk that could then again encourage them to release better models maybe
that that in a sense is a very positive thing a hundred percent these chinese companies have set
things into motion that i think would potentially not have happened if they were not all releasing
models so i think it is like i'm i'm almost sure that those discussions have been had by leadership
is there a possible future where the dominant models and models in the world are all open source
depends on the trajectory of progress that you predict if you think saturation and progress is
even coming within a few years so essentially within the time where financial support is still
very good then open models will be so optimized and so much cheaper to run that they will want out
essentially this goes back to open source ideas where so many more people will be putting money into
optimizing the serving of these open weight common architectures that they will become standards
and then you could have chips dedicated to them and it'll be way cheaper than the
offerings from these close companies that are custom we should say that AI 27 report kind of
predicts one of the things it does from a narrative perspective is that there will be a lot of
centralization as the AI system gets smarter and smarter the national security concerns will
come to be and you'll centralize the labs and you'll become super secretive and there'll be this
whole race from a military perspective of how to you between china and united states and so all
of this fun conversations we're having about it lambs all the generals the soldiers will come into
the room and be like all right we're now in the Manhattan project stage of this whole thing
I think 2025 627 I don't think something like that is even remotely possible I mean you can make
the same argument for computers right you can say okay computers are capable and we don't want the
general public to get them or chips even AI chips but you see how like you know Huawei makes chips
not you know took a few years but and I think that I don't think there is a way you can contain
something like that like knowledge like that I think in this day and eight age it is impossible
like the internet I don't think this is a possibility on the minhaven project thing one of my
funny things making out of them is I think that like a minhaven project like thing for open models
would actually be pretty reasonable because I wouldn't cost that much but I think that that will come
it seems like culturally the companies are changing but I agree with Sebastian all the
stuff they just said it's like I don't see it happening nor being helpful yeah I mean the
the motivating force behind them in Manhattan projects is there a civilizational risk
I it's harder to motivate that for open source models there's not civilization over risk
you think on the hardware side we mentioned Nvidia a bunch of times do you think
Janssen and Nvidia are gonna keep burning I think they have the downside that they have to iterate a lot
and manufacture a lot and I think they probably what they're doing they do innovate but I think
there's always the chance that there is something who does something fundamentally different who gets
very lucky and then does something but the problem is I think adoption you know like the the
mode of Nvidia is probably not just the GPU it's more like the CUDA ecosystem and that has evolved
over so many times in two decades I think I mean even back when I was a grad student we I wasn't a
lab we did biophysical simulations molecular dynamics and we had a Tesla GPU back then just for
the computation it was bar in 15 years ago now and just they built this up for a long time and
that's like that's the mode I think it's not the chip itself although they have now the money to
iterate and build and scale but then it's really on the compatibility it's like well if you're at
that scale as a company why would you go with something risky where it's only a few chips that
they can make per year you go with a big one but then I do think with LLMs now also it will be
easier to design something like CUDA you know like the next so it took 15 years because it's hard but
then now we have LLMs we can maybe replicate CUDA and I wonder if there will be a separation of
the training and the inference compute as we kind of stabilize a bit more and more and more more
computers needed for inference that's supposed to be the point of the crock acquisition
and that's why part of what Vera Ruben is where they have a new chip with no high band with memory
which is one of or very little which is one of the most expensive pieces it's designed for
pre-fill it's just the part of inference where you essentially do a lot of matrix multiplications
and then you only need the memory when you're doing this auto regressive generation you have the KV
cache swaps so they have this new GPU that's designed for that specific use case and then the cost
of ownership per flop or whatever is actually way lower but I think that Nvidia's fate lies in the
diffusion of AI still their biggest clients are still these hyper scale companies whether it's like
Google obviously can make TPUs Amazon is making training Microsoft will try to do its own
things and like so long as the pace of AI progress is high Nvidia's platform is the most flexible
and people will want that but if they're stagnation then creating the spoke chips there's more time
to do it is it is it is quite active in trying to develop all kinds of different products they
tried to create areas of commercial value that will use a lot of GPUs but they keep innovating and
they're doing a lot of incredible research so everyone says the company is super oriented around
Jensen and how operationally plugged in he is and it sounds so unlike many other big companies that
I've heard about and so long as that's the culture I think that I will expect them to keep progress
happening and it's like he's still in the Steve Jobs era of Apple so long as that is how it operates
I'm pretty optimistic for their situation because it's like it is their top order problem and I
don't know if making these chips for the Holy Ghost system is the top goal of all these other
companies they will do a good job but it might not be as good of a job since you mentioned Jensen
I've been reading a lot about history and both singular figures in history what do you guys think
about the single man woman view of history how important their individuals for steering the
direction of history in the tech sector so you know what's in video without Jensen you might
just Steve Jobs what's Apple with Steve Jobs what's XAI without Elon or DeepMind with Autodemis
people make things earlier and faster where scientifically many great scientists credit to being
the right place at the right time and still making the innovation where eventually someone else will
still have the idea so I think that in that way Jensen is helping manifest this GPU revolution
much faster and much more focused than without having a person there it would do and this is
making the whole AI build out faster but I do still think that eventually like something like
ChatGPT would have happened and a build out like this would have happened but it probably would not
have been as fast or like as like I think that's the sort of flavor that is applied people these
individual people to are people who are placing bets on something some get lucky some don't but if
you don't have these people at the helm it would be more diffused it's almost like investing in a
ETF versus individual stocks individual stocks might go up might go down more heavily than an ETF
which is more balanced it will eventually go up over time we'll get there but it's just like you
know what a focus I think is the thing a passionate focus isn't a real case to be made that without
Jensen there's not a reinvigoration of the deep learning revolution it could have been 20 years
later is something that it's like a deep learning winter could have come if GPUs weren't around
that could change history completely because you could think of all the other technologies that
that could have come in the meantime and the focus of human civilization could still come value
be captured by different hype but I do think that this I mean there's certainly an aspect where it
was all planned or the GPU trajectory but on the other end it's also a lot of lucky coincidences for
example or good intuition like the investment into this let's say biophysical simulations or like
I mean I think it started with video games and then it just happened to be good at linear algebra
because video games require a lot of linear algebra and then you have the biophysical simulations
and then but still I don't think the plan the master plan was AI I think there was just it happened
to be Alex Krzyszewski so someone took these GPUs and like let's try to train a neural network
on that and happen to work really well and I think it only happened because you could purchase
those GPUs gaming would have created a demand for faster processors if Nvidia had gone out of business
in the early days that's what I would think like I think that the GPUs would have been different
for the Alex but I think like GPUs would still exist at the time of Alex net and at the time of
the transformer it was just hard to know if it would be one company as successful or multiple
smaller companies with worse chips but I don't think that's like a hundred year delay it might be
a decade delay well it could be one two three four five decade delay I mean I just can't see
Intel or AMD doing what in video I don't think it would be a company that exists I think it would
be a different company would write silicon graphics or something so yeah some company that has died
would have done it but it does like just looking at it it seems like these singular figures these
leaders have a huge impact on the trajectory of the world obviously incredible teams behind them
but you know having that kind of very singular almost dogmatic focus is necessary to make progress
yeah I mean even with a GPT it wouldn't exist if there wasn't a person ilia who pushed for the
scaling right I mean Dario is also deeply involved in that they read some of the histories of open AI
it almost seems wild picking about how early these people are like we need to hook up 10,000
GPUs and take all of open AI's compute and train one model there's a lot of people there that
didn't want to do that which isn't an insane thing to believe that to believe scaling before scaling
has any indication that it's going to materialize again singular figures speaking of which
how did years from now this is presumably post singularity whatever singularity is
when historians look back at our time now what technological breakthroughs would they really emphasize
as the breakthroughs that led to the singularity so far we have touring today 80 years I think it
would still be computing like the umbrella term computing just I don't necessarily think it's even
like 100 years 200 years from now it would be I it would it could be still well-being computers you know
just we are now taking better advantage of computers but like the fact of computing it's basically
more as a law kind of discussion you're not even the details of code and GPUs won't even be remembered
and it won't be all this software term oil it'll be just obviously compute I've generally
agreed but it's like is the connectivity of the internet and compute able to be merged
or is that both of them I think the internet will probably relate to yeah I mean communication
that it could be the phone internet satellite that stuff where yeah when compute is more like
the scaling aspect of it is possible that the internet is completely forgotten the internet is
wrapped into the phone networks like communication networks this is just another
manifestation of that and the real breakthrough comes from the just the increased compute is the
Moore's law broadly defined well I think that connection of people is very fundamental to it so it's
you can talk to anybody you want to find the best person in the world or something they are
somewhere in the world and being able to have that flow of information the AI's will also rely on
I think I've been fixating on the lake the when I said the dream was dead about the one central
model and the thing that is evolving is like people have many agents for different tasks people
are start doing this with different clouds for different tasks and it's described as many
AGI's in the data center where each one manages and they talk to each other and I
That is wrote so reliant on networking and free flow of information on top of compute but like
networking especially with GPUs is such a part of scaling up compute like the GPUs and the data
centers need to talk to each other anything about neural networks will be remembered like do you
think there's something very specific and singular to the fact that it's neural networks that
seen as a breakthrough like a genius that you're basically replicating in a very crude way the human
mind the structure the structure of the human brain the human mind I think without the human mind we
probably wouldn't have neural networks because it just was an inspiration for that but at the other
and I think it's just still so different I mean it's digital versus you know biological that I do
think it will probably be more like grouped as an algorithm that's massively parallelizable on this
particular kind of compute could have been like genetic computing like genetic genetic algorithms
just this paralyzed thing it just happens that this is more efficient works better you know and
it very well could be that the LLM you know the neural networks the way we architect them now it's
just a small component of the system that leads to singularity I think if you think of it a hundred
years like society I think can be changed more with more compute intelligence because of autonomy but
it's like looking at looking at this like what are the things from the industrial revolution that
we remember we remember like the engine is probably the equivalent of the computer in this but there's
a lot of other like physical transformations that people are aware of like like all the
congen and all these things that these machines that are still known air conditioning refrigerators like
some of these things from AI will still be known like the word transformer could still very well be
known I would guess the deep learning is definitely still learned known but the transformer might be
evolved away from in a hundred years of with ASIA I researchers everywhere but I think deep learning is
likely to be a term that is remembered and I wonder what the air conditioning and the
refrigeration of the future is that AI brings is there if we travel forward a hundred years from now
we transport there right now what do you think is different how do you think the world looks different
first of all you think there's humans you think there's robots everywhere walking around I do think
specialized robots for sure for certain tasks humanoid form that I'm maybe half humanoid
we'll see I think for certain things yes there will be humanoid robots because it's just
amenable for the environment but like for certain tasks it might make sense what's harder to imagine
is how we interact with devices and what humans do with devices will I mean I'm pretty sure
will probably not be the cell phone will probably not be the laptop will it be you know implants
I mean it has to be brain computers yeah I mean a hundred years from now it has to like given the
progress we're seeing now there has to be unless there's legitimately complete alteration of how we
interact with the reality on the other hand if you think of cars cars are older than 100 years
and it's still the same interface it's not we haven't replaced cars with something else we just
made the cars better but it's still steering wheel it's still wheels you know I think we will
still carry around a physical break of compute because people want some ability to have a
private like you might not engage with it as much as a phone but having something where you can
have private information that is yours as an interface between the rest of the internet I think
is something that people will still exist it might not look like an iPhone it might be used a
lot less but I still expect to have people carry things around why do you think the smartphone is
the embodiment of private does a camera on it um private for you like encrypted messages encrypted
photos you know what your life is like I guess this is a question on whether how optimistic on brain
machine interfaces you are if the is all that just going to be stored in the cloud in your whole
calendar like it's hard to think about processing all the information that we can process visually
through brain machine interfaces presenting something like a calendar or something to you like
it's hard to just think about knowing without looking you know your email inbox like you
signal to a computer and then you just know your email inbox like what does that like is that
something that the human brain can handle being piped into it non visually like I don't
know exactly how those transformations happen because humans aren't changing in a hundred years
I think agency and community are things that people actually want local community so people you
are close to being able to do things with them and being able to ascribe mean like describe
meeting to your life and to build to do things I think that that is maybe if not in a hundred years
don't think that human biology is changing away from those on a time scale that we can discuss
and I think that like UBI does not solve agency I do expect mass wealth and I hope that it is spread
so that the average life does look very different in a hundred years but that's still a lot to
happen in a hundred years if you think about countries that are early in their development process
to getting access to computing and internet like to build all the infrastructure and to have
policy that shares one nation's wealth with another is I think it's an optimistic view to see
all that happening in a hundred years while that is still being well they are still independent
entities and not just like absorbed into some international order by force but there could be just
better more elaborate more effective social support systems that help alleviate some levels of
basic suffering from the world you know the transformation of society where a lot of jobs are
lost in the short term I think we have to really remember that each individual job that's lost
is a human being who's suffering that's like when jobs are lost at scales are real tragedy
you can make all kinds of arguments about economics or it's all going to be okay it's good for the
GDP there's going to be new jobs created fundamental to the individual level for that human being
that's that's real suffering that's a real personal sort of tragedy and we have to not forget that
as the technology is being developed and also my my hope for all the AI slot we're seeing
is that there will be a greater and greater premium for the the fundamentals aspects of the
human experience that are like in person the things that we all like seeing each other talking
together in person the next few years are definitely going to be an increased value on
physical goods and events and even more pressure on slop so there'll be so there'll keep the
slop is only starting the next few years will be more and we'll be drowning in slop as I'm hoping
that we society drowns in slop enough to snap out of it and be like we can't like none like it
just doesn't matter we all can't deal with it and then like the physical has such a higher premium
on it even like classic examples I honestly think this is true and I think we get tired of it we
are already kind of tired of it same with I mean even art I don't think art will go away
mean you have paintings physical paintings there's more value not just monetary value but just
more value appreciation for something that is the actual painting then a photocopy of that painting
it could be a perfect digital reprint of that but there is something when you go to a museum and
you look at that art and you see that real thing and you think about okay human I know it's like a
craft you have like appreciation for that and I think the same is true for writing for talking
any type of experience where it will be I do unfortunate thing it will be like a dichomed like
it will be like a fork where more some things will be automated like you know they're not as many
paintings as they used to be 200 years ago they're more more photographs more photocopies but at the same
time it won't go away there will be a you know value in that I think that the difference will just be
a bit you know what's the proportion of that but personally I I have a hard time reading things where
I obviously see it's obviously AI generated I'm I'm sorry it might be really good information
there but I have like a certain nah not for me I think eventually they'll fool you and it'll be
on platforms that give ways of verifying or building trust so you will trust that likes it's not
AI generated having been here so then you have trust in this channel but it's harder for
new people than don't have that trust well that that will get interesting because I think for
now mentally I think it's a solvable problem by having you know trust in certain outlets that
they won't do it but it's all going to be kind of trust based there will be some systems to authorize
okay this is real this is not real there will be some tell tell tell science where you can
obviously tell this is AI generated and this is not but they want I mean some will be so good
that it's hard to tell and then you have to trust and I'm on that that that will get interesting
and a bit problematic the extreme case of this is to watermark all human content so all photos
that we take on our own have some watermark until they are edited or something like this in software
can manage communications with the device manufacturer to maintain a human editing which is the
opposite of the discussion to try to watermark AI images and then you can make a Google image
has a watermark and use a different Google tool to remove the watermark yeah it's going to be
Thomas Ray's decision yeah and we've been most focusing on the positive aspects of AI I mean there's
also the the all the capabilities we've been talking about can be used to destabilize human civilization
with even just relatively dummy AI applied at scale and then further and further super intelligent
AI systems of course there's the sort of do more take that's important to consider a little bit
as we develop these technologies well gives you hope about the future of human civilization
everything we've been talking about are we going to be okay I think we we will I'm definitely a
warrior both about AI and non AI things but humans that do tend to find a way I think that's what
humans are built for is to have community and find a way to figure out problems and that's what
has gotten us to this point and I think that the AI opportunity in related technologies is really big
and I think that when there's big social and political problems to help everybody understand that
and I think that's what we're staring at a lot of right now it's like the world is a scary place
and AI is a very uncertain thing and it takes a lot of work that is not necessarily building things
it's like telling people and understanding people that the people building AI are historically not
motivated or wanting to do but it is something that is probably doable just will take
longer than people want we have to go through that long period of like hard to straw AI
discussions if we want to have the lasting benefits yeah through that process I'm especially excited
that we get a chance to better understand ourselves also at the individual levels humans and at the
civilization level the answer some of the big mysteries like what is this whole like
consciousness thing going on here seems to be truly special like there's a real miracle in our
mind and AI puts a merit ourselves and get to answer some little bit questions about like what
is this whole thing going on here well one thing about that is also what I do think makes us very
different from AI and why I don't worry about AI taking over is like you said consciousness
we humans we decide what we want to do AI in its current implementation I can't see a changing
you have to tell it what to do and so you have still the agency it doesn't take the agency from
you because you have to you just it becomes a tool you can think of it as a tool do you tell it what
to do it will be more automatic than other previous tools it's certainly more powerful than a hammer it
can figure things out but it's still you in in in in charge right so the AI is not in charge you
and charge you tell the AI what to do and it's doing it for you so in the post singularity post
apocalyptic war between humans and machines you're saying humans are worth fighting for
under percent I mean this is the movie Terminator they made the 80s essentially and I do think
well the only thing I can see going wrong is of course if things I explicitly programmed to do
the thing that is harmful basically I think actually in that in the Terminator type of setup I think
human win mm-hmm I think we're too clever um it's hard to explain how we figured it out but we do
and we'll probably be using local LLM's open source LLM to help fight the machines
I apologize for the ridiculousness like I said Nathan really knows I'm gonna a big fan of his for
a long time been a big fan of yours Suresh for a long time so it's an honor to finally meet you
thank you for everything you put out into the world thank you for the excellent books you're writing
thank you for teaching us and thank you for talking today this was fun thank you for inviting us
here and having this human connection which is extremely valuable human connection thanks for listening
to this conversation with Sureshka and Nathan Lambert to support this podcast please check
out our sponsors in the description where you can also find links to contact me ask questions
give feedback and so on and now let me leave you with some words from Albert Einstein
it is not that I'm so smart but I stay with the questions much longer thank you for listening
and hope to see you next time
you